<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Foure sermons of Maister Iohn Caluin entreating of matters very profitable for our time, as may bee seene by the preface: with a briefe exposition of the LXXXVII. Psalme. Translated out of Frenche into Englishe by Iohn Fielde.</title>
            <title>Quatre sermons avec exposition du Pseaume 87. English</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 236 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107288</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842990</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842990</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7693</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17694)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7693)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 416:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Foure sermons of Maister Iohn Caluin entreating of matters very profitable for our time, as may bee seene by the preface: with a briefe exposition of the LXXXVII. Psalme. Translated out of Frenche into Englishe by Iohn Fielde.</title>
                  <title>Quatre sermons avec exposition du Pseaume 87. English</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>Fielde, John, d. 1588.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 59, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Thomas Dawson] for Thomas Man, dwelling in Pater Noster Rowe, at the signe of the Talbot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Quatre sermons avec exposition du Pseaume 87.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in foliation.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXXXVII --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
               <term>Reformed Church --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Foure</hi> SERMONS OF <hi>Maister Iohn Caluin,</hi> Entreating of matters very <hi>profitable for our time, as may <hi>bee ſeene by the</hi>
               </hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face:</p>
            <p>With a briefe expoſition of the <hi>LXXXVII. Pſalme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Frenche into Engliſhe by <hi>Iohn Fielde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Jmprinted at London</hi> for Thomas Man, dwelling <hi>in Pater Noſter Rome, at the</hi> Signe of the Talbot. 1579.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:2"/>
            <head>To the right <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and my verie good Lorde, Henry</hi> Earle of Huntington, Lord Haſtings, Hungerford, Botreaux, Mullens and Moyles, of <hi>the moſt Honorable order of the Garter Knight, and Lorde</hi> Preſident of the Queenes Maieſties Councell eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the North partes, <hi>Iohn Fielde</hi> wiſheth <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of true faith and continuance in the zeale of his bleſſed religion for euer Amen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may bee (right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; my very good Lord) that men will maruayle, whye I ſhoulde publiſhe theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> excellente Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of Maiſter Iohn Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, the Argumentes whereof bee not ſo fitte and agreeable (as they thinke) to theſe times: ſeeing GOD in mercy hath geuen vs peace, and ſet vs at libertie from that Romiſh yoke, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fering the beames of his glorious Goſpel to ſpread far and wide, to the great comfort of many, and his owne euerlaſting glory. Theſe benefits, as they are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by me: ſo I beſeech God to make vs all more thankfull then we haue beene, that the litle fruite they haue brought foorth amongeſt vs, the common igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that is yet vpon the face of the whole lande, the ſmall preparation to the croſſe and bending our backs too beare it with Ieſus Chriſte our head, doe not prouoke him too geue vs ouer too followe our owne wayes, to haue no conſcience nor care of any religion: as I feare me the worlde is too to ful of ſuch, the more
<pb facs="tcp:7693:3"/> is the pitie. For who ſeeth not, that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort are ſo far from being inſtructed, hauing plaide the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antes in Gods Schole theſe twenty and odde yeeres, that they haue not yet taken out this one leſſon, to bee of minde when God ſhall trie them, too ſeparate them ſelues from the curſed fellowſhip of Antichriſte. For they haue not yet learned too make any difference of religion, but bende them ſelues too ſerue all times: come there falſhood or trueth, light or darkneſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or ſuperſtition, the Goſpell or the Maſſe, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme or Chriſtianiſme, al is one too them, ſo that they may liue at eaſe, they are at a point: no Scripture ſo ſtrong, or teſtimonie ſo euident, that can conuince them, too make them ſtand faſt too Gods euerlaſting trueth, the ſeale of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir adoption. Though Chriſte haue pronounced that whoſoeuer denye him before men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.33.38.</note> hee wyll denie him before his father which is in heauen: though he ſay playnely that hee that will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe him muſt take vp his croſſe and followe him, and that he that is aſhamed too confeſſe him before men,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18.4.</note> he wil deny him before his heauenly father: yea although we bee commaunded too come out of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13.3.11.</note> and it be plainely ſaide that the red Dragon will powre out his waters as a riuer to ouertake the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with childe, and that the victorie of the lambe muſte be by his own blood, &amp; by the word of their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, who loue not their liues vntoo the death: yet can not all this mooue them to ſeeke too be grounded and prepared, calling vpon God that they may ſtand reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute through his grace, to beare teſtimonie to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name, who hath beſtowed ſo many bleſſings vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. If they may haue Chriſte with caſe, wealth, honour, with the peace of the worlde and fauour of
<pb facs="tcp:7693:3"/> men, if they may inioy him with their pleaſures and proceeding on in ſinne, they wil be content with Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees a litle to entertaine him, that they make a mock of him. But if in the entertaining of him, he ſhal neuer ſo litle touch their botch and pinch theyr pleaſure: if hee ſhall come neare their purſe and endanger theyr leaſt commoditie, if he ſhal require mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with obedience &amp; ſanctification, then either they wil come by night like Nicodemus, or elſe they wil pray him to be packing with the Gergeſites, or too conclude they wil lay violent hands vpon him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.3. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 11.47. <hi>Mark.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14.64 15.12.</note> and naile him faſt to the croſſe with the proude Scribes and Phariſees. As for the common ſort they that yeſterday receiued him as a king, with <hi>oſianna in excelſis,</hi> they wil to morow cry out <hi>Crucifige,</hi> with the high Prieſts, that they may liue in ſecuritie. Theſe ſermons therefore as for their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe they haue been tranſlated long agoe into other tongues, and (as I vnderſtoode, when I had almoſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed them) out of the Latine into ours alſo: ſo my labour being paſt, they being alſo by authoritie allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and I eſpecially following maiſter Caluines owne french copie, ſo what differing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other: I thought they coulde not but be very profitable, at the leaſte too prepare vs againſt the time to come. For God hath geuen vs long peace, and our reſt hauing bred ruſt, gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vp eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the height of the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of his graces, muſt needes prouoke him to puniſh the wicked with wonted plagues &amp; to correct vs with the fire of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, that we may be purged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our foule corruption. Our cold ſtarued Papiſtes, I cannot tel what warmeth hath drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of their holes, but now they begin a litle to ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, they loke big, &amp; their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging looks ſhew what malice lurketh in their ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kred harts:
<pb facs="tcp:7693:4"/> But our God liueth and therefore wee will not feare, we know that all powers both in heauen and in earth are ſubiect to him: and we nothing doubt though our ſinnes haue ſtrengthened the handes of his aduerſaries, that they ſhoulde be heauy vpon vs, yet our God will in our puniſhmentes geue them an euerlaſting ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and an vnrecouerable confuſion. Though there be many Newters which haue made a couenant with their owne heartes rather to be of all religions, and to ſerue al times, then to endure the leaſt danger, yet there are an infinite number of true Chriſtians, that by his grace to die for it, will neuer bow the Knee too Baall, will neuer pertake with the table of God and the table of deuilles,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kinges.</hi> 19.</note> will neuer draw in that vnequall yoke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather with ſuch Infidelles. Theſe ſhal neither the ſwoordes of Hazael, nor of Ichu, or of Eliſha once touch, for they are marked of the Lorde. And if the woorde of God be ſure as him ſelfe, and hee haue ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelfe as head too vs his members, why ſhoulde we feare? If our head liue we ſhall liue, if he be aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, we his members ſhalbe drawen vp vnto him. Our blood ſhalbe of ſtrength too breake all their cheines. The ſhame, ſlaunder and reproche that they lay vpon vs, ſhalbe our greateſt glory, and our innocency laide to theyr crueltie, ſhalbe ſtrong enough to ſet the ſeale of true happineſſe vpon vs for ſuffering for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſake, and of wretched confuſion vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſo rage againſt ſuch as haue done the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no harme,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.10.</note> and who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ought too haue moſt eſteemed of, as for whoſe ſakes they haue &amp; poſſeſſe al thoſe temporall bleſſings that god in his mercy hath geuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. We wil there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the name of our God, likewiſe Marriners, in this calme time prouide againſt ſtormes and tempeſts.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:4"/> We are not ignorant what the order of nature ſetteth before vs: there is no ſommer but bringeth a Winter, no day but hath a night: nor any profeſſed trueth that bringeth not a tryall. Health is alwayes ioyned with ſickneſſe, and the bodily life is ſubiect to death: ſo the peace of the Church is ſeldome without aduerſitie: &amp; GOD forbid that we ſhoulde not prepare, euen to the powring foorth of our blood, to ſtriue for the trueth of our God, yea too death it ſelfe, if God ſo appointe. If they be (as Chryſoſtom ſaith) not onely betraiers of the trueth that ſpeake lyes in ſteede of the trueth, but alſo that doo not freely vtter the trueth: God forbid that wee ſhoulde not be ready in time and place when he willeth, both to vtter it freely, and to ſtande too it valiauntly and conſtantly for the glory of his name. And one thing I doe aſſure the Papiſtes of and all of Caynes progenie, that the more they kil and perſecute the children of God, the more wil Chriſt &amp; his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell flooriſh. Our blood wilbe a fructifiyng &amp; multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliyng ſeede, they haue ſeene it and knowen it true by long experience, &amp; herein they be but the inſtruments of haſtening vs too our happineſſe. Not when they will, for we are not ſubiect vnto them. The Deuil him ſelfe their Father and all helliſhe furyes are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect too our God, and cannot touch one heare of our heades, tyll he haue geuen them leaue and that for our good and tryall. Let the ſonnes therefore of ſeruitude in the pride of bondage ieare neuer ſo muche againſt the ſonnes of libertie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.</note> yet a day ſhall come when their righteouſneſſe ſhall breake foorth and appeare more glorious then the Sunne and all the Starres: when as too them (what pleaſures ſoeuer they ſhall vſurpe in this world) ſhall belong nothing but perpetuall
<pb facs="tcp:7693:5"/> ſhame, ioyned with an euill name too all poſterities, and an euerlaſting death in the ende worlde without ende. Wherefore (good my Lorde) I am bolde too offer vp theſe ſermons vnto your honour, rudely tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated by me, beſeeching your honour in the behalfe of Gods Church to accept of them. I will ſay nothing in their commendation, they are able and of ſufficient age to ſpeake for themſelues. Onely I thought good to ſhew this humble duetie towards you, by this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique teſtimonie. And I beſeech God the father of all mercies to ſtrengthen you in that happy courſe of the Goſpel, wherinto of his ſinguler goodneſſe hee hath drawen you: that you may be as a bright ſtarre in his Churche comfortably ſhining forth in conſtancie and maintenance of the ſame trueth, too the ſtirring vp of many: that not onely it may be geuen you (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaieth) to beleeue in him, but alſo too ſuffer for him. For this is true honour too ſuffer for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: The cauſe is it that muſt comfort all that are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and herein we haue wonderfully to reioyce, when it is for his name ſake, herevnto alſo, wee muſt (as I haue ſaid) prepare our ſelues. For it is impoſſible that Chriſte and his Croſſe ſhoulde bee ſundred. The worlde muſte loue her owne, and in the worlde wee ſhalbe troubled. Chriſt in his members muſt be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied til he come againe in his ſecond &amp; glorious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to ſubdue all his enimies. The remainder of his afflictions muſt bee borne in our bodies, not becauſe hee hath not ſuffered fully, but becauſe wee muſte bee made conformable vnto him, till wee bee fined from the droſſe that is in vs, too deteſt it and wholly too loue his righteouſneſſe. Wherfore we muſte deteſt all thoſe Libertines, who count themſelues the Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:7693:5"/> of Loue, and the Atheiſtes of the worlde, who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe all confeſſion and profeſſion of the Faith of Chriſte, beeing indifferent for all religions: that tread vnder their feete the blood of all Martyres, and account them but for fooles. Nowe the God of all patience and comfort, bleſſe your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor togeather with my good Lady, that you may feele and poſſeſſe that comfort that none can take from you. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt bounden</hi> and Faythfull euer to commaunde, <hi>IOHN FIELDE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:6"/>
            <head>¶ Iohn Caluin to all true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>who deſire the aduancement of</hi> the kingdome of our Lorde <hi>Ieſus Chriſte.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen you ſhall vnderſtande wherfore and to what ende, I was deſirous too publiſhe theſe Sermons, and ſhall bee aduertiſed of the Argument which they conteine, you ſhall know the better howe too make your profite of them, and to apply them to ſuche vſe as I haue appointed them. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that I haue written heeretofore two Treatiſes large enough, to ſhew that it is not lawful for a Chriſtian, knowing the pure doctrine of the Goſpell, when he liueth in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, too diſſemble howſoeuer it be, to conſent or to cleaue vnto the abuſes, ſuperſtitions and Idolatries, which raigne there: Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding there are euery day ſome people that demaund my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel therof a freeſh, as if I had neuer ſpoken therof. I vnderſtand alſo that there are others which neuer ceaſe to alleage their replies, &amp; haue new ſtarti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g holes agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt that which I haue written thereof. Therefore to cut of al oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, aſwel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe which iniquire of that which ought to be ſufficiently knowen &amp; vnderſtoode of them, as alſo from them which thinke to couer themſelues vnder this wet ſacke from the vengeance of God: I thought that it ſhoulde be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expedient to reuiew ouer againe and to bring into order a Sermon that I had made as touching this matter, the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me whereof had beene gathered. Wherefore this firſt Sermon conteineth an admonition, what a ſlouthfulnes it is in them too whom God hath geuen to know the trueth of his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, too defile themſelues with the abhominations of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, the which are altogeather contrary too Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, foraſmuche as in ſo doyng, they deny as muche as lyeth in them, the ſonne of GOD who hath redeemed them.</p>
            <p>Nowe becauſe that it is impoſſible for a Chriſtian man dwelling vnder the tyranny of Antichriſte, too make a right
<pb facs="tcp:7693:6"/> and pure confeſſion of his faith, but that incontinent hee muſt bee in daunger to be perſecuted, I haue adioyned ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecond Sermon, for to exhort all the faithfull, more too eſteeme the honor and ſeruice of God then theyr owne life, and to fortifie themſelues againſt all temptations. And in deede whereas many thinke it ſtrange that they be not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to diſguiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; to play the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfaites, it is not, for that they are not conuinced, that the duetie of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God is too worſhip him onely in all plaineſſe and ſimplicitie, withdrawing themſelues from all pollutions and Idolatry: but it is, becauſe they ſee they cannot doe the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Chriſtians, but they muſt kindle the rage of the wicked againſt them. Nowe they woulde flye the croſſe as muche as they coulde, I therefore ſeeing that the doctrine of the pure worſhipping God ſhoulde be altogeather vnprofitable, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that men be ſetled to deſpiſe this brickle &amp; tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitory life, too ſeeke the kingdome of God and to follow Ieſus Chriſte to the Croſſe, to come vnto the glory of his reſurrection: I haue added the ſecond ſermon to exhort them which at this day are ouer weake to courage and conſtancie.</p>
            <p>The thirde Sermon is too declare what a treaſure it is to haue libertie not onely to ſerue God purely and too make publique confeſſion of his faith: but alſo to be in a well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and gouerned Churche, where the woorde of God is preached and the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are adminiſtred as they ought: ſeeing that theſe are the meanes by which the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god may ſtrengthen themſelues in the faith, and bee ſtirred vp too liue and to die in his obedience. Now it ſeemed vntoo me that this Argument was very neceſſary at this day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are many Chriſtians in immagination, whiche flout at them which take paine to goe into a ſtraunge coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and farre of to enioy ſuch libertie,</p>
            <p>Now becauſe there are many withholden and hindred from following of this benefite which God ſo muche eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, for the too great regard that they haue to their eaſe &amp; commodities: or rather for the feare and doubt which they haue, that any thing ſhoulde be wanting vnto them: and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:7693:7"/> are ſo delicate that if all fall not out to their deſire, they whine and murmure, or rather fall to playne wickedneſſe: I haue added the fourth Sermon too ſhew vnto Chriſtians how they ought to be armed againſt al offences, patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly too beare al the troubles that may happen vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that God geue them this grace to mainteine them in his houſe. So the ſumme of the fourth Sermon is, that when we haue this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge to heare the worde of God purely preached, to call vppon his name and too vſe the Sacramentes, that this is a benefit recompenſing all the vexations, troubles and griefes, that Satan ſhalbe able to ſtirre vp againſt vs.</p>
            <p>I haue ſet downe in the end a briefe expoſition of the 87. Pſalme, the which ſeemeth vnto me to ſerue fitly for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: for there is handled the reſtoring of the Churche of God. Now we ſee many at this day that ſeeing the Churche ſo deſolate as it is, they diſcourage themſelues, as if ſhortly it ſhould altogeather periſhe. Suche kinde of people, and generally all the faithfull ſhall finde here wherwith too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themſelues, ſeeing the hope that God giueth of ſetting vp his Church againe after that for a time it hath beene caſt downe: and of making it to proſper and flooriſh againe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that it ſhall haue beene miſerable in reſpect of the world. I beſeech our good God that my labour be not in vaine, but that you may be edified through my trauaile according as I deſire,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From Geneua, <date>this 20. of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> 1552.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7693:7"/>
            <head>A Sermon wherein all Chriſtians are exhorted to flie from outward Idolatrie, vpon the 4. verſe of the 16. Pſalme. <hi>I will not co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="8 letters">
                     <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>e with their ſacrifices of blood, and their n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es ſhall not paſſe through my mouth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E haue here to handle a</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine cleare and eaſie inough, were it not that the moſt part of thoſe which call them ſelues Chriſtians, ſought, I can not tell what maner of ſubtilties, to cloke their euill withall. The ſumme is, that after we knowe the liuing God to be our father, and Ieſus Chriſt our redeemer, wee ought to dedicate both our body and ſoule vnto him, who by his infinit goodnes hath adopted vs for his children, and endeuo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r to do homage vnto this ſo good a Sauiour, for that it hath coſt him ſo deare. And becauſe we are bound not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to renounce all infidelitie, but alſo too ſeparate our ſelues from all ſuperſtitions, which are contrary as well to the ſeruice of God, as to the honour of his Sonne, &amp; which can not agree with the pure doctrine of the Goſpel, and the true confeſſion of faith: I haue ſaide that this doctrine is eaſie ynough of it ſelfe, and that there remaineth nothing but to put the ſame well in practiſe, ſauing that there are a ſort of people that ſeeke certaine ſtarting holes and ſubtill ſhiftes, to the ende they may not ſeeme culpable, in that which is ſo greatly condemned by Gods owne mouth. This
<pb facs="tcp:7693:8"/> cauſe conſtraineth vs to dwel longer in the declaration of this matter, to the ende that euery one may knowe what is his duetie, and that no man deceiue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, imagining that hee is eſcaped by couering him ſelfe, as the common ſaying is, vnder a wette ſacke.</p>
            <p>But becauſe that ſome may thinke that this is a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous argument in reſpect of vs, who haue by the grace of God, our churches purged from the infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and the Idolatryes of the Papacie: before wee paſſe any farther, it is good to ſhewe that ſuch people are foulely deceiued. For in the firſt place when it is ſhowed vs, what an offence it is too defile our ſelues with Idolatries, faigning to conſent or to cleaue too their impieties, we are put in mind to mourne for our former faultes, and to aſke pardon of God for them with all humilitie: and therevpon too acknowledge the ineſtimable benefite that he hath ſhewed vnto vs, in pulling vs out from ſuch filth wherein wee were plunged. For wee can not too much magnifie ſuch an excellent grace. And becauſe we knowe not what may happen vnto vs, nor to what end God dooth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs, it is good that wee be alwayes armed afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande and in a readineſſe, to the ende that in what ſo euer place we come, or with what temptation ſo euer we be aſſaulted, we neuer ſwarue from the pure word of God. It may fall out that many in this company which haue to trauell into the countries of Papiſtes: they beeing there in the combate haue neede to bee ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med aforehand. On the other ſide, if GOD giue vs at this day libertie to ſerue him purely, wee knowe not how long it wil indure. Let vs therefore take the time wherin we be in reſt, not as though it ſhould alwaies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7693:8"/> laſt vs: but as a truce in which god gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth vs leaſure to fortifie our ſelues to the end that being called to make confeſſion of our faith, we be not to ſeeke for not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thought vpon it in time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient. In the meane while, we haue alſo to think vpon our pore brethren, which are kept vnder the tyranny of Antichriſt, to the end to haue pittie vpon them, and to beſeech God that he wil fortifie them with ſuch conſtancie, as he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by his word. Further alſo we haue to ſtir them vp to the end that they ſleepe not &amp; flatter themſelues, but rather that knowing their dutie, they inforce the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to giue glory to God. For it is not only for our ſelues that we are taught: but to th'end that euery one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of his faith, imparte to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors of that which hath bin ſhewed him in the ſchole of God. We ſee therfore that it is very profitable, yea neceſſary not only for vs, but for our brethren, that the memory of this doctrine be oftentimes renewed vnto vs, eſpecially ſeeing the text which we haue to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d leadeth vs thereto. As in this place, Dauid maketh a great proteſtation, and as it were a ſolemne vowe that he wil neuer be a partaker in the ſacrifices of the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters eſpecially to haue the Idolles in ſuch hatred and deteſtation, that he wil abſtaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> name them, as though he ſhoulde defile his mouth in naming them. This is not the particular facte of any meane man: but the example of Dauid a moſt excellent King and Prophet, which ought to be a generall rule to all the children of God.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding to the end that this may be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen more cleerely, &amp; that we alſo may be better tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched therwith, let vs mark the reaſon that he addeth, the which is, as it were the ground of the horror that
<pb facs="tcp:7693:9"/> hee hath to mingle him ſelfe amonge the idolaters. <hi>The Lorde</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>is mine inheritance.</hi> And is not this common to all the faithfull? At the leaſt there is not anie one which dooth not reioyce herein. And in deede it is very certayne, that God being once giuen vnto vs in the perſon of his Sonne, doeth day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inuite vs, to the ende that we ſhould poſſeſſe him: but there are verie fewe which are ſo affected in this behalf as the matter deſerueth. For we cannot poſſeſſe God but with this condition, that wee alſo be altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his. It is therefore for good cauſe that Dauid groundeth him ſelfe vppon this theame, ſeeing that God is his inheritance that hee will abſtayne from all pollutions of idols, the which do turne vs away and eſtraunge vs from him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 57.</note>This is the cauſe why the Prophet Eſaie when hee had vpbraided the Iewes, that they had giuen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to falſe and ſtraunge gods, whiche they had made vnto them ſelues, hee addeth, <hi>Loe theſe, theſe</hi> (I ſay) <hi>are thy portion:</hi> ſignifying by theſe wordes, that God denieth all couenaunt and felowſhip with idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and diſheriteth and depriueth them of that ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite a benefite, which he would haue beſtowed vppon them by giuing him ſelf vnto them. Some man will replie that he entreateth there, of thoſe which put their truſt in idols, and deceyue them ſelues through vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe. I confeſſe it: but contrariwiſe I aunſwere, that if they which wholie attribute, the honour of God vnto idolles, are fully cut off from him: they alſo at the leaſt ſtraye in part from him, who through feare and infirmitie faigne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent vnto ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions. For it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be, that any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in what ſorte ſoeuer it be, can draw nere vnto idols, either in hart, in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7693:9"/> geſture, in wil, or in ſhewe, but be muſt recoyle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo much the farther from God. Wherefore let vs hold this article for reſolute, that they which ſeeke truely and in puritie of heart to poſſeſſe God for their heritage, will haue no fellowſhip with Idolles, with whom they haue ſuch a diuorce, that hee will that all thoſe that are his, ſhould proclaime &amp; make continual and deadly warre againſt them. And Dauid expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetteth forth in this place, that he wil not be a parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker with their offringes, and that their names ſhal not paſſe by his mouth. He might haue ſaid, I will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe my ſelfe with the fooliſh deuotions of vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, I will not put my confidence in ſuch abuſes, I will not leaue the trueth of God to followe ſuch lies. He ſpeaketh not ſo: but rather that he will haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with their ceremonies. He proteſteth then that he will abide continually in the puritie both of body and ſoule, concerning the ſeruice of God. In the firſt place we haue hereto ſee, if this be not idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, to ſhewe by outward ſignes that a man agreeth to ſuperſtitions, through which the ſeruice of God is corrupted and peruerted. They who ſwimme (as they ſay) betweene two waters, alledge, that ſeeing God will be worſhipped in ſpirite, that one can not woorſhip idolles, without hauing his truſt in them. But the aunſwere is eaſie: That God will not bee woorſhipped in ſpirite in ſuch ſorte, that hee forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the other parte to witte, the body, as though that pertayned not vnto him. For hee hath ſpoken e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough thereof in other places, of bowing the knees before him, and of lifting vp the handes vnto hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: what then? The principall ſeruice that hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, is in deede ſpirituall: but the open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration
<pb facs="tcp:7693:10"/> which the faithfull make, that it is he one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whome they ſerue and honour, followeth imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly, and muſte ſtraightwaye bee ioyned vnto it. But the obiection which they make, taking occaſion of one woorde, one onely place ſhall be ſufficient to reprooue them. It is written in the ſeconde Chapter of the Prophet Daniel, that Sidrach, Miſach and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bednego, refuſing too Nabuchodonoſor once too ſeeme to conſent to the ſuperſtition whiche hee had erected, they plainely declare, that they will not woorſhip his gods.</p>
            <p>If theſe ſubtil Sophiſters had beene there, they woulde haue laughed too skorne the ſimplicitie of theſe three ſeruauntes of GOD. For they woulde haue ſayde, Poore ſoules, This is not too woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe them, ſeeing you put no affiance in them: theere is no idolatrie but where there is deuotion. But theſe holy perſonages followed better counſell. And in deede, this aunſwere proceeded not from their owne braine: but it was the holye Ghoſte that enforced their tongues: againſt which if we will not reſiſte, it is meete we take out of this place a true rule and definition, that this is a true kinde of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, when any outward acte is done that is contrary to the true ſeruice of God, although that it be done co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourably and through hypocriſie. Theſe hypocrites cauill gaily, This no Idolatrie, ſeeing wee haue no truſt in them: yet ſhall theſe men continually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne condemned by this ſentence, that the great iudge hath pronounced therof. But ſuch kinde of people ſtriue about a woorde, pretending onely in parte too leſſen their faulte, whiche they can not altogyther excuſe. They will eaſily graunt and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7693:10"/> confeſſe, that this is yll done: but they woulde haue men too eſteeme it as a veniall ſinne.</p>
            <p>But if a man ſhoulde agree with them concerning the name and yeelde that which they demaunde, yet they haue gained nothing thereby. Let vs put the caſe, that it were not called Idolatrie, too faigne too worſhippe Idolls: yet this ceaſeth not too bee a trayterous acte againſt GOD, an acte repugnaunt to the confeſſion of Faith, a pollution and a ſacriledge. I pray you, when the honour of God is violated, that we falſifie the promiſe that we haue made vnto him, that through cowardiſe and fayntneſſe of ſtomake wee crookedly renounce our Chriſtian profeſſion, that wee are ſo double and defile our ſelues in thinges which GOD hath accurſed: is this ſo lighte a matter, that after wee haue doone it, wee ſhoulde onely wipe our mouth, and ſaie that we haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſome little faulte? Let vs therefore put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way theſe ſhiftes, ſeeing they ſerue to no other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe but to make vs boulder in euill, without leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our faulte any whit.</p>
            <p>There are yet ſome others which are more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudente: For not onely they labour too wreſte the worde, making men beleeue that it is not ſo great &amp; enormious a ſinne: but they moſt plainely and flatly maintaine that it is no ſinne at all. It is ſufficient, ſay they, that GOD bee ſerued with the hearte: verie well, if the heart were not double. For where there is an integritie and ſoundneſſe, there the body ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be drawne into a contrary pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. I would knowe of them what it is that carryeth their feete too the Church, when they goe to heare Maſſe. Their legges would neuer ſturre of their owne motion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:11"/>
            <p>They muſt therefore needes confeſſe that they haue ſome manner of affection to ſerue the idolles: yea in that they deſire too beholde them with the enimies of the trueth, and that their life is more precious vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them then the honour of God. But albeit their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie be too too ſhameful: in ſuch ſorte, that I am aſhamed to diſpute againſt it, as though they had ſome colour of reaſon: yet neuertheleſſe it behoueth to doo it foraſmuch as they pleaſe them ſelues ſo much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, &amp; are as it were ſo drunken therwith. It is inough as they thinke, if God bee worſhipped in ſpirite. But whereto then ſhal the body ſerue?<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20.</note> Saint Paule exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs to ſerue the Lord with both: becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto him. God hath created the body, and ſhal it be permitted therewith to do homage to the Diuell? It were much better that they ſhewed them ſelues to be flat Manichees, denying that God were the creator of the whole man. If they had the leaſt taſte in the world of the Goſpel, they would neuer burſt out into ſuch licentious libertie: For they ſhew that they know not what it is to haue bin bought by the bloud of the ſonne of God. And if it be ſo, howe ſhould wee hope for the reſurrection of the fleſhe, vnleſſe it were for that Ieſus Chriſt is the Redeemer both of our bodies and ſoules. Saint Paule in the firſte Epiſtle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, and the 7. Chapter, giueth vs warning, that wee ought not too bee the ſeruauntes of men, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wee were bought ſo dearely. Hee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that giues himſelfe too the ſeruice of Idolles, treadeth he not the blood of Ieſus Chriſte vnder his feete, which is the price of the immortall glory that we wait for in our bodyes? And to what reaſon is it, that our bodyes ſhould be defyled and prophaned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7693:11"/> Idols, ſeeing that the crowne of life is promiſed vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in heauen? Is this the meane to enter into the heauenly kingdome of God, to wallow our ſelues in Sathans ſtewes? Moreouer it is not ſaid in vaine, that our bodyes are the temples of the holy ghoſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they who knowe not that they ought too keepe them in all holynes, they ſufficiently declare that they neuer vnderſtoode any thing of the Goſpel: they ſhew alſo that they knowe not what belongeth too Ieſus Chriſt not to his grace. For when it is ſayd, that wee are bones of his bones, and fleſh of his fleſh, this plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſheweth that we are ioyned to him, bothe in body and ſoule. And therefore a man can no ſooner defile his body with any ſuperſtition, but he depriueth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of that holy vnion through which we are made members of the ſonne of God: Let theſe ſubtile doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours anſwere me if they haue receiued baptiſme only in their ſoules, hath not God ordayned that this ſigne ſhould be ingrauen in our fleſhe? Should therefore the body in which the marke of Ieſus Chriſte is engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, be defiled with contrarie Abhominations. Is the Supper onely receyued of the ſoule, and not alſo with the handes and with the mouth? GOD hath put the Armes and Badges of his Sonne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our bodyes, and ſhoulde wee beray them with dutie and dounge? It is not lawefull too imprinte twoo Coynes vpon one peece of Golde: or to ſet two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſeales one vpon another to a publike inſtrument and writing: and ſhall a mortall man take vpon him to falſifie baptiſme &amp; the holy Supper of Ieſus Chriſte and ſay, there is no euill in it? Such men truely are worthy that their ſeruants ſhould make them beleeue that they were well minded to ſerue them, in ſleeping
<pb facs="tcp:7693:12"/> and ſporting themſelues, and yet not moouing a fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to doe any thing. If they alledge that it is not all one, for aſmuch as wee haue neede of their ſeruice that are vnder vs: I anſwere, that ſeeing God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hauing any neede, will imploy vs to his honor, that it is a great ſhame for vs, that in doing all things quite contrary to his wil, would be quite rid of him: and yet a greater ſhame that a worme of the earth, &amp; a ſtincking carrion would haue more preheminence, then his creator. It behoueth a man yet too ſpeake more groſely to ſuch beaſts. They ſay that it is lawfull for them to diſſemble amongſt Papiſtes. Who is it then that giueth them the breade they eate there? And who is it that maketh the earth to bring foorth fruite? If they cannot deny but that God nouriſheth them as others,, wherfore doe they homage to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill with their bodyes? If they were Chriſtians, I would vſe more waightie reaſons, to witte, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding of them, to what end we liue heere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath: but it is pitie, that they who wil through their ſubtleties ſo dally and ieſt with God, ſhould become ſo brutiſh that they muſt be handled as men voyde of common ſenſe. It ſeemeth to them that they haue ſaid ſufficiently to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mater, when they ſay they doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothing in this behalf but for feare. But if this collour may take place, then it muſt be ſaid that Ioſeph ſhould haue don no euil, to haue committed whordom with his maiſtreſſe, not ſeeking the fulfilling of his pleaſure: but only to yeelde to the violence which ſhee offred him. This had then bin foliſhly don of him to ſuffer ſo much, and to lay himſelf open to ſuch infamie, ſeeing he had the meane to eſcape it. But it rather beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vs to hold vs to the teſtimonie of the holy ghoſt, who
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7693:12"/> praiſeth this conſtancie of his. If men doe no euill in playing the idolaters, to auoid the rage of Papiſts: He that ſhall bee his maiſters bande, ſhall not offende. A man ſhalbe excuſed when he poyſoneth his neighbor, or when he committeth any treaſon for feare of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him to whom he is ſubiect. This article is much ſtoode vpon, but as I haue ſaid, there is no hardnes or doubt in it: but it is good to ſee into what confuſion they fall, who imagine by their cunning ſleights to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the iudgement of god. There are diuers which at this day vſe another ſtarting hole: for cofeſſing that it is a deteſtable thing to mingle themſelues with the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatries of the Painims, they wil not that this extend it ſelfe to the ſuperſtitions of the Papacie: as though all the impieties of the Panims had not bin the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the true ſeruice of God, Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence I pray you drew the Panims al their ceremonies, but from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers? The miſchief was that they corrupted that which was wel inſtituted of God. And yet all the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations that euer were in the worlde, had this goodly cloke of the name of God &amp; of Religion: but this made them not therfore iuſtifiable, neither might the faithful communicate with them. Let vs procede farther. Although that I agre he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ther was a difference betwixt the ido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eof Papiſts, and that of the Painims in times paſt, yet they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not deny but that God as ſtraightly forbad his olde people the Idolatrie of Bethel, as the Idolatrie of ſtraunge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. When the Calues were ſet vp in Dan and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel, it was doone vnder the name of God: yea, of him which broughte his people out of Egypt. But, foraſmuche as the Seruice there eſtabliſhed, was contrarie too the doctrine of the Lawe, God
<pb facs="tcp:7693:13"/> condemned all thoſe that went thither to defile them ſelues. And truely theſe thinges, the Supper of Ieſus Chriſt, and the Popiſh Maſſe, are thinges no leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnaunt and contrary one to the other, then the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of Moyſes &amp; Ieroboham. Wherfore, whence came that diſpenſation to goe to the Maſſe, vnder cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, that it is but an altering or diſguiſing of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Ieſus Chriſte? Contrarywiſe I ſay, that they whiche truely feare God oughte too haue it in a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deteſtation, for aſmuch as it more manifeſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneth the holy ordinance of the ſonne of God, then if it had not beene ſo contrary and repugnant vnto it. Let vs then briefely holde this rule, that all the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men, which are ſet vp to corrupte the ſimple puritie of the word of God, and to ouerthrowe the ſeruice which he demaundeth and alloweth, they are very ſacriledges, wherewith a Chriſtian man may not communicate, without blaſpheming of God: that is to ſay, without treading his honor vnder his feete. I knowe very wel that this rigour wil ſeeme harde and intollerable to them that would haue a man to handle them according to their appetite. But what woulde they that I ſhould d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> heerein, knowing them to be ſo delicate? I would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>re them if it were poſible for me. But yet muſt bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> I and they ſuffer condemnation, when God once ſpeaketh: They ſay they finde no man more ſeuere herein then I am. But I would them to vnderſtand, that hitherto I haue handled them but too gentlely, which beeing ſo, they cannot be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from that which the Prophet Ieremie requireth of the Iewes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 10.2.</note> who were Captiues in Babylon. It was not onely forbidden them to goe to the abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Chaldeans, or to make ſhew to conſent vnto
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7693:13"/> them: but an expreſſe commaundemente is giuen them, to ſhewe that they ſhould count it a moſte vile and filthie ſauour. His words are theſe: <hi>You ſhall ſay vnto them. The Gods which haue not made Heauen and earth, ſhall periſhe from the earth, and from vnder the Heauen.</hi> There is one circumſtance woorthy to bee well marked, that the Prophete hauing written his Booke in He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brewe coucheth this verſe in greate Calda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y letters: as though he had preſſed the Iewes to chaunge their language, to the ende to ſhewe more playnly the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agrement they had with the idolaters.</p>
            <p>Nowe let them hardly goe and complayne of me, as though I were too exceſſiue. And yet I neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired half ſo much of them as the Prophet doth. But whether I ſpeake of it, or holde my peace, wee ceale not to be all bound to that Law which GOD hath laid vpon vs. And indeed it is not without cauſe, that God ſpeaking vnto his faithfull, he layeth vnto them. <hi>Yee are my witneſſes, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> choſen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 44.2.</note> Whoſoeuer will approue himſelfe to be a member of Ieſus Chriſte, muſt ſhewe that this title agreeth vnto him, ſo that they that through their f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe diſſembling and hypocriſie bury this teſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th, can in no wiſe be excuſed. And what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> them, I pray you, who all their lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>err it, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they do, who not only hid their chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the end they may ſhew no ſigne therof before men: but do commit acts altogither co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to it? There remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing then to the Children of God, that are i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the midſt of ſuch pollutions, but to afflict their ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> by the example of good Lott: yea to ſpeake againſte euill, according as GOD ſhall giue them the meane and opportunitie. Nowe let vs come too ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:7693:14"/> of thoſe Idolaters which at this day beare the ſway. I haue already ſomewhat touched the Maſſe. Now although this bee a blaſphemie ſo foule and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as nothing can bee more, yet notwithſtanding there are yet found aduocates of ſo ill a cauſe, who in this behalfe ſlinke backe: and yet will they nill they, they are conſtrayned to confeſſe that which I ſay: that is, that the Maſſe in it ſelfe is a renouncing of the death of Ieſus Chriſt, and a ſacriledge forged by Sathan, vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to aboliſh the Sacrament of the ſupper. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not likewiſe denie but that the Prayers made vnto Saintes, and ſuffrages that are made for the deade, are wicked abuſes, whereby the inuocation of the name of God (which aboue all others is moſte holy) is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned: notwithſtanding medling them ſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuch filthineſſes amongſt the Papiſtes, they think that they are not faultie. What ſhould we doe heerein ſay they? It is not lawfull for vs to reforme theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which we knowe to be euill: For we are priuate men, and they who haue publique authoritie main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them: wherefore it behoueth vs to goe thorow that way: I graunt them all that they ſay: but this is nothing to the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>. It is not their parts, to reforme the common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the people: and no man requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> man may admoniſh them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>: the which belongeth to their due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. It is not ſayd vnto them, that they ſhould purge the Churches or the ſtreetes: but that euerye one ſhoulde keepe his owne bodie and ſoule in puritie, and labour by all meanes, that GOD may be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured in his owne houſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe twoo things are diuerſe enough, too aboliſh
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7693:14"/> the maſſe out of any Countrie, are not to bee fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e there, when he cannot let the vſe of it. But yet they eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoones returne to the foote of their ſonge: that is that they renounce not the death &amp; paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, becauſe they haue no ſuch intent. But I aſke of them what it is that a Chriſtian man confeſſeth, with his mouthe, but that ſame that hee beleeueth with his heart? That the acte which they commit is altogither contrary too Chriſtian profeſſion, is notorious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe. So that, (aſmuche as lyeth in them) they renounce and forſake that which is of pure faith. I will ſpeake yet more familiarly. The maſſe is a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, wherein the Papiſts will offer vppe Chriſt, to bee reconciled too God. If this were true, Ieſus Chriſte by his death and paſſion had not purchaſed righteouſneſſe not euerlaſting ſaluatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for vs, let a man goe aboute the buſhe as farre as he will, yet hee muſt come to this poynt. All they that goe to Maſſe vnder the title of deuotion, proteſſe too conſente heerein. So that, aſmuch as lyeth in them, they ſhewe that they holde not their redemption perfecte by the death of Ieſus Chriſte. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> there bee ſome which bounde them ſelues a li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> narrowlye: that is, that they reſerue but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſt or highe Maſſe, in which it ſeemeth to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re is more conformitie with the ſupper of Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſte.</p>
            <p>And in deede a man might ſaye that the Maſſes whiche are ſaide aſwell by thoſe hedge Preiſtes as whiche by thoſe Chanons and Chaplaynes, and all thoſe are founded vppon ſome particular deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whiche they ſette out euery day to ſale, are as Harlotes of the Stewes. The Pariſhe Prieſtes
<pb facs="tcp:7693:15"/> Maſſe is as a ſtumpet, that ſhroudeth her ſelfe vnder the name of her huſbande, to keepe her ſelfe in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of an honeſt woman. Although the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude bee not altogither fitte: For a married whore, will alwayes yet haue ſome ſhame from giuing ouer her ſelfe too all commers: but that ſame Parriſhe Prieſtes Maſſe, is the moſte common idolatrie of all others. So farre is it off, that they that paint her out with this coulour, keepe here yet any trace of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Ieſus Chriſt: yea as if a theefe were euer the better, when hee ſhall be apparelled with the ſpoyle of him, whoſe throte hee hath cutte, and ſhall bee mounted vp vpon his Horſe. Wee ſeeke (ſay they) the ſupper of Ieſus Chriſte. Seeing we cannot haue it pure, in the tyranny in which we liue, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues too take that which is lefte, waytinge when God will put to his hand. Forſooth a goodly excuſe. Foraſmuch as they haue no right and ſounde vſe of the Supper, by way of prouiſion, they proteſt, that they account not Ieſus Chriſt for their onely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting Sauiour, and they ſeeke euery morning a newe ſacrifice to blot out their ſinnes. For all this is in the Parriſh Prieſtes Maſſe, aſwell as in that of S. Nicholas, or in thoſe that are ſaid for the dead. They faigne to worſhip an Idoll, and yet boaſte themſelues to ſeeke Ieſus Chriſt. And to the end, they may not fight againſt God without a ſwoorde and a Buckler. they bring foorth the authoritie of this man here, and of that man there. As if the abſolution of a man could exempt them, from beeing condemned of God. I ſpare to ſay that they notably belie them, whom they bring for their aduocates. But admit it were ſo, that a holy man for a time thought it not ſo greate an euill too
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7693:15"/> goe to an high Maſſe: yet yf afterwardes he knew the errour wherein he was, his latter iudgement is ſo much the more to be beleeued, for the condemnation thereof, foraſmuch as men may ſee, that the power of God hath compelled him therevnto, and he is plainly found to be ouercome in that thing, which before he did holde and alowe of. But what a blundering and ſtirre keepe they heere? Imagine they too reſtraine God by the opinion or ſaying of a mortall man? We know that there is nothing but the onely trueth that ſhall raigne in his iudgement, without acception of perſons. Now the fact is this, that the pariſh maſſe is inſtituted for to ſacrifice Ieſus Chriſt, and to make an attonement with God, aſwel for the quicke as the deade and that a peece of bread is woorſhipped there, as if it were the ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of God. I doe not ſcanne euery thing by peecemeale: there are a thouſande other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: but I onely take the groffeſt. Let them which ſeeme to agree h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> theyr handes, as much as they wyll, in the ende they ſhal bee no more iuſt then Pilate was. But this is marueilous that theſe good pariſhioners, when Eaſter comes they goe to ſeeke ſome Chappell in a corner, or ſome Fryer ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hot nor colde, that he may deliuer vnto them a counterfaite and baſtarde ſupper. If the pariſh Maſſe, as they ſay, be ſo like the ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt, why doo they not obſerue it and keepe them ſelues to it? But nowe after they ſhal haue beene at high Maſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Sunday throughout the yeere, that they may ſeeme to communicate aright in the ſacrament of the Supper, they ſodenly re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nce it: although we muſt not greatly woonder at ſuche inconſtancie: For it is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> payment and iuſte puniſhmente of all thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:7693:16"/> which are not grounded vpon the trueth of God: and God reuengeth him ſelfe vpon them, making them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be ſhaken, and to contrary the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in that which they take in hand. Touching ſuch a paynted Supper, I knowe that in their fantaſie, a man ſhall doe them great wrong to reproue it. But how can we doe otherwiſe, ſeeing it agreeth not to the rule of our mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? I doe not condemne them, becauſe they doe it in ſecret. For I knowe that the holy Supper was neuer better Miniſtred, nor more holyly, then when the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were withdrawne to doe it in ſecrete, becauſe of the tyranny of their enemyes. But heerein there are two intollerable faults: one is that they which patch vp ſuch a Pageant of the Supper, faigne that they haue their maſſe there, &amp; would that it ſhuld be ſo thought: the ſeconde, is, that their goodly father of whom they receiue it, giueth it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not as a Chriſtian paſtor, but in the condition of a popiſh prieſt. They think that they haue goodly bucklers and defences, in ſaying, that the ſinger of their Maſſe hath no intention to make them worſhip the bread or the wine, that hee omitteth the Canon, wherein are the greateſt impieties, and that he giueth the ſacrament to all the company vnder bothe kinds. But when this ſhal come before the great iudg, they ſhall feele what they haue gotten by ſuch goodly gloſing pretextes: yea they ought already to feele the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and I reporte me to the prickes &amp; ſtingings they haue in their conſciences: And this is the place where this matter muſt be decided: For without making any longer enquiryes, they knowe what they pretende to ſhewe, aſwell to the enemyes of GOD, as to all the common people. It muſt needes be that God denye himſelfe, if he allow an act of ſuch a profeſſion. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:7693:16"/> all the men of the world ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all haue conſpired togither to iuſtifie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. yet ſhal not the hableſt of them be euer ſo abſolued, that he ſhal not halt downe right on both ſides. Now God hath declared by his prophet, that no ſuch halting ſhal euer be found good. Concerning the man whome they take to be the miniſter of their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, it is a very mockery to goe about to make him ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any ſuch office, yea, but (ſay they) the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyneſſe of the ſacramentes doe not depend vpon the worthyneſſe of the perſons. I graunt it, and I ſay far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that if a Deuil ſhould miniſter the Supper, it were not the worſe: and contrarywiſe, if an Angell ſhould ſing Maſſe, it were not a poynt the better. But we are nowe in hand with another queſtion: to witte, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the orders of the Pope giuen too a Munke or a Fryer, make him fit to execute the office of a Paſtor. If they reply that they meane not that hee ſhould doe any thing therin, and that they chooſe him not in any ſuch condition: the thing ſheweth the contrary. But let vs put the caſe that concerning them, they haue no ſuch regarde, yet haue I alwayes to ſtande vppon the outwarde profeſſion which they make. Nowe it is manifeſt that they couer themſelues vnder the vizard of a prieſt. For the dew celebratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Lords ſupper, it wer meete for them, to ſeperate themſelues from the ranke of Idolaters, becauſe they haue nothing heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in common with them. In ſteade of dooing this they goe as it were to be matriculated and incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt them, and faigne themſelues to be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame body. And heerevpon they would make vs to be lyke thoſe ancient heretiques who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the vſe of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for the vices of men: as though we looked vnto mens particular vices, and
<pb facs="tcp:7693:17"/> not rather to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſtate and condition. I paſſ ouer this briefly, but as little as I haue touched therof is more then enough to conuince ſo villanous an im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pudency. Notwithſtanding if they bee ſo blockyſhe, that they will vnderſtand nothing thereof, the worde of God ought to ſuffice vs. As when the Lorde ſaithe by Ieremie,<note place="margin">Iere. 4.<hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O Iſrael if thou returne, returne vnto me.</hi> The which wordes ſhew in what ſimplicitie we ought to walke before God, without turnyng backe agayne to any thing not allowed of him.<note place="margin">Actes. 14.<hi>15</hi>
               </note> And this is the cauſe why ſaint Paule proteſteth, that he was ſent too con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerte the vnbeleeuers from their vanities to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God: as if hee ſhoulde haue ſaide, that it was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to make men to chaunge an yll cuſtome, with other hypocriſies: but they muſt roundly aboliſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, to the ende that true religion maye bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in her owne puritie and holynes: For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, men cannot come directly to God: but they ſtagger &amp; reele, not knowing which way to turne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. There are others who are come ſo farre to for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſake the maſſe: but they would retaine certaine pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of that which they call the ſeruice of God: to the ende not to be accounted (as they ſay) altogeather for prophane people. And it may be, that there are which go that waies of a good affection: at the leaſte I am content to beleeue ſo: but whatſoeuer purpoſe they haue, yet this may we not ſay, that they therfore keep a ſtreight rule, &amp; a good meſure therin. Some wil ſay, we can wel go to their baptiſmes: For therein there is no manifeſt Idolatry. As though the Sacrament were not there defiled diuerſe waies, ſo that it ſhould ſeeme that Ieſus Chriſt were yet in Pilats houſe, to be boxed on the eare, &amp; abuſed with all reproche and villanie.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7693:17"/> To conclude, whereas they ſay, that it is to ſhewe that they are a people not without religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they ſhould be demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences why they do it, they would anſwere that it were to pleaſe the Papiſtes, and to make a ſhew to the end to ſhun perſecution. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſpye out theyr time not to come while maſſe is a ſaying: and yet they come to Churche, to the end men might thinke they were there. Others onely for theyr part keepe themſelues to euenſong; but I would faine knowe of them, whether they thinke it nothing to cenſe their Idolles, and that a ſolempne praier bee grounded vppon the interceſſion and merites of any Saint: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſing <hi>Salueregine,</hi> a thing ſo ſtuffed with execrable and diuiliſh blaſphemies. I paſſe ouer that the ſinging it ſelfe in an vnknowen tongue, is a many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt prophanation of the holy Scripture, and of the prayſes of God: as ſaint Paule doth admoniſhe in the 14. of the firſte to the Corinthians. But admit, that this laſt fault be pardoned them, if they come to euen ſong to geue ſome teſtimonie of their Chriſtianitie, this ſhoulde eſpecially be done at their great feaſtes They wil make there a ſolempne incenſing of theyr chiefe Idols: which is a kinde of Sacrifice as the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſheweth: and likewiſe this was a common faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the Heathen had too make thoſe that were weake to renounce God. And this is the ſpeciall quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell for which the greateſt parte of Martyres haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered death: to wit, becauſe they would not make per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes and burne incenſe too Idolles. When theſe men bee come thus farre that they receiue in theyr noſes the ſauour of the Cenſours, they infecte them ſelues with the pollution which is there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted: and they thought that this ſo great wickedneſſe muſte bee
<pb facs="tcp:7693:18"/> hid and couered. But I pray theſe in the name of God, that they will marke well that which is ſaid here that the Idols ought to be in ſo great deteſtation to a faithfull man, that they ſhould not bee taken in his mouth for feare of defiling him. This onely woorde vndoubtedly ought rather to pul vs backe from al that might entangle vs amiddeſt the pollutions of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters.</p>
            <p>But nowe to ſpeake more freely of all thoſe that woulde keepe a meane betwixt God and the Deuill, they are double faced hypocrites: and I can finde no better compariſon too painte them out liuely in their colours, then that of Eſau: For when he ſawe that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaack his father ſent Iacob into Meſopotamia to take him a wife, for aſmuche as thoſe of the Countrey of Canaan diſpleaſed both him and Rebecca his wife, ſo farre foorth as they hated them deadly, to ſatiſfie his parentes in parte, he tooke him a newe wife: but hee forſooke not her who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had alredy. He kept the euil then whereof Iſaack complayned: but to botch vp the matter in ſome ſort, he huddled vp a newe marriage. So, they who are ſo wrapped in the world that they cannot follow that which GOD commaundeth, they make many medlayes, and hotchpotches of ſundry ſortes, that in ſome ſorte they maye conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues too Goddes wyll: but they ceaſe not for all that, alwayes too retaine ſome corruption, ſo as all that they doo, is neither pure nor ſincere. I know very well that there are many poore ſoules in great perplexitie, who without hypocriſie deſire to walke the ryght way, and yet notwithſtanding they can not ridde them ſelues from many doubtes: wherat
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7693:18"/> I doe not much wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder, conſidering the horrible confuſion that is in the Papacy. In very deede I much pitie theyr caſe, who ſeeke the meanes that they may to ſerue GOD, keeping them ſelues if it were poſſible, amongeſt the enimies of the faith. But what? I know not what elſe to do either to the one or to the other, but to ſhewe them wherein they haue faulted, to the ende they may amend it.</p>
            <p>If any will come and demaunde this or that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, I will ſende ſuche enquirers to that generall rule of GOD which I holde. I ſpeake this, becauſe there are ſome ſo importune, that a man ſhall neuer haue doone, if he would anſwere all theyr doubtes. Such people may rightly be compared to them who after they haue hearde a Sermon, wherein they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted without ſuperfluitie &amp; pompe ſoberly to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto it, would rather haue the preacher to make theyr Hoſe and ſewe their ſhooes. Well, what muſte we doo then? wee haue in all this a certaine marke whereunto we muſt aime: that is, that the zeale of Gods houſe do euen eate vp our hearte, and ſo moue vs that we take vppon our ſelues all the diſhonours and opprobries which are doone vntoo vs for his name.</p>
            <p>When ſuch zeale ſhall be well kindled in our heartes, and ſhall not be like ſtubble ſet on fyer, and quickly quenched, but ſhall burne continually therewith: a man ſhall bee ſo farre of, from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng ſhewe too approue the abhominations where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with GOD is diſhonoured, that it ſhall bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for vs too holde our peace, and too diſſemble when we ſee them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:19"/>
            <p>And let vs marke well that it is ſaide: <hi>The zeale of Gods houſe:</hi> to the ende we ſhoulde knowe that this is too be referred to the outward order which is in the church, to the end wee ſhoulde exerciſe our ſelues in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of our faith. I way not thoſe mockers, who ſay that I can talke trimly of theſe matters, liuing at mine own eaſe: for they haue no great adoe with me, foraſmuche as it is well knowen that I haue no land heere. And as muche ſay I of all theſe phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers who geue ſentence thereof, without knowledge of the cauſe. For ſeeing that they will not hearken vnto God, who ſpeaketh vnto them, to teache them, I cite them too appeare before his iudgemente ſeate, where they ſhall heare their ſentence, againſt which there ſhalbe no more queſtion of replie. Seeing they will not now heare him as their maiſter, they ſhal then vnderſtande him too bee theyr iudge in ſpite of their teethe. The beſt able and craftieſt ſhall there find the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ouerreached &amp; deceiued in their accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be as wel exerciſed and trained as can bee, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe or to darken the trueth: yet their Miniuer hoodes and badges wherin they are woont ſo proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vaunt them ſelues, and in highly eſteeming them ſelues to deceiue them ſelues, ſhall not geue them the victory. I ſpeake this becauſe my Lordes the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, Iudges, and Aduocates not onely enterpriſe too pleade againſt GOD too haue a priuiledge to mocke him: but in reiecting the holy Scripture they ſpewe out their blaſpemies, as Soueraigne and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuocable determinations and ſentences. And ſuche manner of Idolles wyll bee ſo prowde that when they haue once ſpoken a woorde, they cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide that reaſon or trueth haue anye place. But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7693:19"/> yet this I ſhew them by the way that it were much better for them to think what an horrible vengeance is prepared for all thoſe that turne the trueth of God into a lye. Let not theſe chamber and carpet Doctors take heere any higher eſtate vpon them then is fit for them. For this were to chatter againſte our heauenly maiſter, to whome it is meete that all we giue audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Theſe goodly titles auaile nothing heere too exempt any man from iudgement: except it bee that the Lord Abbots, Pryors, Deanes, and Archdeacons be conſtrained to lead the dance in this greeuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation that God ſhall pronounce. Now although my Lordes the Courtiers were woont too pleaſe men with their holie Water, yet they ſhall not ſo pleaſe God. To conclude, let all theſe trifling Spendthriftes Ieſters and Praters holde their tongue, and not caſte foorth their accuſtomed cauills, vnleſſe they wil feele his mightie hande, at whoſe woorde they ought too tremble. This is a foule errour to make men beleeue, that in taking me to be their aduerſarie they ſhall not haue God any more to be their Iudge. Let them then blot my name out of their papers in this matter, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende therein nothing but that God may be hearde &amp; obayed, and not to gouerne mens conſciences accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my appetite, not to lay any neceſſitie or lawe vpon them. Concerning others, that reiect not Gods word in ſuch pride and outrage, and yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are ſo weake and ſluggiſh, that one cannot make them once to wag, I exhorte them that they take bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heede unto themſelues, not to flatter themſelues, as they haue doone hetherto. But that they open their eyes, &amp; awaken, to ſee and to feele their wretchedne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and miſerie. I knowe the difficulties and ſtraight<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7693:20"/> wherein they are, neyther doe I ſpeake vnto them of ſeruing GOD purely among Idolaters, as of an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie matter: but if they want ſtrength, let them flye vntoo GOD, too the ende hee may fortifie them, and they may learne to preferre his glory before all the thinges in the worlde. I deſire al the poore faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ones that are in the Papacie that they wyll mark this, as the Prophet Ieremie beyng in Ieruſalem, ſente the ſame leſſon too the people that were kept in captiuitie at Babylon. If the tyrrannie of the Pope and of his bee ſo harde and cruell, the Iewes of that time had their parte thereof: And yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng they were commaunded too deteſt and abhorre the Idolatrie of Chaldea, euen in the very boſome of the Countrey: For it is no reaſon that the tyrrannye of men ſhoulde empayre or diminiſh the due honor that wee owe vnto GOD. There is here no excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or priuiledge, for great or ſmall, rych or poore. Let all men therefore bowe downe theyr neckes, let the poore feare, leaſt he ſaying for feare I knowe not what to do, GOD aunſweare, neyther knowe I what too make of thee. Let not the ryche be drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with theyr eaſe, as it were lying vppon theyr Bedde? But rather let them learne by the Apoſtle Sainte Paule his example too accounte all but Dung and loſſe, which may turne or hynder them from Chriſtian life.</p>
            <p>In the meane tyme, let not vs forget for our parte, that which I touched in the beginning: that is, too applie this to our inſtruction, too bee alwayes ready into what coaſt of the world ſo euer wee ſhall be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, or what thing ſoeuer happen vnto vs, too con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7693:20"/> ſtedfaſte in the ſincere confeſſion of our faith, deteſtyng all ſuperſtitions, and Idolatries and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which are contrary too the trueth of GOD, dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his honour, and ouerthrowe his ſeruice.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The ſeconde Sermon, conteining</hi> an exhortation to ſuffer perſecution <hi>too followe Ieſus Chriſte and his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, vppon that place which is in the</hi> thriteenth Chapter too the <hi>Hebrewes.</hi> Let vs therefore g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his reproch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL the exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that can be made vnto vs to ſuffer patiently for Chriſte his name, and for the Goſpels cauſe, ſhall haue no place, if wee bee not well aſſured of the cauſe for whiche we fyght. For when the queſtion is of forſaking our lyfe wee muſt be well reſolued and certayne, wherefore it is. And ſuch conſtancie can not bee in vs, vnleſſe it bee grounded in the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of faith. It is true that certaine wyll fooliſhly and raſhly venter too die, too vpholde certaine fooliſhe opinions and dreames, that they haue conceyued in theyr owne braine. But ſuch headineſſe deſerueth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be holden for frenſie, then for Chriſtian zeale. As alſo in verye deede there is no ſtayedneſſe not
<pb facs="tcp:7693:21"/> ſetled vnderſtanding in ſuch people which ſo caſt them ſelues into peril with ſuch headie raſhnes. Howſoeuer it be there is nothing but a good cauſe, that maketh god to auow vs for his Martyrs: for death is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all. And the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned withlike ignomie and torments as Theeues are: But God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a difference betwixt them, in ſo much as he can not deny his owne trueth. Nowe it is requiſite that on our parte, we haue a certaine and vndoubted teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of the doctrine, for which we ſuffer. Therfore (as I haue ſayd) we cannot bee mooued nor earneſtly touched by any exhortations, which may bee made vnto vs to ſuffer perſecution for the Goſpel, if there be not a true certaintie of faith imprinted in our heartes. For it is not a naturall thing too hazarde our liues at aduenture. And when we ſhall doe it, it ſhalbe nothing but raſhneſſe, and not any Chriſtian vertue. Finally, God will allowe nothing of all that we ſhall doe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we be fully perſwaded that it is for him and for his quarrell that we are moleſted, and that the worlde is enemie vnto vs. Nowe when I ſpeake of ſuch a certaintie, I meane not onely that we muſt knowe to diſcerne betweene true religion, and the abuſes or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes of men: but alſo that we be well perſwaded of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life, and of the crowne which is promiſed vnto vs from aboue, after that wee ſhall haue fought heere beneth in this world. By the way let vs note that theſe two pointes are requiſite, and ought not to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated the one from the other. It is meete for vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to begin at this poynt, thorowly to knowe what our Chriſtianitie is, what manner of faith it is, that we haue to holde and to followe, and what rule it is that God hath giuen vnto vs: and that we be ſo tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7693:21"/> armed with ſuch inſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> able, boldly to condemne, all the fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>es, error<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that Satan hath brought in to corrupt the pure ſimplicitie of Gods doctrine. Wherefore a man ought not at this day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, if he ſee not many people which are diſpoſed to ſuffer for the Goſpell: and that the moſt part of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe which are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Chriſtians know not what chriſtianitie is. For all are, as it were ignorant, and they make no recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning too heare o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to reade but it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> haue ſome little taſt of the Chriſtian faith. And this is the cauſe that there are very fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſetled, and if they be aſſaulted they are found ſtraightway to be ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. This ought to ſtirre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of God, to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> certaine therof. But yet this is not al, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly inſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ght. For we may ſee that thoſe which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be (as it were) altogether ſetled in good doctrine, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> if they had neuer kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any thing of GOD, vnleſſe it be by ſome flying fantaſie. And why is this, vnleſſe it be bicauſe they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer comprehended the maieſty of the holy Scripture And in deed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that it is go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that had ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it is very cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that we ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> to hearken, &amp; alſo doe it with greater reuerence. When we ſhould thinke that in reading the holy Scripture, wee are in the ſchoole of Angels: we ſhould haue another maner of care and deſire, to exerciſe our ſelues in that doctrin that is ſet foorth vnto vs. We ſee nowe what manner of meane it is, whereby we ſhoulde prepare our ſelues to ſuffer for the Goſpel to wit, that we haue profited
<pb facs="tcp:7693:22"/> thus far in the ſchoole of God, that we are reſolute co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the doctrin that we ought to hold, that we can deſpite al the ſubtilties and crafts of Satan, al mens inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as things not onely friuolous, but alſo accurſed, for as much as they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> puritie, &amp; that herein we differ as the true Maryrs of Ieſus Chriſt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe franticke ones which ſuffer for their fooliſh opinions. For the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that being certaine of a good cauſe, we be ſo inflamed as it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vs, to follow God throughly whither ſoeuer he calleth vs: that his word haue ſuch authority with vs as it deſerueth: &amp; that being withdrawen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this world, we be as it were rapt vp &amp; rauiſhed to ſeek the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly life. But this is a thing more then ſtrange, that the light of god ſhining at this day, as clearely as euer it did, that there is ſo ſmal zeale as it is pitiful to behold. If we be not confounded with ſhame, it is ſo much the worſe: For to be brief if we ſhould come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that great iudge: where the euil that wee haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored to couer, ſhal be brought to light, with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes &amp; reproches, we ſhal haue wherwith to be alto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether ſwalowed vp. For if, we be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to GOD according to the meaſure of knowledge which he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I pray you is it that we are ſo feareful &amp; ſo cold to enter into co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bat, ſeeing that he hath in ſuche ſort manifeſted him ſelfe in this time, that it may be ſaid that he hath opened and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaied the great treaſure of his ſecretes? Muſte it not heedes be ſaide that we would not haue any thing too do with God? For if we had any regard of his maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, we durſt neuer be ſo bold too turne the doctrine which proceedeth from his mouth, into a philoſophy or I know not into what idle ſpeculation, To be ſhort
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7693:22"/> there is no excuſe that we ſhould not be greatly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, yea that we ſhold not haue an horrible condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, hauing knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much of the trueth of God, and hauing ſo little courage to mainteine it. Aboue al when we ſhal loke vnto the Martyres that haue bin in times paſt, we ſhal find paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng great cauſe to deteſt the villany that is in vs. For the greateſt part were not ſo mightily exerciſed in the holy ſcripture, to haue tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row knowledg to diſpute of al things they knew that there was one God, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ought to worſhip &amp; to ſerue. Alſo that they were redee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> by the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, to the end they might p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the confidence of their ſaluation in him and in his grace. And f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ther that al that which had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wherby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne al Idolatrie and ſuperſtitions. To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> their diuinitie was there is one God which hath created al the world, &amp; hath declared v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>to vs his will by Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by the prophets, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>lly by Ieſus Chriſt &amp; his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles we haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> who hath bough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs by his blood &amp; through whoſe grace we hope to be ſaued. All the Idolatries of the world are accurſed and execrable, hauing nothing but this they we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtoutly &amp; freely either to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or to ſome other kind of death. And this was not for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but in ſo great troups that the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of thoſe which went through the hands of tyrants, was as it were infinit. We a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for our parts ſo great clarkes as none can bee greater: (at the leaſt wee think for) &amp; indeed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the vnderſtanding of the holy ſcripture god hath ſo liberally delt with vs as he hath neuer done with any age. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ther is hardly found one drop of zeale. Now to nouriſh ſuch ſlouth there is no other way, vnleſſe we would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and wittingly prouoke the vengeance of God
<pb facs="tcp:7693:23"/> what then muſt wee doe too gette a good courage? We haue to conſider in the firſt place, that there ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no more pretious a thing before God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of our faith: for we do little know how god eſteemeth it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our life which is nothing, is more deare vnto vs the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. And herein we ſhew a marueilous beaſtlines. For we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſpare our life in this point, but we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that it is more eſteemed of vs then the honour of God and the ſaluation of our ſoules. A certayne Heathen, had the knowledge to ſaie, that it was a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable thing, to forſake and betray the cauſe why we liue, for the conſeruation of our life: notwithſtanding he and ſuch like neuer knew truely, to what end men were placed in this world, and wherefore they liued therein. It is true that they k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>we well, that a man ought to followe vertue, that he ought to mainteine him ſelf honeſtly &amp; without blame: but all their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues were nothing elſe but colloures and ſhadowes. We knowe much better, whereto our life ought too be applied to wit, that we glorifie God, to the ende that he may be our glory, without this woe vpon vs, and we cannot prolong our life vppon the earth one minute, but that wee ſhall alwayes heape vpon our heades, ſo muche the more malediction. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding we are nothing aſhamed, for the redeeming of a fewe dayes for this feeble life to renounce that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting kingdome, and to ſeparate our ſelues from him, through whoſe power we are mainteined in this life. If a man aſke the verieſt idiots, yea the moſt bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhe people of the worlde, wherefore it is that they liue, they dare not ſimply ſay, that it is too eate, too drinke, and to ſleepe. For all men knowe that they are created to a more noble and excellent ende. And
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7693:23"/> what other ende ſhall we finde out, vnleſſe it be to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God, and to ſuffer our ſelues to bee gouerned by him, as children of a good father: to the end that after we ſhall haue finiſhed the voyage of this coruptible life, we may bee receiued into his euerlaſting inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce: And this is the moſte principall thing, yea and all in all. When we make no account thereof, and that we are ſo ill inclyned to a beaſtly life, which is worſe then a thouſand deathes, what can we alleadge for our excuſe? To liue and not to knowe wherfore this is euen againſt nature. To reiect the cauſes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we liue, for the deſire of prolonging our life, as it were for three dayes, too the ende to liue in this deceitfull worlde, and beeing ſeparate from God, is ſuch a bewitching and madneſſe, as I knowe not by what name to cal it. But becauſe that perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ceaſſe not to be hard &amp; bitter vnto vs, let vs marke howe and by what meanes, chriſtians may ſtrengthen them ſelues to patience, euen to the laying downe of their liues for Gods trueth. The text which we haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyted, when it ſhall bee well vnderſtoode, is ſufficient inough for to leade vs heerevnto.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.13.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs goe foorth</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>of the Cittie, after our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his reproch.</hi> Firſt of al he exhorteth vs, although that the ſwoordes were not drawen againſt vs, nor fyers kindled for to broile and burne vs, that yet we cannot be truely ioyned and knit to the ſonne of God, ſo long as we are rooted in this world. Wherfore a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an although he be in quiet, yet he muſt haue one foote alwayes lifted vp, to match towardes the battell: and not onely this, but hee muſt haue his affection with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen from the worlde, although that his body dwell therein. Admit that this at the firſt fight ſeeme
<pb facs="tcp:7693:24"/> vnto vs very blunt, yet ought we well to content our ſelues with this word of S. Paule: that is, <hi>That wee are called and appointed to ſuffer perſecution.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.3.</note> As if he ſhould ſay: that ſuch is the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Chriſtianitie: that we muſt needes enter in and paſſe thorow this path, if we will followe Ieſus Chriſt. In the meane time, too eaſe our infirmitie, too ſweeten and mitigate the trouble and heauineſſe that perſecutions may bring vnto vs, we haue this great and ſweete comfort, &amp; that is, that in ſuffering for the Goſpel, we followe as it were ſtep by ſtep the ſonne of God, and wee haue him for our guide. If it had beene ſimply ſaide vnto vs, that to bee Chriſtians we haue to march thorowe all the oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bryes of the worlde, to come freely to death as often as it ſhould pleaſe God, we ſhold haue had ſome coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor as it ſhould ſeeme to replye, that this were a very ſtrange thing and farre from our nature, to wander ſo without a guide. But ſeeing we are commaunded to followe our Lorde Ieſus, his leading is more right and honourable, then for vs to refuſe it. But to the ende that wee may bee better touched, it is not onely ſayde that Ieſus Chriſt goeth before vs as our Captaine: but that we are conformed to his image: as S. Paule hath ſpoken in the 8. to the Romaines,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> that God hath ordeined al thoſe whom he hath adopted to be his Children, that they ſhould be made conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him who is the head and paterne of all. Are we ſo nice and dayntie that we will indure nothing? then muſt we renounce the grace of God, whereby he hath called vs to the hope of ſaluation. For theſe are two things, that can not be ſundred, too be a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; to be exerciſed with many afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Surely we ought a great deale more to eſteeme ſuch a confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7693:24"/> with the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do. It is true that in the world, to ſuffer for the Goſpel is a thing condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: but ſeeing that we know that Infidels are blinde, ought not we to haue clerer &amp; better eies the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they? It is aſhame to be afflicted of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which occupye the place of iuſtice: but S. Paul ſheweth vs by his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple that we haue gretly to reioice our ſelues in the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Ieſus chriſt, as it were in certain imprinted marks, by which God acknowledgeth vs, and auoweth vs for his. And we know what S. Luke reherſeth of S. Peter &amp; Iohn:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.42.</note> to wit, that they reioyced, that they were accounted worthy too ſuffer infamy &amp; reproche for the name of our Lord Ieſus. Loe two things quite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my &amp; dignitie: yea inaſmuch as the world being mad and outragious, iudgeth contrary to all reaſon: and by this meanes turneth the glory of God into diſhonour. But for our part let vs not refuſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the world to be defaſed and baſely eſtemed, that we may hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be honored before god &amp; his angels. We ſee what pain ambitious men take to obteine the order of ſome king, &amp; what triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>phes they make therof. The ſonne of god preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth his order vnto vs, &amp; euery one deſpiſeth it. I pray you in doing this are we worthy to haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon with him? Our voluptuouſneſſe is here bitten and can perceiue nothing: for theſe are the true armes of heauenly nobilitie. Priſons, baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts curſed ſpekings, import nothing but altogether ſhame &amp; reproch in the fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſie of men: but what ſhal let vs to look vp vnto that which God hath iudged &amp; pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced therof, vnles it be our own infidelitie? Wherefore let the name of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of god haue ſuch credit amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs as it deſerueth, to the end that we may learn to take it for a ſingular honor, that he ſetteth his marks vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs otherwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:7693:25"/> our vnthankfulneſſe is intollerable. If God handle vs according too our deſertes, hath hee not iuſt cauſe, too chaſtiſe vs dayly a thouſande kinde of wayes: yea which is more, a hundred thouſand deathes, were not ſufficient for ſome litle portion of our miſdeedes. But by his infinite goodneſſe he putteth all our faultes vnder his feete and aboliſheth them: and whereas he might puniſh vs as we haue deſerued, he findeth a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful meane, to cauſe our afflictions to be turned too our honor, &amp; a ſpeciall priuiledge: foraſmuch as tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe them, we are aſſociated and knit into the felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp of his ſonne. And muſt we not ſay that when we diſdayne ſuch a bleſſed condition that we haue il pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited in the Chriſtian doctrine?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15.</note> And this is the reaſon why S. Peter, after that he hath exhorted vs, to walke holily in the feare of god, that we ſuffer not as theeues, Whoremaiſters and Murderers, hee addeth by &amp; by, that if we ſuffer as Chriſtians, therein we glorifie god with that benefite which he hath beſtowed vppon vs. It is not without cauſe that he hath ſpoken ſo. For who are we I pray you, that we ſhoulde bee witneſſes of the trueth of GOD and procurers of the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of his cauſe? Loe we bee poore wormes of the earth, creatures ful of vanities and lyes: and yet God wil that his trueth be defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by vs: which is truly ſo greate honour that it apperteineth not, no not too the angels of Paradiſe. Ought not this conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alone ſufficiently inflame vs to offer vp our ſelues vnto god, ſeeing that it pleaſeth him to imploy vs to ſo honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a thing? Notwithſtanding many cannot withold them ſelues from reaſoning againſt GOD: or at the leaſte from making theyr complayntes for that GOD dooth not better ſupporte theyr weakeneſſe.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7693:25"/> It is a merueilous matter (ſay they) ſeeing that GOD hath choſen vs for his children, how he can ſuffer that wee ſhoulde bee ſo troden vnderfoote and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the wicked. I anſwere, although that it appeare not vnto vs wherefore he doth it, yet that he ought by good right to haue this authoritie ouer vs to bring vs in to order according to his pleaſure. But when wee ſee that Ieſus Chriſte is our patterne, ought we not too eſteeme it a great bleſſing to be made like vnto him, without any further enquirie? Notwithſtanding god ſheweth vs moſt euident cauſes why hee will haue vs to be perſecuted. When there ſhalbe no other thing but this admonition which S. Peter maketh,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7.</note> wee are diſdainfull and ſturdy enough, if wee doo not reſte our ſelues vpon it, that is, that foraſmuch as gold and ſiluer which are but corruptible me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alles, are pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ged and tried by the fire, it is good reaſon that our faith, which excelleth al the riches of the worlde,<note place="margin">Pſalme. 110.</note> ſhould be proued. God coulde very well crowne vs at the firſte daſhe, without making vs too endure any combates: but as hee woulde that Ieſus Chriſte ſhoulde raigne in the middeſt of his enimies vntil the end of the world: ſo likewiſe he would that we being mingled amongſt them, wee ſhoulde ſuffer their wronges and oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vntill that he ſhoulde deliuer vs from them. I know very well that the fleſhe will ſpurne when it muſte be brought to this pointe, but yet muſt the wil of god haue the maiſterie. If we feele any contradiction in vs, we muſt not woonder at it. For this is very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, too flie the croſſe: Notwithſtanding let vs not ceaſe to go forward knowing that god accepteth our obedience, ſo that we bring vnder and ſubdue all our ſenſes and deſires, to the end to make them ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:7693:26"/> him: for the Prophetes and the Apoſtles went not ſo readily to death, but that they felte in them ſelues ſome deſire of falling backe.<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>21.</hi>18.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt be led thither</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte vnto Peter) <hi>whyther thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not.</hi> So when ſuch feares of death ſhall pricke vs: let vs labour to haue the vpper hand, or rather let God ouercome for vs: and not withſtanding let vs holde our ſelues aſſured, that this is an acceptable ſacrifice vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him, that we reſiſt &amp; fight againſt our affections, to the ende we may be wholy at his commaundement. And this is the principall warre, wherein God wyl haue thoſe that are his to employ them ſelues: that is, that they enforce themſelues, to bring downe all that which exalteth it ſelf in their minds &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dings, too turne them away from the path that is ſhewed, vnto them. In the meane time the conſolations are ſo ample, that we may well ſay that wee are more then ſlouthfull, when we faile and waxe faint hearted. In olde time a great number of people, for the deſire of a ſilly Garland of leaues, refuſed no trauaile, no paine nor trouble: yea they made no accounte to die: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding there was not any one of them, whiche fought not at aduenture, being vncertaine whether he ſhoulde winne or looſe the priſe. God hath ſet foorth vnto vs an immortall crowne, through which we are made partakers of his glorye. Hee meaneth not that we ſhoulde fight at aduenture: but he promiſeth vnto vs all, ſuch a reward as wee ought ſpecially too deſire. What occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then haue we, to ſeeke any farther: doe we think that it is ſaid in vaine that if we die with Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt we ſhal alſo liue with him? The triumph is altogeather like,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> &amp; we ſhun to fight as much as lieth in vs. This in the iudgement of man is a doctrine quite
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7693:26"/> contrary. I confeſſe it: and alſo when Ieſus Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.10.</note> that they that ſuffer perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſake are bleſſed, he propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth a ſentence which is not eaſily receiued, in the world. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe, he wold that we ſhold eſteeme that to be our chiefeſt happines, which our vnderſtanding would iudge to be our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt miſery. It ſeemeth vnto vs that we are miſerable, when God leaueth vs to be troaden downe by the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and crueltie of our enimies: but the want is that we looke not vnto the promiſes of GOD, the which certifie vs that all ſhall turne to our good. We are throwen downe, ſeeing the wicked ſtronger then we, and to ſet their feete vpon our throte: but ſuche a confuſion as S. Paule ſaith, ought rather to lift vs vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on high. Foraſmuch as we are to to muche giuen, too imbuſie our ſelues, with the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t things of the world, God in ſuffering that the good are euill intreated, and that the wicked haue their ſway, ſheweth vs by euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſignes, that a day ſhal come, wherin al that is now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſhalbe reformed. If the time ſeeme long vnto vs, let vs run to the remedie, and not flatter our ſelues in our vice: for it is certaine, that we haue no faith at all, vnleſſe we lift vp the eyes of our ſoules to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte. Now God to the end he might leaue no meane vnattempted, whiche myght be fyt to driue vs forwarde, he ſetteth before vs the promiſes on the one ſide, and his threatninges on the other. Doe we thinke that the promyſes haue not power enough in vs? let vs ioyne the threatnings for too ſtrengthen them. It is very true that wee muſt bee ſo muche the more peruerſe and froward, not too adioyne more fayth then wee doo too the promyſes of GOD, when the Lorde Ieſus ſayeth,
<pb facs="tcp:7693:27"/> that hee will auowe and acknowledge vs before his father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.32.</note> ſo that we confeſſe him before men. And what is there that ought to let vs, that we ſhoulde not yeeld him that confeſſion that he requireth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 12.8.</note> When men ſhal haue doone their vttermoſt, they can doe no woorſe but murder vs. And what ſhall eternall life be in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon thereof? I heape not not vp heere all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes conteined in the Scriptures, which tende to one and the ſame ende: yet (foraſmuch as they are ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times repeated) we ought wholy to ſtay vppon them. But if when the plague hang ouer our heades, if three or foure be not enough, one whole hundred wil not ſerue to make vs to ouercome all aduerſitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary temptations. But if God can not drawe vs vnto him ſelfe through gentleneſſe, muſt wee not bee more then beetle blockiſh heades, when his ſeuere threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges can do no more therein?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 9:26.</note> Ieſus Chriſte citeth all thoſe before his father, who ſhall through feare of bodyly death deny the trueth: and ſaith that both the body and ſoule,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>10.</hi>3.</note> ſhall be throwen too perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And in an other place hee ſayth, that he will deny all thoſe that ſhall deny him before men, vnleſſe that wee bee too muche bereaued of all vnderſtanding, theſe woordes ought to make our hear to ſtande vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right vppon our heades, Howſoeuer it be, when wee ſhal not bee moued therewith as were meete, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth nothing for vs but an horrible confuſion: For in tha, tthat all the woordes of Ieſus Chriſt do ſo little profite vs, we are conuinced of too to great infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie. Wee ſhall haue alleadged too godly purpoſe that there is ſome pitie in vs, foraſmuche as our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſo brittle:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.25.</note> For it is ſaid contrariwiſe that Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes lookyng vnto GOD through faith, was ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7693:27"/> not to bow vnder any tentation. Wherfore when we are ſo ſoft and flexible, yea, that there is no zeale and conſtancie in vs, it is a ſigne that wee are vtterly ignoraunt both of God and his kingdome. When it is ſhewed vs that wee ought to be ioyned to our head, we thinke that we haue a goodly coulour to exempte our ſelues from it, by ſaying that wee are men. But they which haue gone before vs, who were they? It is true, that when we ſhall not haue the pure doctrine, al the excuſes that we can bring foorth ſhall be vaine: but hauing ſo many examples which ought too ſerue for the greater approbation, ſo much the more are we to be condemned. But heere we haue twoo pointes to be conſidered. The firſt is, that all the body of the Church generally, was and ſhalbe alwayes ſubiect till the ende, to be afflicted by the wicked: as it is ſaide in the Pſalme.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>They haue vexed me from my youth vp, they haue drawen the Plo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vpon me from one ende to another.</hi> The holy Ghoſte bringeth in the olde Church ſpeaking, to the ende that we, after wee haue knowen the afflictions thereof, we ſhould not finde it ſtraunge or troubleſom if the like at this day be done vnto vs. Sainct Paule al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo drawing this place from an other Pſalme where it is ſaid, <hi>Wee haue beene as ſheepe that are led to the ſlaughter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.36.</note> ſheweth that this was not for one age alone:<note place="margin">Pſa. 44.<hi>23</hi>
               </note> but that it is and ſhal be ordinary and vſuall in the Church. So ſeeing the Church of God to beat this day troaden vnder, by the pride of worldelings, that one barketh, another byteth, that men torment it, and alwayes miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieuouſly deuiſe againſt it, that without ceaſing it is aſſayled of madde Dogges and ſauage beaſtes: let vs remember that this was doone vnto it of olde time.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:28"/> It is true that God may wel geue it ſometimes certain truſes and releaſements. And this is it that is ſayde in the Pſalme before alleadged, <hi>hee cutteth aſunder the cordes of the wicked.</hi> And in an other place, that he wyll breake theyr ſtuffe, for feare that the good doe not ouermuch vexe them ſelues, beeing too muche oppreſſed. But God woulde alwayes that his Churche ſhoulde bee toſſed in this world, and be as it were in a continuall conflicte, reſeruyng reſte for it aboue in the heauens. Notwithſtanding that yet the iſſue of theſe aflictions was alwayes bleſſed, and at the leaſt GOD brought to paſſe, that being oppreſſed with many euyls, it was neuer vtterly oppreſſed, as it is ſayde that the wicked with al their forces neuer attained to that,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 7.15.</note> which they immagined: Saint Paule alſo reioyſeth him ſelfe of the like too ſhewe, that this is a continuall grace of God:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor. 4.</hi>12.</note> 
               <hi>We</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>endure tribulations, but we are not there with diſtreſſed, wee are poore but we are not deſtitute: we are perſecuted but we are not forſaken: we are caſt downe but we pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe not, euery where bearyng about in our bodies the dying of our Lorde Ieſus, too the ende that his life maye bee made many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in our mortall bodies.</hi> Such iſſue as wee ſee that God hath geuen in all tymes in the perſecutions of his Churche, ought well too encourage vs, knowing that our Fathers, who were brickle men as wee are, had alwayes the victorie ouer theyr enimies: in as muche as they remayned ſtedfaſt in patience. But I doo but touch this poynt briefly, to the ende I may come to the ſeconde, the which more agreeth to our purpoſe: that it is to make our profite of thoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar examples of the Martyrs, which haue gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:7693:28"/>
            <p>Nowe there are not onely two or three of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a thicke and great cloude,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith in the Epiſtle to the Heb. Wherby he ſignifieth th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the number is ſo great, that it ought as it were euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p our eyes. And that I be not too tedious, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> onely the example of the Iewes, which were perſecuted for true Religion, aſwell vnder the tyranny of Antiochus the King, as alſo a little after his death. We cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge that it was a ſmall number of people: for there were then as it were a greate armie of Martyrs. W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cannot ſay that it was of Prophets, whome God had ſeparated from the common people for the women &amp; young infants were of this company. We cannot ſay that they were let go for any priſe: for they were tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented as cruelly as was poſſible. Wee heare alſo that which the Apoſtle ſheweth vs therof.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35.</note> 
               <hi>Some</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>were hanged vp like belles and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ked making no account to be deliuered, to the end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they might receiue a better reſurrecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Others were tryed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>kings and ſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ging<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by ban<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and priſonment others were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſunder: other wandred vp and downe hither and thither, in wilderneſſes by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Caues.</hi> Let vs now enter to make compariſon of them with vs. If they ſuffred for the trueth of God, which was yet ſo darke at that time, what ought wee to doe in this great light that ſhineth nowe? God hath ſpoken vnto vs as it were with full mouth: the greate Gate of the kingdome of Heauen is opened, Ieſus Chriſt hath called vs vnto him, beeing come downe vnto vs, to the ende that wee ſhoulde haue him, as it were preſente before our eyes. And what a ſhame ſhall it bee vnto vs too haue leſſe zeale to ſuffer for the Goſpell, then they had which onely ſaluted and behelde the promiſes of GOD, as it were a farre off?
<pb facs="tcp:7693:29"/> Which had but a little Wicket open to come to the kingdome of heauen? which had nothing but a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne remembraunce and figure of Ieſus Chriſte? Theſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot be expreſſed with mouth as they are woo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e: wherefore I leaue them to euery one to meditate vpon.</p>
            <p>Nowe this doctrine as it is generall, ſo ought it to bee putte in practice of all Chriſtians: But euery one ought to applie it to his own vſe as neceſſitie ſhal require. I ſpeake this to the end that they which ſee the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues in no apparant daunger, ſhoulde not think that it is ſuperfluous vnto them. They are not at this time in the handes of Tyrantes: but what know they how God wyll deale with them heareafter? Wherefore we ought to be ſo armed afore hande, that if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, which we haue not thought vpon ſhal come vpon vs, we be not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at vnwares &amp; vnprouided. But I feare me that there are a great ſorte of deafe eares to heare this worde. So farre of is it that they which are nice &amp; liue at theyr eaſe, prepare themſelues to ſuffer death when neede ſhalbe, that they haue no care too ſerue God whiles they liue. And yet neuertheles this ought to be our ordinary and continuall ſtudie, and ſpecially in this time wherein wee liue. In the meane time they whome God hath called to ſuffer for the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his name, ought too ſhewe in verye deede that they were prepared long before, too ſtand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſtantly. And then they ought to call into their remembraunce all the exhortations that they haue hearde in times paſte: as yf a ſouldier ſhoulde take armes when the Trumpet doeth ſounde. But what? there is no queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſeeking ſtarting holes to eſcape: I ſpeake in reſpect of the greateſt part: For perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7693:29"/> is a true touchſtone whereby god diſcouereth and trieth who are his. So farre of is it, that hee ſhoulde many tymes finde who is faithfull vnto him, vntill that they franckely offer them ſelues to death. But this is as it were an incredible thing, that people whiche boaſt of ſome little knowledge of the Goſpell, dare o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen theyr mouth to vſe ſuche cauilations: For one ſort ſay, what ſhal we gayne to confeſſe our faith to obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate people, and to ſuch who haue determined to fight againſt God? Is not this to caſt pretious ſtones before ſwine.<note place="margin">Mat. 8.38.</note> As though Ieſus Chriſt had not expreſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that he wil that men confeſſe him amongſt the moſt peruerſe and wickedeſt men. If they be not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by edified, yet at the leaſt they remayne confounded: of ſuche a ſweete ſmelling fauour is that confeſſion be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore God, howe deadly ſoeuer it be too the reprobate. Others alſo may be founde who ſaye, what ſhall our death profite? It rather falleth out to an offence. As yf God had lefte too theyr choyſe too die when they thinke good, and when they ſhall ſee a fitte time. But contrariwiſe we approoue our obedience leauing the profite into his hande that ſhall come of our death. Wherefore in the firſt place, it behooueth that a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, in what Countrey ſoeuer hee be, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding dangers and threatninges, that he fully deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine to walke in ſimplicitie, as God hath commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Let him keepe hymſelfe aſmuche as he can from the rage of the woolues: ſo that the ſame be not done through the crafte of the fleſhe. Aboue all let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne his life into Gods handes. Hath hee doone this? If it fall out that he fall into the handes of enimies, let him think that God hath brought him into that place, and will haue him to bee one of the witneſſes of his
<pb facs="tcp:7693:30"/> ſonne, &amp; therfore that there is no way to draw back, vnleſſe it be in denying our faith to him, to whom we haue promiſed al duetie: both to liue &amp; to die, and to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are &amp; belong, although we had promiſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnto him. Hereby I do not bind all men of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiitie to make a full &amp; entire confeſſlinn of all that they beleeue, admit that they were therto required, Sainte Paule in this point hath vſed a good mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, who was as readye as anye other freely too maynteine the cauſe of the Goſpell, as he ought. And alſo it was not without cauſe that our Lord Ieſus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that in ſuch a caſe he will giue vs a mouth and wiſedome: as if he ſhoulde ſay, that the office of the holy Ghoſt is not onely to ſtrengthen vs to be bold &amp; valiant: but alſo to geue vnto vs wiſedome and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to know how it becommeth vs to rule &amp; gouern our ſelues in ſo great and hard a matter. The ſumme is that they which are in ſuche diſtreſſe, ſhoulde aſke and receiue ſuch wiſdome from aboue, not folowing their carnall cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel to ſeeke a way to eſcape, (as they ſay) by any croſſe or by pathes. There are alſo which replye that our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, anſwered not to them that aſked of him. But I ſay firſt of al, that this ſerueth not to aboliſh the rule which he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, to make confeſſion of our faith, when we are thereto required. Secondly I ſay, that he neuer diſſembled too ſaue his life. Thirdly that he neuer gaue aunſwere ſoo doubtfull, that it did not import ſufficient witneſſe of that which he had ſpoken: or rather, that he had not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified them already which came to aſke him further, as it were laying nettes to catch him. Wherfore let this point remain reſolute amongſt al chriſtians: that is, that they ought not to accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their liues more deare
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7693:30"/> then the teſtimony of the trueth, inaſmuch as God wil be glorified in it. Is it in vaine that hee calleth all thoſe witneſſes (for the worde Martyrs ſignifieth the ſame) that haue anſwered to the enimies of the faith? Is it not becauſe hee woulde haue them ſerue too ſuche purpoſe? And here euery one muſt not looke to his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and companion: For God doth not ſhew this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to all to call them therto. And foraſmuch as wee are geuen to marke others, the more we ought to take heede therof.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 21.18.</note> Peter hauing heard at the mouth of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that he ſhould be led in his old age whether he would not, aſketh what ſhould become of Iohn his companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. There is none of vs but he would willingly make ſuch a reply. For this we imagine by and by: Why do I rather ſuffer then others? But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe Ieſus Chriſt exhorteth all in general, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one in particular, alwayes to be ready, to the end that as he ſhall cal either one or other, euery man may march forth in his rank &amp; order. I haue ſhewed before that we ſhal be ill appointed to ſuffer Martyrdom, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that we be armed with Gods promiſes. It remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth now that we lay out a little more fully whereto they tend, not to ſpecify al by peecemeale and exactly: but to ſhew the principal things, that god would haue vs to hope for, to the end to comfort vs in our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Now theſe are briefly 3. thinges. The firſt is, that foraſmuchas our life and death are in his hand, that he wil in ſuch ſort preſerue vs by his power, that not one heare of our heades ſhal fal but by his licence.</p>
            <p>Wherefore the faithfull ought to hold themſelues aſſured into whoſe handes ſoeuer they ſhall come, that GOD hath not caſte of the ſauegard which he hath of theyr perſones. If ſuche a perſwaſion were well
<pb facs="tcp:7693:31"/> imprinted in our heartes, we ſhould be deliuered from the moſt parte of doubtes and perplexities that tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and hinder vs from dooing our duetie. Wee ſee that Tyrantes are let looſe: and hereuppon it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to vs that God hath no further meane too ſaue vs: For this cauſe we are tempted to prouide for our ſelues, as though there were no more waiting vppon him. But contrarywiſe his prouidence which he hath declared vnto vs is ſuch, as ought to be vnto vs an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible fortreſſe. Let vs therefore labour to learne this ſhort ſentence, that our bodies are in his handes who hath created them. For this cauſe he hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times deliuered his owne after a miraculous manner, and beyonde all hope of men, as Sidrach, Miſach and Abednago, from the fyery furnace, Daniel from the Lions denne, Peter from Herodes priſon where hee was enchained fettered, and kept ſo ſtraightly. By theſe examples hee woulde teſtifie vnto vs, that he holdeth our enimies bridled, though it ſeeme not ſo: &amp; hath power to draw vs out, euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mouth &amp; middeſt of death whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wil. Not becauſe he alwaies doth it: But by keeping vnto himſelfe the authoritie of diſpoſing of vs both in lyfe and death, hee woulde haue vs fully reſolued that he hath vs in his keeping: in ſuch ſort that whether ſoeuer Tyrantes looke, or with what fury ſoeuer they ruſhe vppon vs, that it is from him onely who is the orderer of our life. If he ſuffer Tyrants to kyll vs, it is not becauſe our liues are not deare vnto him, and in greater recommendation an hundred fold then it is worthie, ſeeing it is ſo, that he hath pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced by the mouth of Dauid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.15. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 26.21.</note> 
               <hi>That the death of his Saintes is precious before him,</hi> &amp; ſayth alſo by the mouth Eſay: <hi>That the earth ſhall diſcloſe the blood which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7693:31"/> to be hidden.</hi> Let the enimies therefore of the goſpel be as prodigal in ſhedding the blood of his Martyrs, as they will, yet ſhall they render a terrible accounte euen too the laſt and vttermoſt drop. They doe ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully mock at this day when they burne the faithful &amp; after they haue bathed themſelues in their blood, they are ſo drunken therwith, that they care nothing at all what murders they commit. But if we haue pacience too waite, God will ſhewe in the ende that it is not in vaine that he hath ſet ſuch an high priſe vpon our life. In the meane time yf hee doeth vs no euill, that it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to ratifie his Goſpell, which in woorthineſſe ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth heauen &amp; earth. And the better to aſſure vs that God leaueth vs not in the handes of Tyrantes, as hauing forſaken vs, let vs call too minde the ſentence of Ieſus Chriſte, where he ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4.</note> that it is hee whom they perſecute in his members.</p>
            <p>God had well ſaide before by Zacharie:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>Hee that toucheth you toucheth the apple of myne eye.</hi> But this is yet more plaine, that if wee ſuffer for the Goſpell, it is as yf the ſonne of GOD were there in his owne perſon. Wherefore let vs knowe that Ieſus Chriſte muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get him ſelfe, if hee ſhoulde not thinke of vs whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee are in priſon, or in daunger of death for his cauſe: And let vs knowe that God taketh to his owne heart all the outrages that Tyrauntes do vnto vs, as if they were faſtened to his owne ſonne.</p>
            <p>Let vs come too the ſeconde point that GOD in his promiſes hath ſet foorth vnto vs for our conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: that is, that he will ſo ſuſteine vs by the power of his holy Spirite, that our enimies whatſoeuer they do, or Satan theyr head, yet ſhall they not get the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hande ouer vs. And in deede wee ſee how he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playeth
<pb facs="tcp:7693:32"/> his graces in ſuche a neede. For ſuche inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſtancie as is in the true martyres, is a ſufficient ſhewe that GOD worketh mightily in them. There are two greeuous thinges to the fleſh in perſecutions: too wit, the one the rebukes and ſhame of men, and the other the tormentes that the body endureth. But GOD promiſeth vs, ſuche aſſiſtaunce that through patience we ſhal ouercome both the one &amp; the other. And he perfourmeth indeede that which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſed vnto vs. Let vs therefore take this buckler, too repulſe and put backe all feares, wherewith wee are aſſayled, and let vs not reſtraine the power of Gods ſpirite too ſo narrowe a ſcantling, that we thinke not, but that he will eaſily ouercom al mens cruelties. And hereof amongſt others we had an notable example in our time not too bee forgotten.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">This is called alſo Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick.</note>A certain young man who dwelt here with vs bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken in the Citie of Tournay was condemned to bee but beheaded if he recanted: and too bee burned aliue, yf he continued in his opinion. When hee was aſked what he woulde do, he aunſwered ſimply: Hee that ſhall geue me grace too dye paciently for his name, he wyll geue mee grace to endure the fier. We ought too eſteeme this ſentence not as the ſentence of a mortall man: but as a ſentence of the holy Ghoſt, to the ende too aſſure our ſelues that GOD is as able to ſtrengthen vs, and too make vs too ouercome all tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes as too mooue vs too take any other kinde of meeker death in good part. Which is more, we ſee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes, what conſtancie he geueth to poore male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factours who ſuffer for their offences. I ſpeake not of the obſtinate: but of thoſe which comfort themſelues in the grace of Ieſus Chriſt, and by this meane receiue
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7693:32"/> with peaceable heart the moſt grieuous puniſhement that can de doone vnto them: As we may ſee a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table example thereof in the Theefe who was conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed at the death of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte. GOD who ſo mightily aſſiſteth poore offenders, beeing worthily puniſhed for their miſdeedes, wyll he faile his who fight for his cauſe, that he wil not geue them an inuincible power? The third point concerning the promiſes that GOD hath made to his Martyrs, is of the fruite that they ought too hope for of their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes: and in the ende if neede be of death it ſelfe. Nowe this fruite is after that hee hath glorified his name, &amp; edified his Church through theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancie, when they ſhalbe gathered with the Lord Ieſus Chriſt into his immortal glory. But becauſe that wee haue ſpoken more fully of it before, it is enough nowe too bring it in our remembrance. Wherfore let the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full learne too lifte vp theyr heades on high too this crown of immortality &amp; glory, whervnto God doth call them: to the end that he do them no hurte in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to forſake theyr preſent life for ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde: and to be aſſured of this ineſtimable benefite, let them alwayes haue before their eyes this confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie which they haue with our Lorde Ieſus, too be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde life in the middeſt of death, as he by the oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brye and ſhame of the croſſe, came too that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reſurrection in whiche conſiſteth al our felicitie ioye and triumphe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:33"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The third Sermon shewing how</hi> the Faithfull ought too eſteeme the <hi>beeyng in the Churche of GOD, where</hi> they haue free libertie purely to woorſhip <hi>God, gathered vpon the theame of the 27.</hi> Pſalme. I haue required one thing of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Ver. 4.</note> and that I wil require: it is, that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the daies of my lyfe, too the end I may he hold the beautie of the Lord and may viſite his holy Temple.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> is woonderfull what a diuerſitie a man ſhall finde in mens deſires: and yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding there is one thing wherein all agree and iumpe togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that is to bee occupied here beneth in the worlde. Euery man may well haue his marke and meane by hymſelfe: but this vanitie raigneth ouer all, not to ſeeke their good, and felicitie any where elſe but in this corruptible life. The which ſheweth that men are wonderful brutiſh: For wee are created too an ende altogeather contrary and that is that hauing our conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this worlde wee ſhoulde aſpyre to that heauenly kingdome of GOD. And this is the cauſe, why this preſent life is called a pilgrimage or away. Wherefore whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer will not depriue him ſelfe wittingly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly of the euerlaſting inheritaunce of the kingdom of God, hee muſt beginne at this point too cut of all foolyſhe deſires and light thoughtes, whereby hee may bee occupied and witholden in this worlde:
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7693:33"/> ſo as his principall deſire be to draw neare vnto God, and that nothing at the leaſt hinder vs from making haſte thither. I ſay at the leaſt, foraſmuch as it were very requiſite that all our earthly affections which do nothing but cauſe vs to drawe backe from God, were fully rooted out of our heartes, to the ende wee maye runne through ſwiftly in this voyage wee haue too perfourme. But becauſe we are ſo farre of from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a minde that is pure and voyde from all affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it remayneth in the ſeconde place, that wee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all the lettes that may hinder vs, and followe our courſe howſoeuer it be: ſo as in the middeſt of our infirmities, we doe neuertheleſſe preferre the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly life before all that is in this world. It remaineth nowe, that we ſee by what meanes wee may attayne theereto.</p>
            <p>Nowe this is not in vs to deuiſe, but we muſt take theſe which God hath ordeined: of which the moſt principall are named heereby Dauid: to wit, the order and pollicie, that God hath eſtabliſhed in his Churche that we be taught by his woorde, that wee woorſhip him all with one accorde, and cal vpon him, and haue the vſe of the Sacramentes to ayde vs herevnto. And thus muſt wee be exerciſed, too the ende we way bee better &amp; better confirmed in the faith, in the feare of God, in holyneſſe, in the contempt of this worlde and in the loue of the heauenly life. And to this purpoſe and none other, tendeth this that Dauid proteſteth, that he hath a deſire aboue all to dwel in the temple of God. For vnder this woorde of the Temple he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth the libertie of hauing freedome purely to worſhip God with the faithful, to make confeſſion of his faith, to pray &amp; to be a partaker in the ſacraments.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:34"/> For God for this time had choſen a certaine place, in which he woulde that men ſhoulde ſacrifice vntoo him, ſhoulde doe him homage, proteſting that they accounted him for theyr alone God, were inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in his lawe, &amp; had the teſtimonies of his preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And indeede he ſufficiently expreſſeth what regard he had, in deſiring to dwell in the Temple, when hee addeth, that he was in the beautie of God. Wherein he ſheweth that the Temple of it ſelfe was nothing: but that he reſted him ſelfe in the vſe whereto it was conſecrated and appointed. If we thinke that he was occupied with a materiall building of wood &amp; ſtone wee ſhoulde doo him great iniury and wrong: For this were to charge him with ſuperſtition, and not too attribute it to his vertue. We ought therefore to bee reſolued, that hee ſetteth foorth howe honourably hee eſteemed the outwarde order and regiment whereby the faithfull are gouerned in the Church. To be ſhort he ſignifieth that this is an ineſtimable benefite, and a eſpeiall priuiledge to be in the Churche of God, to be a partaker of thoſe meanes, that that good father hath geuen to his children thereby too draw them to him. Let vs marke well who it is that ſpeaketh. It is not a poore Idiote without knowledge and experience: but a Prophete, as excellent and as greatly enlightned by the holy Ghoſt as euer was any. Hee ſpeaketh not of a thing profitable and good in the populare opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: but he proteſteth for his owne parte, that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired nothing more then that he might bee founde in the aſſemblie of the people of GOD, too the ende that declaring his faith hee myght alwayes bee more edified therein, through the doctrine of ſaluation which is there preached, and through the ſacraments: neither onely in this place maketh he this proteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7693:34"/> but in many other places, as in the Pſalme before go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, when hee ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.8.</note> 
               <hi>O Lorde I haue loued the habitation of thine houſe &amp; the place where thy glory hath his dwelling. Alſo in the</hi> 42. <hi>pſ. As the Hart br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> hee refreſhed with the riuers of Water, ſo pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teth my ſoule after thee O Lorde: My ſoule bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with thyrſt in ſeeking after God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.<hi>1.</hi>2</note> 
               <hi>When ſhall it bee that I ſhall come and appeare before the face of the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yng God?</hi> It had beene enough to haue ſpoken this: but his vehemente affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> carrieth him higher: for he addeth immediatly <hi>that teares were his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yng the time that hee was depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from comming too the Temple.</hi> Yea he ſayth yet further that his hearte was powred out like water, when hee remembred the time wherein he went to the Temple praiſing GOD with the multitude of the faithfull. Afterwardes hauing mourned his fill and powred foorth his complaintes and griefes, hee findeth no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſolation, then in the hope that he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued that God would reſtore that benefite againe which he had loſte. <hi>My ſoule</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>why art thou vexed and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet within me?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>84.</hi>12.</note> 
               <hi>yet ſhall I fynde againe the preſence of the Lord</hi> As alſo in the 43. Pſalme he repeateth againe the ſame matter. And eſpecially in the 84. Pſalme, he declareth howe he was affected towardes it. For after that hee hath cried out, <hi>O God of hoſtes howe amiable are thy taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles!</hi> hee ſayth <hi>that his hearte and his body d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e leape for the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deſire that he hath to enter into the countes of the Lord. And</hi> he ſetteth downe the reaſon, <hi>that they which dwell in the houſe of God are bleſſed becauſe they prayſe him</hi> that is to ſay, they acknowledge his graces with one accord, &amp; they reioyce in him, making co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr faith. Seeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that dauid who was ſo much adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced in al holines, yea &amp; was as an angel of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dwelling in the world acknowledged that he had ſo great neede to be aided and ſtirred vp by the meanes that god had giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his people.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:35"/> I pray you what is too bee ſuppoſed of vs, who are ſo rude &amp; earthly, whoſe faith is ſo weake, &amp; whoſe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is ſo colde and barraine? Wee muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, albeit that Dauid for the perfection that was in him might wel haue let ſlip ſuch baſe helps, yet they are more then neceſſary for vs: conſidering the infirmity that is in vs. But what? They who are the perfecteſt know much better what they lacke them ſelues, then thoſe which haue no perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at all. What is Dauid ſo indued and adorned with angelical vertues? Why, this is to make him better too vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, howe meet it was for him to be more enflamed by the preaching of the law, by the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and other like exerciſes. Contrarywiſe theſe glorious villaines that at this day make no reckoning of all theſe thinges, ſhewe euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereby, that they haue not ſo much as a droppe of of Chriſtianitie in them: I ſpeake of our corner cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and caſkate Philoſophers, that liue in Papiſtrie. O it is a goodly matter (ſay they) and much to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that a man cannot be a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnleſſe he not to Geneua, to haue his eares filled with Sermons, and to vſe ſuche Ceremonies as are obſerued in that Citie. Can not we our ſelues alone both reade &amp; pray? Muſt men yet goe to Church to be taught, ſeeing that euery one hath the Scripture in his houſe? I anſweare here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, that wee binde no man to depart from that place where he dwelleth: yea when a man liues purely and ſerueth God as he ought amiddeſt the Popes tyrranny wee eſteeme an hundred times better of him, then of our ſelues who are in libertie and reſt. But the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is heere of two poinctes, to wit, whether they that feeling their owne infirmitie, and commyng to ſeeke in a Chriſtian Churche, ſuch a confirmation as Dauid
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7693:35"/> did at that time when the Temple was at Ieruſalem, doe not well: Alſo whether all generally, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe that are witholden by force ought not too ſigh, ſeeing them ſelues deſtitute of the ordinary meanes, which were to bring them to GOD? The very beaſts who haue no vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding nor reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they wil bray after their paſture, and thoſe who are called the children of God, ſhal not they care for that which ſerueth to nouryſh and mainteine their faith? And yet they are not contended thus proudly too treade vnder foote the moſt precious graces of God, but they alſo ſcorne them which flie into ſtraunge countries to ſeek them, &amp; to reioyce in them. As touching their haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, whereby they beare themſelues in hande, that Sermons, Common prayers, and the Sacraments are thinges ſuperfluous and vayne, there neede no other teſtimony to excommunicate, and baniſh them out of the Churche of God. And that it is euen ſo, Sainte Paule, ſayth not that the order which God hath ſet in his Churche, is onely for the rude and ignoraunt: but he maketh it Common for all, exempting none. <hi>Hee hath ordained</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>Apoſtles, Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>, and Doctour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>for the eſtabliſhing of the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, for the building vp of the bodye of Chriſte, vntill wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, into the meaſure of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>fecte age in Chriſte.</hi> Let vs marke well that hee ſayth not that God hath lefte the Scripture to the end that euery one ſhoulde reade it alone: But hee hath inſtituted a policie wherein certain are appointed to teache &amp; vnder this he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth all other thinges which doeth, as it were depende therevpon. Wherefore though euery one may reade it priuatly, this leueth not but that they ſhould heare it alſo publiquely. And to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> directeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e
<pb facs="tcp:7693:36"/> but that they ſhold heare it publiquely. And to whom directeth he himſelf? to great &amp; ſmal indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. And doth he ſay that this is for one day? No ſurely he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth that this courſe be kept euen vntil death: for this was the tyme of our perfection. They therefore which diſdain to keep themſelues in this range to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite in faith and al vertue by the common order of the Church, they can by nothing ſo much cut themſelues of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fellowſhip of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God as by this. Let them excuſe the matter as finely &amp; as craftely as they liſt: yet the ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of S. Paule is moſt cleare, that none is neither aught to bee accompted of the body of chriſt, vnles that he ſubmit himſelf to this general rule. Wherfore my brethren let vs humble our ſelues and let vs not te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt god,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4.</note> thinking our ſelues able to fly with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out wings. But ſome ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil ſay, it is poſsible that Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſpake for the time of thoſe figures: bicauſe that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god gouerned his people as it were little childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo S. Paule ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.3.</note> &amp; therfore that thoſe feruent lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; hearty requeſtes that he maketh co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple are not ſo fitt for vs, ſeing that we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to thoſe, who being paſt our enfancie are come to a more ful age. To whom I anſwere firſt of al, that the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of being taught by ſermons, of being confirmed by the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, of being exerciſed in publike praiers &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our faith, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to vs with the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers. And herevnto te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d aſwel the promiſes eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe that are in the Prophet Eſay, where God ſaith that his Church ſhal haue infinite childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; that after ſhe hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued &amp; brought them forth, ſhe ſhall nuriſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp. It ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be denied that this belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth alſo to the kingdom of chriſt &amp; to this our time eſpecially. Now God expreſly fendeth his children into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7693:36"/> and lap of his Church. And wherfore is this, but that an order and rule might be kept, which hee hath appointed, to the end to gather his own togeather as it were by flocks? The which is notably expreſſed by an apt ſimilitude, which the Prophet himſelf vſeth in the 60. Chapter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 60.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſaiyng <hi>that the children of God ſhalbe at Donet who retire the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by flight into their Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cetes:</hi> And what I pray you is that ſame Douecote there, but euery place where the worde of God is preached, where the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are adminiſtred, and where the name of Godis called vpon &amp; praiſed? Indeede they which weene too be ſo ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that they haue no further need of this ſame outward order and gouernment, they il conſider their owne ſtate and condition. For wherefore hath God ordeined his ſacraments. vnleſſe becauſe that we being clothed with our bodies, we are too vile to lay holde vpon ſpiritual things, vnleſſe we be aided by theſe viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſignes? The angels indeede haue that trueth of the Sacraments, &amp; this ſuffiſeth them but God muſt come downe lower vnto vs, by reaſon of our rudeneſſe and ignorance. Let theſe fantaſtical Chriſtians ſtrip them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues hardly of their bodies, &amp; make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues angels of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; then they may exempt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe ſmall helpes wherof they make ſo litle account. But it behoueth al thoſe which acknowledge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they paſſe this way, to ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the ordinary pollicy, that god hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to all thoſe that are his. It is true that the grace of God is not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, nor the power of the holy ghoſt is not encloſed either in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or in any other outward thing, that he ſhold not be able to worke whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him without any meane: but here we intreat of the perpetual order that he hath ſet in his church: &amp; not of that which he worketh extraordinaryly, as it wereby myracle.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:37"/> Neuertheleſſe this is moſt true that they which are depriued of the vſe of the ſacraments, &amp; of libertie to call vpon his name, and yet feele not their wretched and miſerable condition, to the ende to bewaile it they are more blockiſh then brute beaſts. I ſay farther that if Dauid had iuſt occaſion in his time, to ſay. <hi>O Lorde how amiable is thy temple!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed are they that dwel in thy houſe. My ſoule burneth for very deſire, that it hath to enter into the Courtes of the Lord</hi> that we ought to bee twiſe as much mooued and inflamed vnto this, at this day. For what were the benefites of the Temple, which Dauid ſo much lamenteth, euen that he is weary of his life, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſelfe to be depriued of them? It is true that in ſubſtaunce they were the ſame that wee haue at this day: howbeit we knowe that theſe were but as darke ſhadowes, wherein GOD diſplaied not his grace ſo largely as we haue it at this preſent. For God hath declared himſelfe ſo familiarly to vs in the order of the Church, that as a man would ſay, the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens are opened vnto vs. The Sacraments do not ſhew Ieſus Chriſt ſo farre of as vnder the lawe: but ſetteth him liuely before our eyes. Wherfore we muſt needs be very vnthankful, if we preferre not theſe bleſſings farre before all that which Dauid might euer finde in the temple of Syon. We are not any more in the vtter Courts, as Dauid hath ſpoken. There is no more any vaile drawen, which might ſeparate vs from the ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary. To be ſhort, this is an euil honouring of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite greatneſſe of the benefites which God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon vs, when our deſire is not equall at the leaſt with that of Dauids. I ſpeake this by a ſimple forme of doctrine. For the exhortation ſhall followe after in his place. It remaineth then that wee ſee next
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7693:37"/> of all, what maner of deſire this was, to the ende that we may conforme our ſelues vnto it, as vnto our rule. <hi>I haue aſked; ſaith he, a thing of the Lord.</hi> By ſpeaking of one thinge alone, he ſignifieth that he was ſo mightily gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto it, that he caſt al other things behinde his back as if he had quite forgotten the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Was it ſo that hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed all his other deſires, in ſuch ſorte that there was nothing but this thing that fayled him? Contrarywiſe he was a fugitiue from the land of his birth, yea bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from the houſe of his father, and from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of his Parents and friendes: he was ſpoyled of al his goods, and depriued of all his dignities &amp; honours which were very great, his wife was rauiſhed: to bee ſhort, loe a man altogither deſolate &amp; quite forſaken. Neuertheles he lamenteth nothing but this one thing, that is to ſay, to haue acceſſe to the Temple, as alſo on the contrary parte, when he giueth thanks vnto God, for al the benefits which he had beſtowed vpon him, after he had made mention of drinking and eating, of reſt and other commodyties of the body: hee ſetteth downe for concluſion that he wil dwell in the church of God: whereby he proteſteth that beeing at his eaſe and in all pleaſure, notwithſtanding he accounteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more pretious then to be in the company of the faithfull,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 23.</note> to be lead vnto that ſame ſoueraigne hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe. Let vs then diligently marke that Dauid aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in his afflictions as in his proſperities, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes this ſame courage to reioyce himſelfe in this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie that God had giuen vnto the children of Iſrael: which cannot be accounted any ſmall vertue. Wee ſhall finde many who beeing oppreſſed with aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and afflictions, doe remember God gladly: but as ſoone as they are deliuered from them, &amp; that they
<pb facs="tcp:7693:38"/> find their eaſe, then they caſt of all reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of him: yea, &amp; which is moſt ſhameful they kick and fling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as reſty Iades that are to wel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed. Others ſo vexe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; rage againſt god in their aduerſity, that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not abide to heare any ſpeach of him. Was not Dauid throwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe with ſuch an heape of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, that hee ſeemed the moſt miſerable creature in the world? And yet is he ſo far of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being wounded with the grief of his mind to vexe himſelfe, &amp; diſdain when god ſpeaketh vnto him, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe it is the only way wherby he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted: yea althogh he could not ſo ſoone thinke of God, but he lamenteth that he is baniſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, &amp; ſhut out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vſe of his ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; other exerciſes of faith, yet hath heno greater pleaſure then to lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuch an euil. Now on the other ſide was not this his chiefeſt labor? Had he ouercome his enimies to be peaceable in his realme &amp; renowmed amongſt al? had he the meane to plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dge himſelfe in all pleaſures? yet for al that he remained firme in this, that his true felicitie is to haue acceſſe to the temple, to the end he might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat with the order of the church. Wherfore we ſee that he proteſteth not in vaine too haue aſked this one thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: for it was ſo deare vnto him, that he did alwaies let goe the reſt for it. Let vs ſee now who it is amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs which hath ſuch a iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as Dauid had. They who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with felicitie in thoſe goodes which they haue in their handes, do they eſteem the libertie of calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of god purely, hearing his word preached, or vſing his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, more then their domeſtical reſt? There are very few that do ſo: but rather their fatnes maketh them ſo ſluggiſh that they care for nothing but for their pau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch &amp; to make good cheare. To be ſhort, the world is ſuch that it ſetteth more ſtore by a trough wel ſtuffed with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7693:38"/> meate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the church of God. If a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeake of the troubles which may come, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greatly feareth to be ſpoiled by warres, to ſuffer loſſes, griefes &amp; hatreds: but they neuer make any reckni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of loſing the prechi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the doctrine of their ſaluation, of the pure vſe of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; ſuch like helpes which ſerue to draw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neare vnto god: &amp; alſo one ſhal perceiue that they that are depriued therof are not greatly touched with it. If the reuenew come not in, at the ende of the yeere or at the quarter day, to the end they may keep ſuch a traine as their ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> driueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deſire: if their gaine and trades decay, if their credite bee loſt, they continually torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the ordinarie paſture of the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god (after which they ought greatly to hunger) is nothing vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And yet this is it that God ſheweth very wel by that threatning that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, that there cannot a greater euil come vntoo vs. I <hi>wil ſend</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a famine, not of bread nor of water:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 8.12.</note> (as if hee ſhold ſay this is a ſmal matter:) <hi>but of hearing my woorde.</hi> Wherfore my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let vs take good heede that we ſuffer not our ſelues, to be made brutiſh by the Deuil &amp; by the world, to the end that we haue not alwaies this benefit in eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue al others: that is to ſay, to be mainteined in the flock of god, vnder the outward or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; gouernment which he hath placed amongſt his owne. And this is yet better expreſſed vnto vs by that which Dauid addeth: that is, that he wil require again the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which he before had aſked. Wherby he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth that he had not ſome ſodain deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was quickly cooled, but that he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; ſtil remained ſearching after this benefite, wee ſhall ſee ſome which wil bee ſo well affected for a little time, that it ſeemeth the next day, they would forſak al that euer they haue: but this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie wherof Dauid ſpeaketh is a very rare thing.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:39"/> yea the moſt part in ſteed of blowing the fire to kindle the good zeale that God hath put in them, do witting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quench it. We haue the like teſtimony concerning Dauid in the Pſalme which I haue already rehearſed: for becauſe that it might haue beene layde before him that being driuen out of the Counrrey of Iudea, hee might haue gone here or there too ſome other place: He crieth out <hi>Thy Altars O Lorde of Hoſtes, my God and my King.</hi> As if he ſhoulde haue ſaid that hee could not find a delectable place, although that he poſſeſt all the pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the worlde, when he had no entraunce into the Temple of GOD. He complaineth that the Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and the Swallowes found a place there to make their Neſtes, and that his condition was woorſe. And why was this? Was it becauſe he had neither cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nor Kitchin? He ſaith not ſo but becauſe he found no good nor meete place, foraſmuch as he was ſhut out and driuen away from the Aultars of GOD. It is very certaine that if this doctrine were entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our heartes, we ſhoulde not be ſo, neither one ſorte ſoo hindred, nor the other ſo quite turned away from exerciſing our ſelues in the meanes that God hath put into our hande, to helpe vs forwarde in the path of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life. But what is the cauſe therof? Ambition holdeth back the one ſort with dignities or high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, and entiſeth others to purchaſe and to ſeeke them. Couetouſneſſe enflameth and carrieth awaye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: many haue nothing in their hearte but theyr vaine pleaſures and wanton delightes. Yea, all lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhe and wallowe in their luſtes? ſo as none crye out. <hi>Thy Aulters O Lorde, where are thy Aultars my God my king?</hi> And indeede the vanities of the worlde raigne to muche in them, to ſuffer God too bee obeyed. This
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7693:39"/> This woorde alſo is of great importaunce, when Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid ſaith, that he hath demaunded of God the thinge whereof he ſpeaketh: for it ſhall be an eaſie matter to make ſuch a goodly ſhew before men, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would deeme all fire in vs. But loe, a man might ſay that this was in good earneſt, that he deſired to be in that flock: though he haue none but God alone to be witneſſe therof, he hath neuertheleſſe this affection. For when we come before ſuch a Iudge, al hypocriſie muſt ceaſe, and there muſt be nothing but plaine dealing &amp; trueth. Would we then followe the example of Dauid? Let euery one enter into his owne conſcience, and in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting his prayer vnto God, Let him ſay: Lord thou knoweſt howe I eſteeme to be in thy Church aboue all the goods in the world. Moreouer we are heere aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well put in minde, not to gnawe out bitte, to lament and grudge at our eſtate: but wee ought directly too ſend our ſighes to him, who can remedie our euill. In deede we ought to knowe that this horrible diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is at this day in the worlde, in that the whole ſeruice and worſhip of God is corrupted, the word of god falſifyed, the ſacraments adulterated and defiled, to be a iuſt vengeaunce vppon our ſinnes. To whom is it then, that we ſhould haue recourſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the pure doctrine, the Sacramentes, and libertie to call vpon the name of God, and to make confeſſion of our faith, but to him who chaſtiſeth vs, in depriuing vs there, of theſe benefits? And it muſt not be that the rigour of Gods chaſtiſements turne vs away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto him: and much leſſe muſt we kick againſt the prick, thereby grudging and diſdayning with our ſelues, in not ſeeking the medicine at his hande who hath giuen vs the wound. Certainly Dauid vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb facs="tcp:7693:40"/> very wel, that he was not baniſhed from the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of Iudea, without the prouidence of God, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he leaueth not to come vnto him &amp; to make his complaintes too him. Not for that it was not a greate griefe and harde temptation vnto him, to ſee himſelfe in apparaunce chaſed &amp; caſt out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God: but the fayth that he had in the promiſe which was made vnto him lifted him vp to pray vnto god, that he would alwaies reſtore the fruition of that thing vnto him, which he had for a tyme taken from him I haue (as I thinke) ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently enough applied this doctrine to vs, and to the ſtate of this tyme, were it not that they were ſo many dul wittes that can ſwallowe downe nothing, vnleſſe the matter propounded bee minced and chewed vnto them againe and againe. Although (too ſay the very truth) the ſlendernes of their capacitie doth not hinder them, nor the obſcuritie of doctrine: but that of their owne wicked willes, they ſo entangle themſelues ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king al the ſtarting holes, that they can imagine too darken that which of it ſelfe is ſo plaine and euident. Neuertheleſſe ſuch kind of reſiſtaunce, conſtraineth vs the more diligently too ſearche out, how this doctrine which we haue before ſet foorth, may be applyed to our tyme. I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that there is no more any ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, whether we ſhold go on pilgrimage to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vnto god: but that we are at this day ſpiritual te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, &amp; that we ought in al places to lift vp pure hands vnto heauen: notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the order of calling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of god in the companie of the faithful, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies one &amp; laſteth for euer: for it is not to be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the figures of the olde Teſtament: but it is the rule that our Lord Ieſus Chriſte hath giuen vntill the end of the world. Wherfore albeit wee differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7693:40"/> concerning that Temple of Sion and in Sacrifices, yet herein we agree and are like, that we pray vntoo God in common, and do aſſemble our ſelues together to make confeſſion of our faith. It is very true that we are no more as little children, holden vnder the tuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; ſcholing of the lawe of Moyſes: but yet we are men, &amp; ſhalbe till God take vs away out of the world. So though the ſhadowes and figures which were in Dauids time, belong not any more vnto vs, yet haue we neede to be ſtirred vp and drawen by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell and adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. If any man wil ſtriue againſt this order, why, very experience will conuince him: For they that be moſt able doe ſhewe euidently what neceſſitie they haue of this helpe of God to relieue their weakeneſſe. We diſpute not here: to wit, whether God can leade thoſe that are his without any inferiour meane: but to declare how his wil is, to gouerne and to leade them. For this is certayne that ſeeing our weakenes, he hath geuen vnto vs as it were croutches &amp; ſtaues for vs to ſtay vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What folly were it I pray you, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we feele that our legges faile vs, to make no reckoning of our props and croutches, as though they ſhould ſtand vs in no ſteede at all? Let vs know then, that whatſoeuer difference there is betwixt vs and the Iewes, yet that the doctrine which Dauid ſetteth downe here is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all: onely we haue to change the name of the Temple, becauſe we are no longer tied too anye one certayne place: Notwithſtanding the thing which Dauid chiefly regarded, toucheth vs no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf. It is very true that hawtie and proude men make no great matter, that men aſſemble themſelues to heare
<pb facs="tcp:7693:41"/> Sermons, to make publique prayers and too admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Sacramentes: but this is the want that they doo not examine their conſcience. For our partes ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is none other but Gods ordinaunce, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues, in that it hath pleaſed him by ſuche meanes, too cheryſhe and ſuſteine our faith in ſuche weakneſſe: But yet (as we haue before declared) wee feele the profite which commeth thereof. Howſoeuer it be, ſeeing Saint Paule hath declared that the way to perfection, is to keepe the order of the church which Chriſte hath inſtituted, when he gaue Paſtors accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the arrogancy of them, that will flye vp into the aire, &amp; pretend to mount vp into heauen by their ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, in deſpiſing both preaching and the vſe of the Sacraments: as though theſe were outward things and not ſo much requiſite. Marke well my brethren of what maner of people I ſpeake. I confeſſe that GOD keepeth thoſe that are his vnder the captiuitie of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſte, albeit that they be deſtitute of thoſe helpes which we enioy with great liberty. The word of god is not preached vnto them, neither haue they any place wherein it is lawful for them too make confeſſion of theyr faith, yea, the Sacramentes are taken from them: but foraſmuch as in ſeparating the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Antichriſt, they ſigh &amp; lament for not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that which were more profitable for them, God worketh in them by the power of his holy ſpirite, and ſupplieth that which is wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, But there are others who for the moſt part being in ſuch deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do yet neuertheleſſe pleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: and being hunger bitten and ſtarued, haue no luſt at all too eate. Theſe are they whiche counterfayte them ſelues to be great Philoſophers, contenting them ſelues too haue read
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7693:41"/> ouer a leafe or two, as a man would ſay, and then they thinke they know what ſoeuer is neceſſary for them. Theſe men thinke they haue no neede of any preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng. And as concerning the Supper they make no accounte whether euer they come too it or no. And as concernyng the outward order of the Church they leaue that vnto little children, as though it were too baſe for them. I pray you may we not thinke ſuch people too bee more then blinde? Notwithſtanding they can accuſe vs becauſe that wee exhorte them too whom our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte hath declared his trueth, to vſe the meanes that God hath ordeined for the encreaſing preſeruation and continuance of our faith. And wherefore is this, vnleſſe it be becauſe they ſtarckle, &amp; can not abide to be awakened by vs, to the ende too make them feele theyr euill? I put the caſe that they did not commit Idolatry with the Papiſtes: yet can they not deny but that this is a miſerable and curſed bondage, that they cannot be ſuffered too call vppon the name of God and too confeſſe Ieſus Chriſte. The holy Ghoſte when thee woulde peerce the heartes of the faithfull who were captiue in Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, putteth this ſentence into their mouth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.4.</note> 
               <hi>How ſhal wee ſing the prayſes of the Lorde in a ſtraunge lande?</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that the kingdome of God is at this day through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the worlde, and that there is now no difference betweene Iudea and other Countreis: But I ſay not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the Countrey where the ſeruice of God is aboliſhed, and true religion caſt of, it well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth to be accounted for a ſtrange and prophane Countrey. It muſt needes bee then, that they whiche haue no remorſe, not too dare to make proteſtation of their faith: nor to celebrate or ſet foorth the name of
<pb facs="tcp:7693:42"/> God, that they be altogeather blockiſhe: Now let the children of God take heede by this admonition not to become blockiſh with them. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning thoſe which babble, ſcorning and deriding vs in this, asking whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no man can goe to heauen, but by Geneua: wold to GOD that they had the heart and care to aſſemble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues together in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, in what part ſoeuer they becom, &amp; that they would erect ſome forme of a Church, aſwel in theyr owne houſes as in their neighbours, to do for their part that which wee doe here in our Churches. But what? in diſdaining to vſe the meanes that GOD hath geuen vnto them, they will be counted religious and ſo be ſaued. This were euen aſmuch as if they ſhold aſke whether they might not ariue at the Hauen going quite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they might not by tempting God boaſt of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour. But let them be as bolde and bragge as they liſt too breake the yoke: yet let all the faithful take heede how they lyft vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with them: &amp; who ſoeuer hath not the meane to be in a Chriſtian Church, wher god is purely worſhipped, at the leaſt let them mourn day and night, with Dauid, Thine Altars O Lorde, there is nothing that I deſire but thine Altars my god and my king. And let this fire remaine alwayes kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in all good heartes, too the ende that whatſoeuer may fal out, that they think it not paineful to endure any thing, that the length of time coole them not from ſeeking alwayes to purchaſe to be gathered into a flocke, and to come to Chriſtes fold. Moreouer that euery one aduiſe well with him ſelfe howe hee may moſte ſpeedily gette him ſelfe too the ſtandarde: ſo ſoone as our Lorde ſhall geue him the meanes. For
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7693:42"/> this is the way too witneſſe, that a man dooth not faintlye make this requeſte too dwell in the houſe of God.</p>
            <p>Nowe too conclude, it remaineth that wee marke well that which Dauid addeth: that is, <hi>That he ſhal finde the beautie of the Lorde, and will conſider his Temple:</hi> For this is not all to exerciſe our ſelues with the faithfull in all the outward order of the Church, vnleſſe we haue our eyes bente to this ende, to knowe GOD better and better. Heere there are two things requiſite: one is that we be diligent to frequent ſermons, and publique prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. The ſeconde is, that we knowe wherefore wee frequente them. For manye come thither with a fooliſhe deuotion, imagining that they haue well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted themſelues, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue ſhewed themſelues at Church.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore my brethren take good heede, For it is to be feared, leſte the moſt parte finde themſelues condemned either in the one or in the other. Howe many be there that flee Sermons, and think themſelues beſt at eaſe if they neuer heare any ſpeaking thereof? But I leaue them there, as thoſe that fully ſhew them ſelues too bee contemners of God. Onely I ſpeake of the contempt or coldenes that is in many, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer remember to come to the Sermon, vnleſſe that the Sunday put them in minde thereof: and yet they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine they haue doone well, as though they woulde make vppe a number togither of many running too God. The Bell maye well ringe dayly, but it is enoughe if they ſhewe them ſelues at the ende of the weeke. They are called foure times euery ſunday: but they come very notably, if they be found there once.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:43"/> For there are that can ſufficiently diſpence, with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming once in xv. dayes. To be ſhort the greateſt ſort of the multitude verifie the olde Prouerb: <hi>The nearer the Churche the further from God.</hi> Yea and ſome be of the number of thoſe whoe haue forſaken their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey to come here to ſerue God, there are who yet in this behalf behaue themſelues negligently enough. What is too be doone then? foraſmuche as God hath ſhewed himſelfe vnto vs, let vs beholde his beautie. But wee muſt not caſt behinde our backe the manner of beholding it: and that is, that wee bee rauiſhed in the loue thereof, and chaunged into his likeneſſe, as S. Paule ſayth.<note place="margin">4. Cor. 3.<hi>18.</hi>
               </note> And that wee may the better doe this, it is meet that we be more attentiue then we are, or haue been accuſtomed too be, too marke that which God ſetteth foorth vnto vs in his Temple: For what is the cauſe that we reape ſo little fruite, but that we doe not more diligently apply our ſtudy to that which is there ſaide and doone? Thus we haue our eares beaten with continuall doctrine, whereas our heartes are no whit touched. Moreouer there are a great many which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heare &amp; vnderſtand a whole ſermon thorow, but here and there a woorde or halfe a worde rather with out regarde. Wherefore it is not without cauſe that Dauid ſpeaketh of viſiting the temple of the Lorde ſo diligently. And in very deede the great treaſures of the wiſedome of God which are there fet out vntoo vs, worthily deſerue that a man ſhoulde ſettle himſelfe carefully to marke them. But as I haue already tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, God woulde not that we ſhoulde ſo marke them that we ſhoulde returne emptie and without profite from them. Let vs knowe therefore that the doctrine hath profited and ſhewed her fruite in vs, when wee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7693:43"/> are dewly reformed to ſerue God: and this is it that Dauid meaneth in the 84. Pſalme, which wee haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged before, <hi>That they that dwel in the houſe of GOD ſhall prayſe him.</hi> To what end therefore doe we aſſemble our ſelues? Wherefore is the Goſpell preached vnto vs? Wherefore haue we Baptiſme and the Lords Supper: vnleſſe it be that God may be magnified in vs? Nowe this praiſe conſiſteth not onely in the tip of the tongue or the lippes, but it ſtretcheth out it ſelfe thorowe our whole life. And therefore it is ſaide in another place. <hi>I will waſh my handes ô Lorde in innocencie, and then I will enter into thy Aultar.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.6.</note> We ſee nowe what the true vſe of the whole order of the Church is, to wit, that we ſhoulde ſerue God purely. In the time of the lawe they which came to worſhip in the temple, eſpecially the Prieſts entering into it to doe their office waſhed themſelues. This ceremonie is paſte, but wee ought too keepe the trueth of it: that is, foraſmuch as we haue the meanes to leade vs to the ſeruice of God, we ought to walke in greater integritie then the other: For in aſmuch as God hath giuen vs the meanes, ſo much the leſſe are we to be excuſed, if we make them of no effect. If wee ſtumble, it is not becauſe we ſee not the path before our feete. If it fall out, that we goe out of the way it is not bicauſe god hath not more ſhined vnto vs the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If we be forgetful to do our dutie, it is not for want of beeing prouoked and ſtirred vp vnto it. To be ſhort God hath omitted no meane to further aduaunce our ſaluation. Let vs feare then that rebuke and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch that he maketh by his Prophet Eſay, in the 65. Chapter. <hi>I haue ſtretched out my hande all the day long,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 65.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and ſtifnecked people.</hi> If they which ſtay in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes of the Papacie ſhall not be ſpared, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they
<pb facs="tcp:7693:44"/> goe not right, what ſhall become of vs I pray you, who are nouriſhed in the houſe as it were in the ſight of our heauenly father? Some haue lefte their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey where they were borne, to gather themſelues here into a Chriſtian Churche: Others haue had a greater priuiledge, ſeeing it pleaſed GOD too viſite them at home, as it were in theyr owne neſt: nowe yf they which are naturally borne in that place, acknowledge not ſuch a ſingular benefite, that they may wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate themſelues to god, who is ſo nearely approched vnto them, ſhall ſuch an vnthankfulneſſe remaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed? Rather let them ſay, O Lorde thou haſte builte thy Temple, and erected thine Aultar amongeſt vs: geue vs grace therefore too purifie our ſelues too the ende wee doo not though our filthineſſe defile the holyneſſe of thy giftes, and that wee turne not the glorye of thy benefites intoo ſhame. Concerning thoſe that are come from a farre, let them take heede that they behaue and order themſelues ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyly as in the houſe of God. They may liue in other places in wickedneſſe: and they ſhoulde not come from the Papacie to leade a diſſolute life not comely for the Goſpel. And indeede there are ſome, it had bin much better they had broken their neckes than euer to haue ſet foote in this Church, too behaue themſelues ſo yll in it: Some linke in themſelues with ſcoffers, to harden and confirme them in theyr malice. Others become gluttons and drunkardes, others are make-bates and troubleſome. There are houſholdes where huſbandes and wiues agree like Dogges and Cattes. And certaine will ſeeme young princes, and play the counter faite Lordes without meaſure, and are wholy geuen too theyr pompe, and worldly ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7693:44"/> Others become ſo idle, ſo delicate, and ſo nice, that they cannot tell what it is too labour, and yet no liuing can content them. There are backbiters and ſlaunderers who woulde finde faulte with the verye Angelles of Paradiſe: and in aſmuche as they burſte with vices, they apply all theyr holineſſe to controule theyr neighbours: notwithſtanding they thinke that God is bounde and muche in their debt that come to Geneua: as though it had not been much better for them too haue remained ſtil in their owne Dung, then too haue come and geuen ſuche offences in the church of God. But if there haue beene ſuch miſchiefe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, let euery one ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d one, and if there be any yet which are altogeather incorrigible, let the children of God arme themſelues with this doctrine, that they bee not infected through their wicked life. In deede it muſt needs greatly greeue vs, when we ſee the church of God ſo prophaned: but foraſmuche as we muſt be as corne amongſt the chaffe, let vs learne patience tyll God ſhall ſeparate vs from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of the wicked. There is no doubt but that this Church ſhall be as a touchſtone to proue many. Howſoeuer it be, let vs ſtriue, that foraſmuch as God hath gathered vs togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into his houſholde, we may geue our ſelues to all puritie, in renouncing all the pollution of the worlde, too the end that our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt may allowe and account vs in the number of thoſe whiche haue called vppon his name without all hypocriſie in that great day.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:45"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>The fourth Sermon shewing what</hi> paine wee ought to take, too purchaſe <hi>libertie to ſerue GOD purely in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churche, vpon a Theame</hi> out of the 27. Pſalme. My heart hath ſayde of thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8.</note> ſeeke my face: I wyll ſeeke thy face O Lorde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S men throw themſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a woondetful confuſion, in letting the bridle looſe to theyr appetites and deſires: ſo alſo is it a great wiſedome in them that ſeeke after that that God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded them, to the ende to follow it. And of this thing wee haue heere a goodly exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. Dauid was a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much ſubiect to the ſame paſſions, which torment and toſſe vs hyther and thither: and there is no doubt but that he was prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with many temptations which might well haue ſhaken his minde, and haue cauſed him to ſtray from God. Howbeit to remedy all occaſions of falling and to haue a certaine and ſure path, hee onely regardeth that which God ſhewed him: he meditateth and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually thinketh vp it. The ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me is that God biddeth &amp; exhorteh al the faithful to ſeeke his face. Dauid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth to haue applied al his ſtudy to this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: in ſuch ſort that there was as it were a goodly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody, &amp; agreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betweene god who ſpeaketh ſaying, ſeke me &amp; him who anſwereth, yea my god I wil ſeeke thee. But here we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider wherfore God expreſly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7693:45"/> mentioneth this woorde <hi>face,</hi> For if he haue not ſome face, wherein he ſheweth himſelfe, he ſhoulde deceiue vs in commaunding vs too ſeeke it. I know that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men who are full of ſubtilties make no more of it, then if he had ſaide ſeeke me: but they which are wel exerciſed in the Scripture, knowe very well that God would ſpecifie, that manner of ſhewing and declaring himſelfe familiarly too men, which he hath kept in al times. And indeede this is an often and vſuall ſpeache in the Scripture, to call the ſanctuary and the arke of the couenaunt the face of God. And wherfore is this It is becauſe God who is incomprehenſible in his Eſſence and Maieſtie, vſeth ſuch meanes as hee know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be meete for mens rudeneſſe and infirmitie, too the ende to drawe them vnto himſelfe. It is true that the world forgeth alwayes falſe and vaine ſhapes of God: but all that we imagine of our owne braine, are nothing elſe but falſe viſors whereby GOD is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed: or too ſpeake more plainely, when men forge ſome forme or remembraunce to haue GOD viſible with them, they haue nothing but an Idoll. But when GOD repreſenteth himſelfe according too his owne pleaſure, and geueth vs euident ſignes and tokens to be knowen of vs, then he taketh as it were a face. And hereupon it is, that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth that euery one of vs do turne our ſight thither, &amp; that we be diligent to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it. For it is alſo one ſoueraigne good, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee ought to be fully ſatiſfied, to reioyce in the countenance of our God as it is ſaide in the 16. Pſalm.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pal.</hi> 16.11</note> Now becauſe we cannot climbe vp ſo high without a Ladder, the ſeconde benefite that he can beſtow vpon vs, is too geue vs the meane to attaine too that princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal &amp; chiefe goodnes. Wherfore let vs note that this
<pb facs="tcp:7693:46"/> ſentence where God ſayth: <hi>ſeeke my face,</hi> is as much as if he ſhoulde open the gate to make vs to enter into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting life. It ſeemeth that it was not ſo great a matter in the time of Dauid too come to the Temple, to ſee ſuch a heape of Ceremonies as they obſerued there: but if we conſider well that ſpirituall patterne which was ſhewed to Moyſes in the mountaine, wee ſhall not thinke it ſtrange that God ſayth it is his face. And indeede ſeeing that Ieſus Chriſte was there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, what ſhall we ſay elſe but that God was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there? Now let vs ſee if God hath ordeined any out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde meane vnto vs, to be ſeene of vs. It is true that he hath appeared vnto vs by his ſonne, who is his liue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly image, and in whoſe perſon he woulde be knowen in al perfection: but Saint Paul declareth foorthwith, in the 4. of the 2. to the Corinthians, that the Goſpell is that looking glaſſe wherein Ieſus Chriſte muſt bee ſeene and conſidered.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.<hi>4</hi>
               </note> The Sacramentes haue one and the ſame nature: &amp; to be ſhort, the order of the church, I meane ſuch as God hath eſtabliſhed in it, doeth ſhew the ſame vnto vs. Therfore let theſe proude gallantes of the worlde mocke as much as they liſt: but foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as God hath ſhewed this benefite too ſtoupe ſo lowe vnto vs, let vs not be aſhamed to geue this honor vnto his woorde and to his Sacramentes: in them to behold as it were his face: not to the ende to be holden here beneth in the corruptible Elementes of the world as the Papiſtes who make Idols of all the ſignes that God hath geuen vs too leade vs too Ieſus Chriſte: but neuertheleſſe too the ende we may fully reioyce in the preſence of GOD, we muſt goe vntoo him by theſe inferiour meanes. It is true that this whiche I ſay muſt not be to ſtricktly taken, as though the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7693:46"/> neuer drew neare to God, but when they come to Church: For this ſhoulde be a foule ſuperſtition. But I meane that we muſt not place God ſo high aboue the cloudes: as ſome fantaſticall heades do, &amp; imagin of his high maieſtie as ſeemeth good vnto vs, neglecting and caſting behinde out backes aſwell the preaching of the goſpell, as other ſuch like meanes and helpes: as though men coulde ſee when they ſhut their eyes. For in very trueth they who deſpiſe as I ſay, not onely the vſe of the ſacraments as alſo al the order of the church they diſdayne to looke vpon God when he appeareth vnto them. Let vs marke nowe howe neceſſary it is for vs, that God ſtirre vs vp to come vnto him. Wee haue already ſayde what fauour and honour he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he calleth vs ſo gently vnto him to ſet forwarde our ſaluation, and too leade vs too the true perfect felicitie from which we are far enough of in reſpect of our ſelues. But we haue alſo too note that it is not without great neceſſitie, that God pricketh and prouoketh vs too take heede that we fall not into mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all, we haue ſo wanton and wandring eyes, that it ſeemeth a very miſerable caſe. For nothing occupie all ourſelues but the vanities of this worlde, and Satan hath infinite illuſions to deceiue vs. It is true that all his ſubtilties are nothing elſe but certaine mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meries and trifling ſhewes to occupie fooles: but experience ſheweth what fooles or rather madbraines we are, in ſuffering ourſelues to be too too eaſily delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and deceiued. Wherefore if wee were wiſe and well aduiſed this voyce of god woulde alwayes ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in our eares, <hi>Seeke my face.</hi> But what? Foraſmuch as god is careful for his part, we are the more careles &amp; ſlow.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:47"/> And woulde to God we were not like kicking and reſty Iades that in ſteede of going forwardes draw backwardes. Neuertheleſſe this example is not ſet foorth vnto vs in vaine: For the proteſtation whiche Dauid maketh, of meditating this doctrine in his heart, that he and all the faithfull ought too ſeeke the face of God, ſheweth vs wherto we ought to employ our ſtudy, that God looſe not his labour in calling vs too himſelfe. Nowe he ioyneth here two pointes, which are woorthy too be marked. The firſt is that when God hath ſpoken <hi>ſeek my face:</hi> that he anſwereth too this voyce with an earneſt affection of the hearte, The ſeconde is, that after he hath conſented and ſayd, yea: he ſayth that he wil employ him ſelfe indeede, to ſeeke the face of God. And in deede this is the order according too which we haue to proceede: that is, to geue entrance and acceſſe to that which God ſaith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, &amp; according to which hee hath alſo ſhewed vs in the Pſalme:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.8.</note> 
               <hi>This day if you heare his voice harden not your heartes:</hi> but there are fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d very few that do it. A great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber wil ſay wel to diſcharge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, yea, it is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: It is not lawfull too reply againſt him: but they ſhoulde ſuffer that too enter into theyr heart, that they confeſſe with their mouth. Therefore let vs learne to beginne at this pointe, that we anſwere GOD tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnfeignedly, that we doe fully vnderſtande the benefite that he hath beſtowed vpon vs, in bidding vs to beholde his face. If this once be doone, it cannot bee but the reſte ſhall followe: that is too ſaye, ſtrength too perfourme that which we knowe to be iuſtly commaunded vs, and for our ſingular benefite. For Dauid ſhewed that hee had not a colde or dead meditation without ſtirring either armes or legges:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7693:47"/> but hauing concluded that he muſt ſeeke God, he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe in the path, and proteſteth that he will purſue it. Now it is a great ſhame too them who call themſelues Chriſtians, ſo yll too put in practice both the one and the other. Some wyll alleadge that it is not lawfull for them too forſake the Countrey where they were borne, albeit they be deſtitute there of the foode of life, and that they haue nothing but deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, concerning the order of the Church: Why ſo? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the duety they beare to theyr naturall prince. To which I will make no longe reply, onely I aſke of them, if they had nothing to eate and too drinke in theyr owne houſe, whether they woulde be ſo ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to tarry there ſtill. There is none that would not boldly aduenture too forſake his Countrey, that hee might not ſtarue for hunger. I put a caſe which is not yet ſo priuiledged: that is, if a man ſhoulde geue them ſixe times as much ſubſtaunce as they haue, in a ſtrange countrey, whether they wold make any great curteſie, too goe quickly &amp; take poſſeſſion? To what purpoſe ſerueth it them to pretend theſe colours, ſeeing that may appeare to be farre from their hearte which they ſpeake? There is no queſtion here of going into their enimies lande, where they ſhall be conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to beare armes againſt their prince, to make warre with their naturall Countrey: but onely of ſeeking a place peaceably to ſerue God, where nothing ſhall let but they may praye for their Prince and for all his ſubiectes. Too bee ſhorte ſuche a iourney is none other, but ſuche as they make dayly for ſome earthly commodities, whiche is deuoyde of all crime and offence. But yet let vs ſee whether neceſſity doo not ſufficiently excuſe them that goe, Loe God
<pb facs="tcp:7693:48"/> who ſayth, <hi>Seeke my face:</hi> The princes of the wolde, butte againſt him, and turne their backs towards him: or rather they robbe the poore ſoules of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon foode: and in ſteede of Gods face, they ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theyr eyes the maſkes of ſuperſtitions. Muſt they be preferred before the liuing God? If GOD be to be heard, we muſt go rather a thouſand miles of to ſee his face, where it is ſhewed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lie neſtling in our neſts. So then as often as Princes wil attempt any thing, in preiudice of him who hath all ſoueraigne authoritie aboue them, men do them no wrong in obeiyng him. Albeit, beſides that which I haue ſaide, ſuche kinde of men ſhewe ſufficiently, that they neuer greatly wayed nor conſidered theyr owne ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And what a miſerable captiuitie is it, in whiche they are holden? Onleſſe their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience were too too ſluggiſhe, it were impoſſible but that they ſhoulde be in continual anguiſhe and diſtreſſe, as though they were tormented in Hell. And howe is it permitted vnto them, too honour GOD in their houſes? We neede not go farre for an example, If any of them haue a childe borne vntoo him, his duetie is too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him vp too GOD with prayers and geuing of thankes, requiring the Seale of ſaluation through Baptiſme to be imprinted into his body.</p>
            <p>Now we knowe that Baptiſme is ſoo corrupted in the Popedome, and ſo defiled with ſuperſtitions and filthineſſes, that a childe cannot receiue it, but he muſte out of hande be defiled with it. So a father cannot baptiſe his childe without ſinning. And if he abſteine, yet he is in the ſame tranſgreſſion, yf there were no more but the offence which he giueth too
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7693:48"/> men, in refuſing the Sacrament, that the ſonne of God hath inſtituted. And what a perplexitie is this, that a man can neither do not leaue vndoone ſuche a thing, but he muſt geeuouſly offende GOD? I omit the reſt, becauſe that this one example alone is more then enough. But when a man ſhall ſo miſerably languiſh all the dayes of his life, not knowing which way too turne him, yet in death great aſſaultes ſhall aſſaile him and then wyll the Diuel haue his whole armie in a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyneſſe againſt him. If the miſerable Captiue were in time too fore let from ſeruing of GOD, in reſpecte of his wife and family, then he ſhall be in woorſe caſe then euer before.</p>
            <p>They therefore who doubt whether it bee lawfull for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to rid themſelues foorth of ſuch filthiemud, or rather from ſuch an helliſh gulfe, vnder the colour of ſubiection they owe to their earthly Princes, certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ouerthrow the whole order of nature. It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry certaine that the prayer that God woulde haue vs too make to him for our princes, is agreeable too the authoritie that he hath geuen them ouer vs, and alſo to that duetie, wherewith he hath bound vs vnto them.<note place="margin">1. Tim. <hi>2.</hi>2</note> Nowe Saint Paule exhorteth vs, that men ſhould pray vnto God for Kings and Magiſtrates, too the ende that we might leade a peaceable and quiet life, with al honeſtie and feare of God. This ſubiection and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience therefore, which wee owe vntoo our earthly Princes, is ouermuch ſtretched out, when they would haue the ſeruice and honour of the king of heauen to geue place vnto it. It is verye true that thoſe poore Iewes muſt tarry in bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage at Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vntil that time was fulfilled that god had appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend, let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew that we are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de
<pb facs="tcp:7693:49"/> too depriue our ſelues of our owne accorde of thoſe ſame ſpirituall benefites which God hath bountifully beſtowed vpon his children. They feele the neceſſitie wherewith they are greeuouſly oppreſſed, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie prouoketh them, and God ſheweth them the remedy? What reaſon then is there, that they ſhoulde not dare too helpe themſelues to the end to complain of thoſe, who ſnatch the bread out of theyr handes? There is alſo another reaſon of the huſbande towards the wife, and of the wife towards the huſband. Foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as God hath knit them togeather as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one fleſhe, the one ſhould not doo well too forſake the other vnder colour of ſeeking God. Not for that they ſhould depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to maintayne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather: but becauſe that ech one ought diligently to labour that he might alſo draw his companion with him. Loe then what they ought to doo: that is, that the huſband doo ſhew the wyfe, howe miſerable and vnhappy they are, that are ſeparated from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and fellowſhip of the Faithfull, that are deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the woord and Sacraments, which are the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted pledges, too make vs aſſured that God dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with vs: And that therefore he exhort her not to diſtruſt, but too be of good comfort, and yf ſo be that he cannot win her, ſo ſoone as he would, that he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaue not of vntill he haue obteined his purpoſe. Although that the wife be vtterly againſt it, yet that he leaue not of to deale importunatly with her, vntyll that ſhe ſhew herſelf altogether obſtinat and wilful. If after he haue done al that which he ſhalbe able &amp; can no longer remaine there, he is altogether free &amp; at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie: for he hath performed his duety to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, &amp; for any thing that was in him, his wife might
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7693:49"/> haue followed him as ſhe was bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; ought to haue doone, Although that ſuch a kinde of departure from the wife is no deuorſe: but the huſbande goeth before to leade his wife the way. Now concerning the wife in aſmuch as ſhe is not the head, ſhe is bounde with a more ſtraight bonde. Therefore ſhe is bounde too la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by all maner of meanes (aſmuch as ſhalbe poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for her) too perſwade her huſbande, to the ſetting of both them two at libertie. When ſhe ſhall haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently perfourmed all this aſmuch as ſhe ſhalbe able, yet is ſhe not therefore at libertie, to leaue her huſband too whom ſhe is ſubiect, vnleſſe that ſome perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be rayſed, and that her manyfeſt daunger be in it: and ſpecially if her huſband be as it were a prouoker too perſecute her to death. Now then ſhee forſaketh not her huſband, but ſhe flyeth the euill which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for her, and the rage of her enimies as it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and graunted vnto her of god. To be ſhort, the conſtraint and force which is doone vnto her, freeth and ſetteth her at libertie: notwithſtandinge no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the worlde ought to witholde the huſbande or the wife one from the other, but onely the mutuall loue which they owe one to the other in God, for the procuring of ech others ſaluation. For if the huſband muſt forget him ſelfe concerning that which belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to this earthly life and to the body, he muſt haue no regarde too any thing that any whit belongeth to him ſelfe. Let vs returne therefore too this eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation which Dauid maketh of ſeeking the face of God, as alſo he ſpeaketh thereof in the 84. Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11.</note> ſaying. <hi>that it is better to liue one day in the courtes of the Lord then a thouſande too bee farre from it.</hi> Wherein he ſignifieth that the lyfe of the faithfull cannot bee too ſhorte, ſoo
<pb facs="tcp:7693:50"/> that GOD ſhew them this grace, that liuing in this worlde, they exerciſe themſelues in ſcruing and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng him, confirming them ſelues in his promiſes, &amp; making confeſſion of his name. If any man obiecte that this might well be doone in ſome wilderneſſe, or amongeſt the enimies of the faith: I anſwere that it is not without cauſe, that Dauid expreſly mentioneth: <hi>the courtes of the Temple:</hi> For he conſidered howe neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the order of the Churche is too all mortall men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially knowyng the bluntneſſe and infirmitie that is in them. If this admonition were well imprinted in the heartes of all, all at the leaſte woulde come into ſome Chriſtian Churche where they might dye qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly and peaceably, and there would not bee any one that would not quickly truſſe vp his pack and be trud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging. But what ſeeke we? All deſire too liue, and that at their eaſe, &amp; euery one according to the luſt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he is led. And this is the cauſe why the temple of GOD at this day is neglected and contemned. Yea which is more, there are very many ſubtill ones, too ſet before mens eies euyll allurementes and ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blockes too turne vs awaye from that ſtudy of godlineſſe that was in Dauid. They alleage what ſhal it profite vs to chaunge the place: whether ſoeuer wee goe, we ſhall finde the worlde there aſwell as in our Countrey: all at this day is corrupted, there are like offences in all places, and temptations too make men fall from God. I graunt them al this. But if the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion were of their bodies, and that they were admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed that in ſome place they might fynde good phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, fit remedies and other helpes for theyr health, woulde they ſay, that they cared not for them, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7693:50"/> that men mighte bee ſicke in any place of the worlde? I confeſſe that where ſoeuer we become, that we ſhall finde many occaſions to doo euill, and many occaſions of falling away: but there is a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, whether we haue thoſe helpes which GOD hath giuen vnto vs to keepe vs in dooing our dewtie and reforming vs, or to be quite deſtitute thereof. Let vs put the caſe that all vices doe equally reigne in the worlde, ſo that the very ayre is infected therewith, as it were with a Peſtilence: Is it not a greate aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to haue the preſeruatiues that God hath orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for his Children? to haue thoſe purgations and medicines, whereby hee woulde heale vs? Nowe I meane alwayes the doctrine of the Goſpell when it is purely preached: as alſo the Sacramentes when they are rightly miniſtred as it becommeth: then alſo publique prayers and other meanes which ſerue too the ſtirring of vs vp, and awakening of vs, that wee ſhould not be poyſoned with the temptations of the world. Now euery man knoweth that nothing of all this is found in the papacie, but rather altogither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Let vs therefore take good heede, leaſt that in ſuch neceſſitie, wherein wee haue neede to bee ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured, we reiect not the helpes that GOD in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie hath offred vnto vs. There are others, whiche yet more playnely, vomite out the filth and diſeaſe of their ſtomack. Shall we goe (ſay they) to a Churche, wherein to our greate offence, wee ſhall ſee troubles and ſtumblinge blockes whiche are altogither vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen vnto vs? If in thoſe places where the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is preached, there were ſuch gouernment and polycie, as were moſte requiſite too edyfye vs,
<pb facs="tcp:7693:51"/> if we were ſure that we ſhoulde finde none but angels there that ſhould leade vs into Paradiſe, wee woulde runne thither moſt ſpeedily. But when we ſhall come thither we ſhal heare many thinges, and peraduenture more then were meete that ſhall doo nothing but of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs: Yea and there ſhalbe people geuen too all kinde of iniquitie, who through theyr lewd and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute life defame the Goſpel. Beſides that, vanities, pompes, drunkenneſſe and ſuch like thinges ſhal there beare to much ſway. And which is worſe to be borne, many ſhal ſhew them ſelues ſuch obſtinate and vnruly contemners of God, that more vngodlineſſe ſhall bee found amongſt them, then amongeſt the Papiſts. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore amongeſt the Magiſtrates and thoſe that ſit at the helue of iuſtice, there ſhalbe founde no leſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe and corruption then in other places: yea men ſhall finde many amongeſt the preachers that might be amended. Some wyl be founde negligent in their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, or rather they wil be ſo geuen to ſeeke their owne profite, that they wil haue no great care of their office. And which is worſt of all, there are amongeſt theſe ſome ieſters and belly Gods which deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but too make good cheare, and too make them ſelues companions of the wickeddeſt ſorte, that they may haue libertie too liue as they liſte. But let vs put the caſe thar it were ten times as yll as they ſay: yet notwithſtanding their excuſe is alwayes friuolous who ſet ſuch barres vnto them ſelues, leaſt they ſhould draw neare and come too the Churche of God.</p>
            <p>But let vs indeede fixe our eyes vpon the example of Dauid. I beſeech you, was there ſuch vprightnes in the eſtate of iuſtice in Saules time, as had beene too
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:7693:51"/> be wiſhed? Nay contrariwiſe we hear the complaints which they often times made aſwell of the malice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptes, crueltie, and pride of the king, as of his offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. Furthermore the Prieſts &amp; the Leuites, did they behaue them ſelues ſo holyly as men had occaſion to be contented therewith? Nay rather we maye gather that the greateſt parte of them cleaued vnto euill and nouriſhed theyr iniquities flattering them ſelues in them. And as concerning the common people, there was amongeſt them great hypocriſie, and many mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt vices and wickedneſſes. Loe then the Churche of God full of many corruptions, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Dauid lotheth not to enter therin, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that he had waxed not cold. This is a merueilous hard temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I confeſſe it: For the more that any is touched with the zeale and honour of God, ſo much the more iuſt cauſe he hath of greeuing and vexing himſelfe, when by the corruption of the Churche hee ſeeth the ſhameful things which are doone vnto him. But the remedie to ouercome all this, is ſhewed vs by Dauid: that is to ſay, that we ſeeke the face of God &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent our ſelues in the only beholding of him, that in deſpite of al the troubles which Satan rayſeth vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs, we on the contrary part ſet downe this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that there is nothing more pleaſant and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, then to dwell in the Temple of God, where we may behold his preſence. So, as often as ſuch offences ſhalbe ſet before vs, let vs reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that it is Satan that woorketh, according to his accuſtomed craft, that he may trouble our ſight: and therfore let vs be wiſe and wary that we be neuer led away from beholding the face of God, too the ende we may more fully reioyce our ſelues, in the beholding thereof. Let vs be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:7693:52"/> of thoſe miſerable Idolaters: for if any of them, after he hath ill ſpent his money, and waſted his body with trauaile, too goe on ſome foolyſhe pilgrimage, when he is come vnto that ſame place whither he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, he find ſome Hoſte which dealeth hardly with him, or ſome boiſteous knaues, which offer him violence, or ſome prieſtes which deceiue him, to be ſhort, he findeth nothing there but confuſion: yet for all this he deſiſteth not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his deuotion: For he will ſay, that he went thither for this cauſe, that he might ſee and woorſhip, eyther the body of ſome bleſſed Saint, or ſome image of our Lady, or els ſome ſuch relique: ſhall the onely beholding of ſome dead carrion or ſome apiſh Idol haue more power to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the vnbeleeuers in their ſuperſtitions, then the face and preſence of God ſhall haue towardes vs, in geuing vs conſtancie too follow that which is good? We ſee this thing and that thing which doth vexe vs: God calleth vs vnto himſelfe and woulde haue vs, in beholding his face and countenaunce too take ſuche pleaſure and delight, as wee might patiently beare all the reſt. Wherfore let this be the buckler and onely refuge of all the faithful &amp; godly to hold themſelues faſte, in the continuall contemplation of the face of God, howſoeuer Satan craftely goe about to turne vs from it. And in very deede when we ſhal ſo eſteeme it as it deſerueth, we ſhal ſuffer no damage in the loſſe of any other thinges whatſoeuer: albeit to ſay the trueth the greateſt part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be let and hindred not ſo much in the difficultie and diſcommoditie of thoſe things which concerne the body. Not but that the children of God haue very great and harde combates in their conſciences when they finde in the Churches whiche
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7693:52"/> are ſaide to be refourmed, thoſe offences whereof we haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before. And therfore they that aduiſe with themſelues to withdraw themſelues, into thoſe places where the Goſpel is preached, muſt be warned too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt greeuouſe aſſaultes &amp; too prepare them ſelues to withſtande them. And they alſo which haue had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience already, muſt fortifie themſelues, and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of the Deuill, conſtantly continue too ſeeke the face of God. But when all ſhalbe wel wayed, there is nothing but very diſtruſt, which ſlacketh and holdeth back the greateſt multitude: &amp; as men are very cunning to deuiſe excuſes, ſo the riche haue theirs on the one ſide, &amp; the pore haue theirs on the other. But how can it be, wil ſome great rich landed man ſay, that I ſhould ſpoyle my ſelfe of al that I haue? Shal I ſo go and ſtrip my ſelfe of al my goodes and poſſeſſions? I haue wife and children: and we haue been brought vp and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed without any trauayle: and what ſhall we do in a ſtraunge country where we ſhal neyther haue rents nor reuenewes? And againe the poore man he wil al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, indeede I haue but a little heere: but I haue friends who relieue me through their liberalitie, I am called to liue by my labor: what ſhal I do in a ſtrange countrey without peny or halpeny being altogeather vnknowen, hauing no fauour nor maintenance? And it may be that theſe excuſes may be in parte true: and without any further inquirie I graunt vnto all, that it is a very bitter &amp; troubleſome thing, not onely to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the countrey where we were borne, but any place wherin we haue dwelt. Notwithſtanding, al theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe howe they may ſet lets and ſtops before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues that they come not too GOD: that is to ſay, although they find, not onely things ſo hard as they make them:
<pb facs="tcp:7693:53"/> yet they willingly ſhroude them ſelues vnder any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text or colour whatſoeuer. Which is more, when they haue made their goodly complaynts, they thinke that they haue ſtopt Gods mouth, &amp; if that he would preſſe them any farther, that hee dooth them greate wrong, as though he compelled them to an impoſſible matter. To this I haue no other aunſwere, but that which is written in the 84.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7.</note> Pſalm, to wit, <hi>That the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gooing by the dry valleyes and deſertes, to goe vnto the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, ſhall dig vnto them ſelues pittes or ceſternes.</hi> And I beleeue that this is ſufficient inough to tame al thoſe, who will not through obſtinate mallice reſiſt God.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let thoſe which ſee them ſeles to be ſo beſet with difficulties, that they can ſee no way to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape out, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that euen the deſert places in which there is not to be founde one drop of water, ought not to ſtop their paſſage. And too the ende that wee may more fully vnderſtande this matter, let vs marke that God cauſeth his children to ſeeke him, not in the goodly medowes, or in thoſe ſame pleaſant and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful ſhadowes, but euen by ſharp &amp; roughe pathes, by rocky and ſtony places, through waſte and hidious regions, and all this he dooth too exerciſe their faith, and to try their zeale and deſire which they haue too come vnto him. Although then that we cannot come vnto God, but we muſt paſſe by ſome deſert and waſte way, yet let vs knowe, that this is not the firſte time that God hath ſo delt with his faithfull ones, and let vs be of good courage to followe thoſe which haue gone long time before vs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond poynt is, that there ought to bee ſuch a great and feruent deſire in the Children of God, that nothing ſhould let them from comming to woorſhip
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7693:53"/> him. The which thing at this day is to be ſeene in very fewe, al in a manner are as it were become ſo delicate and ſo nice, that there needs not (as a man woulde ſay) but the wagging of a ſtrawe too ſtop them and altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſtay them. They wil ſay we can goe no farther. And why ſo? Becauſe they wil not vouchſafe too take the payne, to leape ouer the leaſt block. It muſt needs be ſaid, that that zeale is very weake that is diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for ſo ſmal a thing. But wee muſt not onely bee aſtoniſhed ſo eaſily, but we muſt be armed againſt the greateſt lets and hinderances in the world. And that this may be brought about, let vs remember this leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God acknowledgeth none for his children, but they that ſeeke by dry and barren places, and whiche digge ceſternes where there was not any drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Now vnder this woorde hee ſignifieth vntoo vs, that there is no labour or troubleſo greate that is not meete for vs to endure, to the ende we may enioye the face of God. Is the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore of ſeeking a place, where a man may haue libertie of ſeruing of God and worſhipping him purely? how euil ſoeuer the paſſage be, be it as they ſay betwixt fire or water, let not a man leaue of to goe on forewarde. Is any man in gooing, pinched with famine or thirſt? yet therefore muſt hee not faint. Neither let any man ſo thinke as though I ſpake thereof at myne owne eaſe for it is the ſpirite of God, which teacheth vs, that rather the earth is too be ſcratched with our nayles, then wee too bee turned, or driuen backe from comming too the Temple of God. Now if they which dwel in farre countries, and in the iudgement of men are deſtitute and ſhut from al thoſe meanes, of drawing themſelues intoo the Countrie where the Goſpel is preached haue no excuſe, what
<pb facs="tcp:7693:54"/> condemnation I pray you, ought they too looke for, which haue the goſpel at their doore, &amp; yet vouchſafe not to moue one foote that they may enter intoo the temple of God? There are ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s had euery day, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like praiers are conceaued, that they might come too Church, and there is but the ſtepping ouer of one little brooke, to come thither, and yet euery one prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth that he hath ſome buſines in his houſe. To bee ſhort it ſeemeth that men place their felicitie in this too turne away from God. For it ſeemeth vntoo them that they haue gotten al, when they haue founde but one ſhifte, though it bee the moſt friuolous and lighteſt in the world. But ſeing that it is ſo that we are ſo enclined by nature to runne from God, yea to parte our ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him when he draweth neereſt vnto vs, let vs pray that he wil ſo ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthen vs that we may goe couragiouſly foreward, vntil that wee haue founde liuely foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines where there was nothing but drought before. And although that that ſhould faile vs, yet let vs digge ceſterns, wayting for raine from Heauen. And if it pleaſe God that we feele not his helpe ſo quickly, that yet wee giue not ouer too goe on forewarde. I doubt not but that this wil bee founde darke too many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: but wherefore is it, but euen for want of practiſe? wee may preach a hundred thouſande yeeres and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnderſtande a worde thereof, vntil that we learne by experience, what it is too goe by a drie and thirſtie way, when wee muſt come vnto God. But yet ought this doctrine too bee familiar too all the faithful, too wit, that they prepare and arme themſelues againſt all the temptations that Sathan can deuiſe againſt them, too breake of this path whereby they are brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>too
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7693:54"/> God. And in very deede al they which faithfully employ them ſelues too ſeeke God, although they goe not out of their place, yet they finde many lettes and incombraunces, which might eaſily turne them away if they had not a ſetled courage too reſiſt them. But it is great pitie, that the greateſt patte of them (as I haue alreadie ſaid) lie downe vnder thoſe difficulties which offer themſelues vnto them. They will graunt that they ought too doo ſo, and wil ſeeme too be very well appointed, but when neede is their hearte faileth them: and they which are well entred, for the moſte part lye downe for wearineſſe in the middeſt of the way. This leſſon therefore of digging pittes, is ſo much the more to be remembred of vs: that is to ſay, that we ſeeke the meanes which are yet hidden from vs, that we may goe on forwardes. Let vs I ſay en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force our ſelues and ſtriue aboue all humane ſtrength, If thinges fall not out to our deſire, let vs not therfore geue ouer, to follow with pacience, that happie courſe wherein God hath ſet vs. It is certaine that when wee ſhall cal vpon the name of God in true faith, that hee can eaſily turne theſe dry deſertes, intoo running wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: but in the meane time it is meete that wee accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our duetie, put our handes as they ſay too the worke. For God woulde not that wee ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine blockiſhe and ſlouthful, without remoouing either hand or foote, Rather he commaundeth vs too digge pittes. Let vs therfore trauaile too digge vntill that wee haue acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed our iourney. Let vs ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes the poore miſerable Souldiers, who eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie moneth ſel their life for a certayn price as for their wages. If they be in the campe what pouerty do they endure?
<pb facs="tcp:7693:55"/> If they be beſieged in any place, they yet indure much more greeuous thinges: If they vndertake any voyage, there is neither cold nor heat, wind nor raine, that may let them of, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the enterpriſe they haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hand. And ſometimes they are brought to ſuche exremitie, that vnleſſe they digge too finde water, they haue not a droppe to drinke. There is no labour diſtreſſe or miſerie, which they will not ſuffer for the perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunce of that which they haue vndertaken. And yet when they haue doone all, whether they eſcape or no, they haue but loſt theyr labour, becauſe they haue but ſerued Satan.<note place="margin">This is to bee vnderſtoode of euil &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked ſouldiers, that haue not the feare of GOD before their eyes.</note> The ſonne of God through his infinite grace hath choſen vs to be his ſouldiers: &amp; we know what reward he hath prepared for vs. How muche more couragious then ought we to bee in his ſeruice? the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe miſerable &amp; deſperate men, that do but pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe their own deſtruction? Neither is this me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned heere that any man ſhould reckon how many miles there is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his houſe to the place where he may freely worſhip God, make confeſſion of his faith, and heare the pure doctrine of the Goſpell: We haue yet to goe a farre longer iourney which laſteth all our lyfe long. Haue we haunted the Church of GOD a yeere or more? If we continue, we ſhall dayly finde new cares. For ſometimes we ſhalbe viſited with ſickneſſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with pouertie, eyther our wiues or children, ſhall die, or elſe the meanes wee haue too ſerue God ſhalbe taken away as before time, &amp; we ſhall be toſſed with diſquietneſſe and ſundry troubles. Wherefore it is very requiſite that euen vnto the end we haue our handes ready too digge Pittes, and our nayles too ſcratch the earth, if neceſſitie ſo require. If any man al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leadge, how then? are we not in the Temple of God? I
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7693:55"/> aunſweare that we are ſo in it, as we muſt come euery day nearer &amp; nearer vnto it, &amp; enter into it. True it is that wee daylye beholde the face of God, but wee are not yet ſo fully ſatiſfied therewith, as wee ſhall bee whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhalbe gathered vnto him. Wherfore it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that all generally apply this to their vſe, &amp; becauſe Satan ceaſeth not to hinder al thoſe that go vnto God, let euery one enforce himſelfe, too continue conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too doo that too morrow which he hath doone to day. For if the enimie ceaſe not too endeuour to driue vs backe from our courſe towardes GOD, muche leſſe ought we too looſe our courage to ſet our ſelues forward, and continually without ceaſing gather new ſtrength. But to the end we may do this thing, it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that we haue ſuch an affection wel printed in our heartes as Dauid had: <hi>I had rather</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>dwell at the threſholde of Gods houſe, then in the Tentes and Tabernacles of the wicked:</hi> Wherein he plainely declareth that to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe this benefit, to dwel in the houſe of God, he will accounte it no euill too be abaſed and made the moſte deſpiſed in the worlde. Let vs conſider I beſeech you, what his eſtate was. He was the kinges ſonne in lawe and one of the chiefe Princes in the Countrey, and yet notwithſtanding hee is content too bee ſet behinde, and put among the baſeſt ſort of the common people, vppon condition too haue ſome little corner in the Churche of God. If this deſire raigned in all, they woulde not make ſo much adoe too ridde them ſelues and ſpende ſo long time in bargening for exchaunge they haue too make, in forſaking their houſes and Countrey to come to the Church of God. But there are very fewe founde, whiche can take in hande and willingly beare the diminiſhing of their ſubſtaunce,
<pb facs="tcp:7693:56"/> euery man doth greatly deſire, nicely to be caried in a horſelitter where he may worſhip god at libertie, and he would haue both la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds &amp; poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, trading of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, credite, kinred and friendeſhip, and all other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities of this life, by &amp; by to follow. But whiles they are at this point, I pray you how eſteeme they Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt? For all that euer they wil do, at his deſire is but as it were by way of paſtime: which is but a very poore &amp; ſeely conſideration. For albeit we be nothing woorth indeede, yet hath he of his infinite goodnes ſo greatly eſtemed vs, that he hath not ſpared him for our ſaluation: yea I ſay him in whom conſiſteth the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all our felicitie. And ſhall we in the meane time grudge &amp; repine to forgo ſome tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitorie things, and to account our eſtate &amp; condition worſe, if we be not ſo wel handled &amp; entreated &amp; haue our pleaſures as before? This is verie far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> following that which S. Paule hath ſhewed vs by his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: that is, that we ſhould count all things as filth &amp; dung that doth hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſſeſſing of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; that we ſhould forſake it as a hurtful thing, knowing that whatſoeuer ſeparateth vs from the true life muſt needes drawe vs vnto death. This alſo is far of from folowing that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation which is made vnto vs by Ieſus Chriſt, that we ſhould ſel &amp; forſake al that we haue in this world for the kingdome of heauen, knowing that this is that precious ſtone, that is a hundred thouſand times more worth then al thoſe things that men ſo much deſire &amp; ſo greatly eſteeme. If any man wil obiect that a man may come to the kingdome of heauen, without forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his houſe: I anſwere that it is not without cauſe that our Sauior Chriſt doth thus name the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the goſpel. They therefore that are deſtitute
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7693:56"/> therof &amp; make not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt aſmuch as is poſsible to ſel e thoſe meanes wherby they may enioy it, ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that they are too carnally affected to the pelfe of this world, &amp; are not yet diſpoſed to exchange them with the kingdom of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But if they might poſſeſſe both togither, I would not enuie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but if they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not hold their poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; neſtle ſtil in their neaſtes, vnles they wil defraude the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues of the fode of the children of God: yea if they cannot maintaine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues in the ſtate wherin they are, without cutting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the churche, it is meete for them to regard that neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty which god hath laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They may eaſily bring forth ſuch excuſes as theſe, but al theſe ſhal ſtand the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in no ſteed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that great Iudge ſhal thunder vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe with his terrible voice that ſet more ſtore by that earthly life that is commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs with brute beaſtes, then by the euerlaſting inheritaunce which hee hath appointed for his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And it is a very ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thing that many imagine to ſtop our mouth, vnleſſe we do aſſigne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome meanes &amp; ſtate wherby they may liue in ſeruing god. My conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (they wil ſay) is thus in my countrie: if I forſake it, what ſhal become of mee, or how ſhal I liue? As though god had appointed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that preach the Goſpel to be ſtewardes &amp; ouerſeers, to appoint euery man his ſtate &amp; his ordinarie, and to giue euerie one according to his worthineſſe &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie his certain pencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; wages? If we can helpe them by cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel or directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are bound to do it, yea thogh they do not requeſt it: but if we be not able, ſhal our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie therfore be loſt to teache euery man that which God hath comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him? But if they had wel lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and remembred this doctrine of Dauid, too loue better a little corner in the porch of the temple of god then the higheſt and moſte honourable places that they might chooſe amongeſt the vnfaithfull, they
<pb facs="tcp:7693:57"/> woulde neuer thinke ſo harde, and ſtand ſo doubtfull what waie were beſt too be taken. But this is the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe that they would holde all, and ſleepe in whole ſkinnes not ſuffering theyr riches or honours too bee diminiſhed in any point, nor forgoing their eaſe and delightes, that is too ſay, they cannot bow their necks nor bend their backes too beare Ieſus Chriſt. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleade and contende about the matter, aſmuch as they liſte, yet muſt they needes in the ende be condempned. Concerning ſuch as haue alredy forſaken theyr coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, that they might come too a place, where they might freely ſerue God, and where the trueth of the Goſpell might be faithfully preached vnto them, it is very neceſſary that they oftentimes call this ſentence to their remembrance, to the ende they may from day too day exerciſe them ſelues in the practice thereof, that they may be hartened in the continual vſe and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of it. For many thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs may come to paſſe with the time, and daily do, which may diſcourage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had a great zeale. They that ioyne themſelues to the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God, are not alwayes ſo receiued as they are woorthie. Order many times is ſo peruerted, that the worthieſt too be ſet forwarde, are ſet behinde. Suche temptation might indeede turne them backe from their ſaluation, cauſing them too leaue of the good courſe wherunto they were entred, were it not that they reſted contented rather too bee in the laſt, and moſte deſpiſed in the houſe of GOD then too bee quite ſhut out.</p>
            <p>Thus the good faithfull men indeede, not hauing all that they might well deſire, but contrariwiſe fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a great many troubles in forſaking theyr coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey learne to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with this onely word,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7693:57"/> yet are we in the houſe of God. Nowe let the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings deride aſmuch as they liſt, &amp; blaſe vs out in their pride as abiectes and outcaſtes: it is enough that God doth vs this honour, too account vs of his Pallace and of his ſanctuary. We ſee what paine ambitious fooles take that they may bee counted and reckoned of the familie and houſe of ſome Prince: and howe happy they reckon themſelues, if they may but come into the kitchin or Hall. Now when we ſhal be the verieſt abiectes in the worlde, yet ſo that we be of the churche of God, he leadeth vs too the moſt high and meruei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſecretes of his wiſedome with ſuche familiaritie as if a father ſhoulde communicate and open himſelfe too his children. And ſure we were very vnthankeful if this recompence ſhould not ſatiſfie vs. It is very true that the faithfull may well be tempted and prouoked when their affaires ſhall goe backwarde, and that the wicked ſhall triumphe in all proſperitie. But when they ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider on the other ſide, that God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen them too be of his houſe, and that hee entertaineth them there as his children, this conſolation ſhall bee woorth litle, if it be not ſufficient to appeaſe all the griefes and enimities wherewith they may bee trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. And certainly they that murmure and vexe them ſelues, becauſe they are not entreated of God as they deſire, or repente themſelues for hauing begun wel, ſhew plainely that they haue not followed the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile of our lord Ieſus, which is, that they ſhould haue made theyr thorowe accounte, when they begin their building, what it will coſt them to make an end of it: to the ende: they vexe not themſelues for hauing ſpent too much, and ſo by this meanes leaue the worke im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. Which is worſt the moſt part of thoſe which
<pb facs="tcp:7693:58"/> ſo faynt in the middeſt of the way, do leaue of with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe: wherin they ſhew themſelues moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent. For they which had neither houſe nor lande, and with whom it was all one, either to dwel in their own Countrey, or in the fartheſt part of the world, yet they are not aſhamed to vpbraid God, that they haue left this and that for his ſake. But yet let vs put the caſe that they had loſt much of their ſubſtance for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles ſake: yet notwithſtanding it is a very mockery, more to eſteeme a dandiprat them a golde noble. In the meane ſeaſon nothing is hearde but theſe murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and complaintes: and would to God that ſuche people were farre away from vs, at theyr owne caſe. And yet notwithſtanding there are neither poore nor rich that haue any iuſt excuſe too fall away for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions whiche happen vntoo them, by following God. But becauſe this is a very hard thing, the remedy is ſhewed vnto vs in the 84. Pſalm, where Dauid, after he had ſaide,<note place="margin">Pſalm. <hi>84.</hi> b.</note> 
               <hi>that the man is bleſſed that hopeth in God,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by and by, <hi>in whoſe heart are his wayes.</hi> As if he wold ſay, he that hath his minde wholy bent too walke as God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him. Loe therefore two thinges which cannot be ſeparated the one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other: that we haue our hope in god, &amp; that we walk in the right path. Wherefore as our infirmitie doth let vs, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs ſo laſie, that we could be content at al aſſaies to turne another way, let vs fortifie our ſelues in faith, &amp; hope, praying our good God, that hee will make vs ſo to looke vnto him, that nothing trouble vs, whileſt wee truſte in his promiſes, whereby hee hath aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs that he will be with vs for euer both in life and in death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:7693:58"/>
            <head>An expoſition vpon the <hi>87.</hi> Pſalme.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>The Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee ſee that when all thinges goe well with the Children of this worlde, howe they pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their owne ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, &amp; how proudly they aduance themſelues in deſpiſing the Church of GOD: and although they bee often times tamed by affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: yet can they not forgette this ſo fooliſhe ouerweening arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, ſo to pleaſe themſelues in the tranſitorie trumperie of the earth. In the meane ſeaſon, they care not greatly for religion, nor for the ſeruice of God: forſomuch as delighting themſelues with their vaine delightes, riches, commodities, pompes and honors they thinke themſelues happy without the helpe of God.</p>
               <p>Now it falleth out oftentimes, that God handleth ſuch people according too their deſires, as if hee would euen fat them vp, vntil the due time of puniſhing them be come: and contrariwiſe he affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth his Churche with many aduerſities, and handleth it wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full roughly: or rather leaueth it too languiſh in a poore and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable condition: in ſuch ſort that it might thinke it ſelfe moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy: at the leaſt it is ſubiect too the ſcoffing and biting ſlaunders of worldlinges. To the ende therefore that the faithfull be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, with ſuch an outward ſhew, it is needefull for them too be drawen too a more high conſideration: too the ende they may hold that for vndoubted, which is ſaide in the <hi>33.</hi> Pſal. ver. <hi>12.</hi> that that people is bleſſed, which hath the Lord for their God. And this is the ſumme of this preſent Pſalme, too ſhewe that there is but one onely Churche of God, which excelleth in dignitie and excellency all the kingdomes and common wealthes of the earth, becauſe that it hath God, for the Tutor and Keeper of the ſaluation thereof.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:59"/> And becauſe it is vnder his hand and leading, yea too the end that amongest the horrible tempeſtes, troubles and chaunges wherewith the worlde is continually ſhaken, it may remaine conſtant and ſtand faſt, and principally I that being ſo miraculouſly ſaued through the grace of God, it may couragiouſly goe on too the battell; vntyll that it attaine too that crowne of glory which is laide vp for it on high. And this vndoubtedly is a ſingular benefite of GOD, and a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle woorthie neuer too bee forgotten, that amongeſt ſo many alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and chaunges of the kingdomes of the worlde, hee continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his churche from age too age, and neuer ſuffereth it too be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed. But becauſe that oftentimes, whiles the vnbeleeuers abound in riches, and flooriſhe in credite and authoritie, the poore Churche of God is toſſed hyther and thyther, with many daungers and infinit ſhipwrackes, yea which is more, is oftentimes ſeene as it were ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp: altogeather like as a Boate which is euen ready too bee drowned: the felicitie thereof conſiſteth principally in that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting eſtate which God hath laid vp for it in his kingdome.</p>
               <p>The circumſtance of the time wherein this Pſalme was made ſerueth vs very much, the better too make vs too vnderſtande it. For although the people were then returned from Babylon, where it had been long time holden Captiue, although that the Churche were gathered as it were into one bodye, too bee no more ſo ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as it had beene: although that the temple were builded and the Altar ſet vp, thereupon to offer vp ſacrifices, and all the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God reſtored: Neuertheleſſe becauſe there was but one handful of people returned into the holy lande, in reſpect of the great multitude that went out of it: and of that that remained, was dayly diminiſhed through the violences and outrages of the enimi-mies: in ſuch ſort that the ſtate of the people was very conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptible: and alſo becauſe the temple had no ſuch maieſtie as it had before: All this maketh that the faithfull coulde haue no great hope, for the time is come. And ſurely it ſeemeth impoſſible that euer they ſhoulde be reſtored too theyr former ſtate from whence they were fallen. Wherefore it was very daungerous, leaſt in calling too re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance theyr diſcomfiture and ouerthrow, and thinking alſo of ſo many euilles wherwith they ceaſed not too bee oppreſſed, that they had not beene ſhaken, and in the ende had not fallen too vtter
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7693:59"/> deſpayre. The ende therefore of this Pſalme is too comfort them, that they might not be diſcouraged in theyr miſeries. And the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to bring this to paſſe, God promiſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they ſhal not onely recouer that which they had loſt, but alſo lifteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp into a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hope, too wit, of an incomparable glory, as alſo it had beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed vnto them by their Prophet Aggeus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Agge.</hi> 2.10</note> that the maieſtie of the ſeconde Temple ſhoulde bee greater then that of the firſt.</p>
               <p>It remayneth nowe that we applie this Pſalme to our vſe, God woulde that this conſolation, ſhoulde be of ſuch power and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce towardes the faithfull of that time, that not onely it might reforme them, to the ende they might not be oppreſſed with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny euilles: but that it ſhoulde as a man woulde ſaye haue drawen them out of the graue, to haue lifted them vppe, euen to Heauen. Nowe foraſmuch as we know, that the thinges which were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde of that time were accompliſhed, we are more then vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if the experience which our auncient Fathers had, beyng ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the promiſes of God, doe not ſuffiſe to confirme our faith ſo much the more. For it cannot be ſufficiently expreſſed in wordes, howe Ieſus Chriſt with his comming hath adorned and magnified his Church. For then the true religion, which was ſhut vp, til that time in the countrie of Iewrie, was ſpread abroade througheout the whole worlde: and God which before was onely knowen of one onely race, began nowe to be called vpon in all tongues and thorow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out all nations. Then the worlde which before had beene ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably diſtracted &amp; as it were torne in peeces with ſo many ſects, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, &amp; ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, was vnited &amp; knit into one holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord of faith. Then all people acquainted them ſelues of very feruent deſire, with the Iewes, whom before they greatly abhorred and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. Alſo kinges and people, of theyr owne accord, willingly yeelded themſelues too be ſubiect to Ieſus Chriſte. Wolues and Lions were chaunged into lambes. God powred out vpon the faithful the gifts of the holy Ghoſte, which excelled all the glory of the worlde. And this was a thing ſo much the more wonderfull, that the body of the Church which was gathered together and compounded of ſo many diuers members, and which were ſeparated the one from the other, by farre diſtaunt Countreis that yet notwithſtanding that hee ſo encreaſed &amp; mainteined the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherefore it muſt needes be alſo that
<pb facs="tcp:7693:60"/> God wrought mightily, in multiplying the preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel in ſo ſhort a time, and in making it ſo wonderfully to fructifie and to profite. Wherefore although that the nobilitie and dignity of the Church, had neuer bin ſet foorth in this preſent Pſalme, yet notwithſtanding the incomparable graces which GOD diſplayed foorth at the comming of his Sonne, ſheweth that the Churche is truely, an heauenly, &amp; not an earthly kingdome. Moreouer it muſt needes be that this be that preſent time, wherein God ſo magnified and made the ſtate of his Church too ſhine, that the faithfull, the better to eſteeme the worthineſſe of it, looke more high then mans reaſon and vnderſtanding can attayn vnto. For fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the time that it ſo flooriſhed as wee haue ſayde, it had no pompe neither of Golde, nor ſiluer, nor pretious ſtones: but rather her triumphes were in the blood of Martyres: and as ſhe was riche in ſpirite, ſo ſhee was naked and poore concerning the mucke of the worlde: as ſhee was precious and beautifull in holineſſe, before God and his Angelles, ſo ſhe was contemptible in the worlde. She had many outward and ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enemies who cruelly perſecuted her: or rather did miſcheuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuiſe to caſt her headlodg vnder the earth. There were many traynes and platformes layed: as the Diuell will neuer ceaſe to moleſt to entrappe her by Hypocrites. To be ſhort the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie thereof was euermore hidden vnder the Croſſe of Chriſt. On the other ſide a man might eaſily iudge, that all the woorthines which ſhee hath, is ſpirituall, ſo as ſhe cannot be ſeene with car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall eye. Wherefore the conſolation which is contayned here cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to be very meete and ſeaſonable for this time: to the ende the faithfull may be warned, to thinke vppon a more perfecte ſtate of the Churche, then that which is apparaunt vnto them. But this is verye neceſſarye for vs at this day. It is longe ſithens that for the ſinnes of our Fathers, GOD ſuffered this noble and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſtate whiche hee had erected in his Churche, too bee diſfigured, and placed in ſteade thereof an horrible deſolation. And yet euen at this time, the poore Churche is woonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppreſſed by our tranſgreſſions, and mourneth vnder the cruell Tyranny of the aduerſaries of his trueth, vnder the ſlaunders and reproches of her enimies, and vnder the moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keries of the Deuil, and of wicked men: in ſuche ſorte that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7693:60"/> there is nothing that the worldlinges, who deſire to be at their caſe doe more ſhunne, then to bee holden and accompted of the number and companye of the Faithfull: whereof it commeth that the moſte parte ſeparate themſelues from the Churche, as thoughe men coulde not bee of it vnleſſe they were moſt vnhappie and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed. Whereupon it is eaſie for vs too gather howe profitable the doctrine of this preſente Pſalme is vnto vs to the ende wee might without ceaſſing me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate vppon it.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Pſalme 87. Ver. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <q>To the ſonnes of Chorah, a Pſalme and a Songue: The fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations thereof are laide amongeſt the Mountaynes of his holineſſe.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE naming of the ſonnes of Chorah, do not ſo much ſhewe that they were the authours of this Pſalme, as that they were ſpeciall Muſitions appointed too ſing in the Temple. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit it might bee ſaide alſo; that ſome of this familie, was the Authour thereof. Concerning the Texte where it is ſaid, <hi>that the foundations thereof are layd amongſt the holy hilles:</hi> this muſt bee applied vntoo God. For it is a common manner of ſpeache amongeſt the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues too put the Relatiue before the Name of him of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion is made. The meaning therfore is this. That he hath laid his fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thoſe holy hilles.
<pb facs="tcp:7693:61"/> Many haue vnderſtood this of the Temple: but this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth not. Others vnderſtande it of the Pſalme as-though it were ſaide that the argument or matter of this Pſalme is too entreate of thoſe holy mountaynes where the Temple was builded: but this is no more agreeable then the former. But as I haue alreadie ſaide the purpoſe of the Prophet is to ſhowe that God hath choſen the holy mountaines, to the ende he may there build his royal Cittie Ieruſalem and his Temple. For it followeth a little after in the text <hi>that the moſt higheſt ſhal eſtabliſh it.</hi> It is very certaine that God is the true &amp; principall founder of all the Cities in the world: but this ſo excellent a title is not attributed too any other Citie but to Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it ſhould be the euerlaſting reſting place of God, and that he wil dwel there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he hath choſen it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.3.</note> We muſte alwayes note this difference, that other Cities were not builded by the power and authoritie of God, vnleſſe it were for their earthly pollicie: but that Ieruſalem was his ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary, and that he had ſpecially choſen it as it were the ſeate of his maieſtie. And ſo alſo doth the Prophet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay ſpeake thereof: <hi>What ſhall the meſſengers of the people ſay? it is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 14.32.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Lord hath founded Syon.</hi> Which is more, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that al the Countrie of Iudea was dedicated vnto him, yet it is ſaide that caſting al other aſide, hee hath reſerued this Citie of Ieruſalem to himſelfe that he may raigne there: and this is that whiche foloweth in the ſecond verſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Verſe. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </bibl> The Lord loueth the gates of Syon aboue al the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles of Iacob.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Too which agreeth that which is ſaide in the 78. Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.60.</note> that God hath reiected Siloh the trybe of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7693:61"/> the tabernacle, of Ioſeph that he might dwell in Syon which he had loued, Let vs marke well alſo the cauſe which the Prophet mentioneth here, why God hath preferred one certaine place, before all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: to wit, not for the woorthineſſe of the place, but for the meere loue which he bare vnto it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any man aſke, whence this excellent priuiledge that Hieruſalem had came, that it ſhoulde be called the holy Citie of God, and his royall Pallace: the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is eaſie and ſhort, and that is becauſe it hath ſoo pleaſed God. This pleaſure is as it were, the fountain and roote of his loue. The end as he ſheweth was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would haue there ſome place, wherin his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold haue dwelling to noriſh an aſſured vnitie of faith amongeſt the Iewes, vntil the comming of our Lord Ieſus: and that in the end the Goſpell ſhould ſpring from thence, too be publiſhed throughout the whole worlde. And thus the Prophet to magnifie the Citie of Ieruſalem ſaith, that God is the founder ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that he there ruleth as the gouernour. But to the ende that men ſhoulde not take occaſion too be proud of ſuch an honour, he addeth and ſheweth, that all the excellencie which Ieruſalem hath, muſt be attributed too the meere grace and adoption of God. In that hee putteth Syon for the whole Citie, and the gates for the whole wal and compaſſe of the Citie, it is by taking a part for the whole. By the mountaines, wherof he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth in the plural nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, they vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; Moriah, which butted either vpon other. Now although I doo not vtterly reiect this expoſition, yet me thinkes one might extend this worde further: too wit, to the whole region. For Ieruſalem was ſituated among mountaines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="verse">
               <pb facs="tcp:7693:62"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Ver. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </bibl> Wonderfull thinges are ſpoken of thee, thou Citie of God. Selah.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Worde for worde it is, that that which is ſaide in thee, are wonderfull thinges. But we haue to marke the purpoſe of the Prophet, or rather that which the holy Ghoſt would here ſpeake by the Prophet. The condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the people of the Iewes, was at this time very conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptible, ſo as there was ſmal account made of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They had many great and greeuous enimies on euery ſide which vexed them, and but few had the courage to put backe offences. Euery day there fell out, newe alterations beyond all hope of men: in ſuch ſorte that it ſeemed, that after thinges went ſo to wracke &amp; waxed worſe and woorſe, that all in the ende ſhoulde come to vtter ruine, in ſuche ſort that any man coulde hardly hope that euer the Citie of Ieruſalem ſhoulde be reſtored againe. Now to the ende that the heartes of the faithfull ſhoulde not bee vtterly ſwalowed vp with heauineſſe and diſpaire, they are here by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, ſet to leane vpon that woorde which God had pronounced of the eſtate of his Church to come: for there is no doubt but that the holy Ghoſte withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the faithfull in this place from the beholding of things preſent, to the ende he might bring them vntoo the promiſes, which did aſſure them of an incredible glory that God woulde ſhortly geue too his Church. So then howſoeuer the thing that appeareth, ſerue not to make the children of God reioice, yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Prophet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to lift vp their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on high, by the vertue of that worde the which is geuen vnto them: too the ende they might patiently wayte vntil thoſe thinges which had beene promiſed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7693:62"/> vnto them ſhould be executed and perfourmed. On this manner they were admoniſhed and exhorted too reade diligently and to meditate day and night, thoſe auncient propheſies which concerned the reſtoring of the Church: and ſpecially thoſe which were conteined in the booke of Eſay from the 40. chap. vnto the ende of the booke. Further that they ſhould reach out their care and diligently hearken, geuing faith and credit to the Prophets, which were ſent at that time to comfort them and to preache vnto them the kingdome of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte which was neare: wherevpon it foloweth that wee can not iudge aright of the felicitie of the Churche, vnleſſe wee iudge of it by the woorde of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Ver. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </bibl> I will rehearſe Rahab and Babylon amongeſt them that knowe mee: beholde Paleſtine and Tyrus, with Aethiopia, he was borne there.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The name of Rahab is put aſwell in other places of the Scripture for Egypt: and here it very well agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to this ſentence: For the Prophetes minde is too deſcribe the excellente and glorious eſtate of the Churche whiche then was hid. Hee ſayth therefore that they who before had beene deadly enimies, or were altogeather ſtraungers vnto it, ſhoulde not onely bee her familiar freendes but as it were engraffed into one body, too the ende too bee accounted for Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens of Hieruſalem. I will put (ſayth hee) intoo myne accounte, or I will enrowle Egypt and Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, amongeſt my famyliars or houſholde ones. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee addeth that the Philiſtines they of Tyre and
<pb facs="tcp:7693:63"/> Ethiopia, who hithertoo had had great diſcorde with the people of God, ſhoulde bee vntoo him as good friendes, as if they were the naturall borne of Iewry. Now in ſpeaking ſo therof he ſpecifieth a ſingular dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the Churche of GOD: and that is that they which did deſpiſe it, and did wiſhe it too bee vtterly raſed and deſtroied, ſhoulde gather themſelues round about vntoo it, yea, and ſhould account it for a great honour too be enrouled and acknowledged amongeſt his people. For the Prophet ſignifieth that all of their owne accorde, ſhoulde renounce their owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Countreyes, wherein tofore they put all their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. This is therefore aſmuch as if he ſhoulde ſay, that from what quarter ſoeuer men were borne, were it in Paleſtine, in Tyre or Ethiopia, they ſhoulde be gladde and well a paide too be numbred with the people of God and acknowledged for Citizens of Ieruſalem. The Rabbines of the Iewes, make a crooked gloſe of this place, that is, that from other nations of the worlde, there ſhall come very fewe excellent men, in witte or vertue: but that in their race there ſhall be a great number. As though it were ſaide that there wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be hardly found a man woorthy of praiſe in any coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. So as they may bee pointed at which are ſuche with the finger: But that in Sion there ſhalbe great abundaunce. The Chriſtian Doctours with one conſent apply this to our Lorde Ieſus, and they think that the reaſon is here rendred, why the ſtraungers yea the enimies of the Churche ſhall deſire too be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graffed and inrowled therein, too wit, becauſe the ſonne of God ſhalbe borne there, whoſe office it is too gather men which were diſperſed into an holy vnitie of faith, &amp; to heape the ſcattered members togeather
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7693:63"/> too make one whole bodie thereof. Nowe this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence indeede is very true in it ſelfe: but it agreeth not vnto the place. And we muſt alwaies diligently take heede that the Scripture vnder colour of ſubtiltie bee not racked too any other ſenſe then it ought. Let it ſuffiſe vs therefore too haue the plaine and ſimple ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition thereof, that euerye one may deſire it for a great benefit, to be receiued a Citizen of the Church. The which is yet more fully confirmed by that which followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Ver <hi>5.</hi>
                     </bibl> And of Syon it ſhalbe ſaide, this and that man is borne in it: and the moſt higheſt ſhall eſtabliſh it.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>As I haue ſaide already the Prophet continueth his ſentence minding to ſignifie, that God ſhal gather peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple togeather af all Countries of the worlde, too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate them into his Churche, as newe burgeſſes and Citizens. Albeit that he vſe an other manner of ſpeaking, it is becauſe ſtrangers ſhalbe reputed among the holy people of GOD, as if they were deſcended of the ſtocke of Abraham. He had ſaide in the former verſe, that the Chaldeans and Egyptians ſhould yeelde themſelues to become of the houſhold of the church-that the Ethyopians, Philiſtines, &amp; the men of Tyre, ſhoulde deſire too bee enrowled in the number of his Children: nowe hee addeth for confirmation of his ſentence that the troupe ſhalbe great and infinite, too repleniſh the Citie of Heruſalem, whiche for a time was deſolate, and to make it moſt populous: or rather which had been inhabited but euen of an handfull of men in compariſon of the people which ſhould arriue there. That which is heere briefely promiſed is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:7693:64"/> more at large in the Prophet Eſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 54..1</note> when he ſaith, <hi>Reioyce ô barren that diddeſt not beare, for the widowe ſhall haue moe children then ſhee who hath a huſbande. Enlarge the place of thy tentes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 60.4</note> 
                  <hi>and let them ſpread out the cordes &amp;c. Alſo thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall come from all farre cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries: lift vp thine eyes rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thee, all thoſe ſhalbe gathered together vnto thee.</hi> And in the 44. Chapter he vſeth the ſame maner of ſpeach that we reade here,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 44.5.</note> or at the leaſt which draweth very neere vnto it. <hi>One ſhall ſay, I am of the Lord: another ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be called by the name of Iſrael: and another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hande, I am the Lordes: and others ſhall call themſelues by the name of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither is it without cauſe that the Prophete v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this woorde of byrth, ſignifying thereby that the Chaldeans, the Aegyptians, and ſuch like ſhould be ioyned to the flocke of God. For albeit they were not by birth, of Syon, and the naturall children, but onely through adoption muſt bee incorporated into the bodie of the holy people: Yet becauſe our entrie into the Church is as a ſecond byrth, this ſimilitude is very apte and agreeable, And indeede Ieſus Chriſte plighteth and marrieth himſelfe with the Faithful vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this condition,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 45.11. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.5.16.</note> that they ſhoulde forgette, their owne people, and the houſe of their Father. And this is the cauſe why Saint Paule ſayeth that wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne too bee the Children of GOD and of the Churche, when wee are borne anewe, of incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Seede, and are made newe Creatures. And ſurely wee are not otherwiſe regenerate into the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly life then by the Miniſterie of the Churche. In the meane time let vs call too remembraunce the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7693:64"/> difference that Sainte Paule putteth here betwixt the earthly Hieruſalem, which as it is a ſeruaunt, cannot but bring foorth children into bondage: and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, which conceaueth and bringeth forth children into libertie through the Goſpel. In the ende of the verſe, there is a promiſe of the long continuance of the Church: for oftentimes it commeth to paſſe that Cities, the ſooner they creepe vppe, into ſuddaine ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and greatneſſe, the ſhorter while they continue in their proſperitie. To the ende therefore that men thinke not the felicitie of the Churche too bee ſo tranſitorie, the Prophete declareth that ſhee ſhal haue her ſtabilitie in GOD, and that therefore ſhee ſhall continue. As though he ſhoulde ſay, it is no maruaile though other Cities be alwayes ſhaken, and ſubiect to many alterations: becauſe they are toſſed with the worlde, and haue not euerlaſting keepers. But the condition of this newe Hieruſalem ſhalbe otherwiſe: for her perpetuitie being founded in God, ſhall ſtand ſure, though Heauen and Earth ſhoulde fall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>er. 6.</bibl> The Lorde ſhall enrowle his people by writing: he was borne there. Selah.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The Prophete meaneth that the name of Syon, ſhall bee ſo Noble and Honourable, that euerie one ſhall deſire too bee receaued there for a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen. For hee ſpeaketh of the principall benefite, and of a thing the moſte too bee wiſhed for that euer coulde happen. The meaning therefore is thus:
<pb facs="tcp:7693:65"/> when God ſhall take accounte of his people, or ſhall enrowle them, the greateſt benefite and honour that he can doe vnto his beſt beloued, ſhalbe too accounte them for Citizens of Syon, rather then of any other Citie. For this ſhalbe a greater dignitie, to haue ſome corner among the common people of the Churche, then to be greately eſteemed or too rule in any other place. Notwithſtanding the Prophete admoniſheth vs, from whence it is that ſuche a benefite proceedeth, that they which were ſtraungers ſhould ſo ſodenly be brought into the Church: to wit of the free gifte of God. And in deed they which are the ſlaues of Sathan and of ſinne can neuer gette by their owne diligence any ſuch title and right to be Citizens of heauen. It is therefore God onely which diſtributeth according to his owne good pleaſure, peoples in their orders, &amp; ſeuereth them one from the other, as it ſeemeth good vnto him: foraſmuch as the condition is equall and alike in all by nature. The enroulement whereof he ſpeaketh here, is too bee vnderſtood of the calling whereby God declareth who are thoſe that hee hath choſen. For although that hee hath written his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the booke of life, before the creation of the worlde, yet notwithſtanding hee ſolempnly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them downe in his regiſter, when hee geueth them the marke of his adoption, calling them to his trueth and renuing them by his ſpirite.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>verſ. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </bibl> As well the fingers as the Players on inſtrumentes, all my ſpringes are in thee.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Partly the ſhortnes of this ſentence, cauſeth it to be doubtful, &amp; partly the doubtfull ſignification of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7693:65"/> worde. All expoſitors agree very well in this, that the worde ſpring or fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine is taken hereby a Metaphor or ſimilitude. But one ſort apply it to the affection of the heart, other ſome to the inward thoughtes. There are alſo whiche tranſlate it Veines or Melodies, whoſe opinion I would wel allow of, if the propriety of the Hebrwe tongue woulde ſuffer it: but becauſe that this is ſomewhat wreſted, I tye my ſelfe to that which is more proper and naturall: and that is, that the Prophet by this woorde ſignifieth the eyes or the looke. As if he ſhould ſay, I haue alwayes my ſight fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and faſtened vpon thee. For the roote of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word ſignifieth an eye. It remaineth therfore to ſee, what that other member ſignifieth <hi>aſwell the fingers as the players on inſtruments.</hi> This is a very abrupt ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but this letteth not but that men may eaſily gather the meaning therof: to wit, that there ſhalbe ſo large an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ioy in the church, after that it ſhalbe reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the prayſes of God, ſhall ſounde foorth, there without ceaſing, aſwel of the voyce as of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of muſick. He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmeth therefore that which he had ſaide before of that glorious repayring of Sion and of Hieruſalem: thereby ſhewing that for the great felicitie which ſhalbe there, men ſhal haue occaſion to reioyſe, too ſing, and too prayſe God for euer. In the meane ſeaſon he ſheweth alſo to what end and purpoſe God ſo liberally enricheth his Church with his giftes and graces: to wit, that the faithfull might ſhew forth by hymnes and prayſes and ſonges, that they are not vnthankeful towardes him: On the other ſide wee haue to note the zeale, the loue, and carefulneſſe, and affection of the Prophet toward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>che. For he geueth teſtimony thereof, too the end to exhort vs
<pb facs="tcp:7693:66"/> al too followe hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> example, as it is ſayde in an other place, let my right hande be forgotten if Hieruſalem be not the chiefe of my ioy. Now then all our ſenſes and affections reſt them ſelues in the Church,<note place="margin">Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> when as we labour too withdrawe them from the vanities of this world, which cauſe them to wander and ſtray. The which thing is doone, when in deſpiſing of the honours, delightes, riches, and pompes of this worlde, we learne too content our ſelues with that ſpirituall glory of the kingdome of Chriſte.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London at the <hi>three Cranes in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inetree, by</hi> Thomas Dawſon, for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1579.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7693:66"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
